The Chapter on Abuse

AN 10.41 Dispute Vivādasutta

Then Venerable Upāli went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“What is the cause, sir, what is the reason, why fights, quarrels, arguments, and disputes arise in the Saṅgha, and the mendicants don’t live happily?”

“Upāli, it’s when a mendicant explains what is not the teaching as the teaching, and what is the teaching as not the teaching. They explain what is not the training as the training, and what is the training as not the training. They explain what was not spoken and stated by the Realized One as spoken and stated by the Realized One, and what was spoken and stated by the Realized One as not spoken and stated by the Realized One. They explain what was not practiced by the Realized One as practiced by the Realized One, and what was practiced by the Realized One as not practiced by the Realized One. They explain what was not prescribed by the Realized One as prescribed by the Realized One, and what was prescribed by the Realized One as not prescribed by the Realized One. This is the cause, this is the reason why fights, quarrels, arguments, and disputes arise in the Saṅgha, and the mendicants don’t live happily.”

AN 10.42 Roots of Dispute (1st) Paṭhamavivādamūlasutta

“Sir, how many roots of dispute are there?”

“Upāli, there are ten roots of dispute. What ten? It’s when a mendicant explains what is not the teaching as the teaching, and what is the teaching as not the teaching. They explain what is not the training as the training, and what is the training as not the training. They explain what was not spoken and stated by the Realized One as spoken and stated by the Realized One, and what was spoken and stated by the Realized One as not spoken and stated by the Realized One. They explain what was not practiced by the Realized One as practiced by the Realized One, and what was practiced by the Realized One as not practiced by the Realized One. They explain what was not prescribed by the Realized One as prescribed by the Realized One, and what was prescribed by the Realized One as not prescribed by the Realized One. These are the ten roots of dispute.”

AN 10.43 Roots of Dispute (2nd) Dutiyavivādamūlasutta

“Sir, how many roots of dispute are there?”

“Upāli, there are ten roots of disputes. What ten? It’s when a mendicant explains what is not an offense as an offense, and what is an offense as not an offense. They explain a light offense as a heavy offense, and a heavy offense as a light offense. They explain a grave offense as a minor offense, and a minor offense as a grave offense. They explain a curable offense as an incurable offense, and an incurable offense as a curable offense. They explain an offense requiring amends as an offense not requiring amends, and an offense not requiring amends as an offense requiring amends. These are the ten roots of dispute.”

AN 10.44 At Kusinārā Kusinārasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Kusinārā in the Forest of Offerings. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, a mendicant who wants to accuse another should first check five things in themselves and establish five things in themselves. What five things should they check in themselves? A mendicant who wants to accuse another should check this: ‘Is my bodily behavior pure? Do I have pure bodily behavior that is impeccable and irreproachable? Is this thing found in me or not?’ If it’s not, there’ll be some who say: ‘Come on, venerable, train your own bodily behavior first.’

Furthermore, a mendicant who wants to accuse another should check this: ‘Is my verbal behavior pure? Do I have pure verbal behavior that is impeccable and irreproachable? Is this thing found in me or not?’ If it’s not, there will be people who say: ‘Come on, venerable, train your own verbal behavior first.’

Furthermore, a mendicant who wants to accuse another should check this: ‘Is my heart established in love for my spiritual companions, without resentment? Is this thing found in me or not?’ If it’s not, there will be people who say: ‘Come on, venerable, establish your heart in love for your spiritual companions first.’

Furthermore, a mendicant who wants to accuse another should check this: ‘Am I very learned, remembering and keeping what I’ve learned? These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. Am I very learned in such teachings, remembering them, rehearsing them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically? Is this thing found in me or not?’ If it’s not, there will be people who say: ‘Come on, venerable, memorize the scriptures first.’

Furthermore, a mendicant who wants to accuse another should check this: ‘Have both monastic codes been passed down to me in detail, well analyzed, well mastered, and well evaluated in both the rules and accompanying material? Is this thing found in me or not?’ If it’s not, and if they are unable to respond when asked “Venerable, where was this spoken by the Buddha?” there will be people who say: ‘Come on, venerable, train in the monastic code first.’ These are the five things they should check in themselves.

What five things should they establish in themselves? ‘I will speak at the right time, not at the wrong time. I will speak truthfully, not falsely. I will speak gently, not harshly. I will speak beneficially, not harmfully. I will speak lovingly, not from secret hate.’ These are the five things they should establish in themselves. A mendicant who wants to accuse another should first check these five things in themselves and establish these five things in themselves.”

AN 10.45 Entering a Royal Compound Rājantepurappavesanasutta

“Mendicants, there are ten drawbacks to entering a royal compound. What ten?

Firstly, a king is sitting with his chief queen when a monk enters. When the queen sees the monk she smiles, or when the monk sees the queen he smiles. So the king thinks: ‘They’ve done it for sure, or they will do it.’ This is the first drawback of entering a royal compound.

Furthermore, a king has many duties, and much to do. He has sex with one of the women but doesn’t remember. She gets pregnant from that. So the king thinks: ‘No-one else has entered here, except that monk. Could this be the monk’s doing?’ This is the second drawback of entering a royal compound.

Furthermore, a gem is lost somewhere in the royal compound. So the king thinks: ‘No-one else has entered here, except that monk. Could this be the monk’s doing?’ This is the third drawback of entering a royal compound.

Furthermore, secret deliberations in the royal compound are leaked outside. So the king thinks: ‘No-one else has entered here, except that monk. Could this be the monk’s doing?’ This is the fourth drawback of entering a royal compound.

Furthermore, in a royal compound, a father longs for their son, or a son longs for his father. They think: ‘No-one else has entered here, except that monk. Could this be the monk’s doing?’ This is the fifth drawback of entering a royal compound.

Furthermore, the king promotes someone to a higher position. Those who are upset by this think: ‘The king is close to that monk. Could this be the monk’s doing?’ This is the sixth drawback of entering a royal compound.

Furthermore, the king demotes someone to a lower position. Those who are upset by this think: ‘The king is close to that monk. Could this be the monk’s doing?’ This is the seventh drawback of entering a royal compound.

Furthermore, the king dispatches the army at the wrong time. Those who are upset by this think: ‘The king is close to that monk. Could this be the monk’s doing?’ This is the eighth drawback of entering a royal compound.

Furthermore, the king dispatches the army at the right time, but orders it to turn back while still on the road. Those who are upset by this think: ‘The king is close to that monk. Could this be the monk’s doing?’ This is the ninth drawback of entering a royal compound.

Furthermore, in the royal compound there is a trampling of elephants, horses, and chariots, as well as arousing sights, sounds, smells, tastes, and touches that do not befit a monk. This is the tenth drawback of entering a royal compound.

These are the ten drawbacks of entering a royal compound.”

AN 10.46 With the Sakyans Sakkasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sakyans, near Kapilavatthu in the Banyan Tree Monastery. Then on the sabbath several Sakyan lay followers went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to them:

“Sakyans, do you observe the sabbath with its eight factors?”

“Sir, sometimes we do, sometimes we don’t.”

“That’s your loss, Sakyans, it’s your misfortune. In this life with its fear of sorrow and death, you sometimes keep the sabbath and you sometimes don’t.

What do you think, Sakyans? Take a man who earns half a dollar for an honest day’s work. Is this enough to call him a deft and industrious man?”

“Yes, sir.”

“What do you think, Sakyans? Take a man who earns a dollar for an honest day’s work. Is this enough to call him a deft and industrious man?”

“Yes, sir.”

“What do you think, Sakyans? Take a man who, for an honest day’s work, earns two dollars … three dollars … four dollars … five dollars … six dollars … seven dollars … eight dollars … nine dollars … ten dollars … twenty dollars … thirty dollars … forty dollars … fifty dollars … a hundred dollars. Is this enough to call him a deft and industrious man?”

“Yes, sir.”

“What do you think, Sakyans? Suppose that man earned a hundred or a thousand dollars every day and saved it all up. If he lived for a hundred years, would he not accumulate a large mass of wealth?”

“Yes, sir.”

“What do you think, Sakyans? Would that man, on account of that wealth, experience absolute happiness for a single day or night, or even half a day or night?”

“No, sir.”

“Why is that?”

“Because sensual pleasures, sir, are impermanent, hollow, false, and deceptive.”

“But take one of my disciples who lives diligent, keen, and resolute for ten years, practicing in line with my instructions. They can experience absolute happiness for a hundred years, ten thousand years, or a hundred thousand years. And they could become a once-returner or a non-returner, or, as a sure bet, a stream-enterer. Let alone ten years, take one of my disciples who lives diligent, keen, and resolute for nine years … eight years … seven years … six years … five years … four years … three years … two years … one year … ten months … nine months … eight months … seven months … six months … five months … four months … three months … two months … one month … a fortnight … ten days … nine days … eight days … seven days … six days … five days … four days … three days … two days …

Let alone two days, take one of my disciples who lives diligent, keen, and resolute for one day, practicing in line with my instructions. They can experience absolute happiness for a hundred years, ten thousand years, or a hundred thousand years. And they could become a once-returner or a non-returner, or, as a sure bet, a stream-enterer. It’s your loss, Sakyans, it’s your misfortune. In this life with its fear of sorrow and death, you sometimes keep the sabbath and you sometimes don’t.”

“Well, sir, from this day forth we will observe the sabbath with its eight factors.”

AN 10.47 With Mahāli Mahālisutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof. Then Mahāli the Licchavi went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“What is the cause, sir, what is the reason for doing bad deeds, for performing bad deeds?”

“Greed is a cause, Mahāli, greed is a reason for doing bad deeds, for performing bad deeds. Hate is a cause of bad deeds … Delusion is a cause of bad deeds … Irrational application of mind is the cause of bad deeds … A wrongly directed mind is a cause of bad deeds … This is the cause, Mahāli, this is the reason for doing bad deeds, for performing bad deeds.”

“What is the cause, sir, what is the reason for doing good deeds, for performing good deeds?”

“Contentment is a cause, Mahāli, contentment is a reason for doing good deeds, for performing good deeds. Love is a cause of good deeds … Understanding is a cause of good deeds … Rational application of mind is the cause of good deeds … A rightly directed mind is a cause of good deeds … This is the cause, Mahāli, this is the reason for doing good deeds, for performing good deeds. If these ten things were not found in the world, we wouldn’t see either unprincipled and immoral conduct, or principled and moral conduct. But since these ten things are found in the world, we see both unprincipled and immoral conduct, and principled and moral conduct.”

AN 10.48 Ten Regular Reflections for a Renunciate Pabbajitaabhiṇhasutta

“Mendicants, one who has gone forth should often review these ten things. What ten?

One who has gone forth should often review this: ‘I have secured freedom from class.’

‘My livelihood is tied up with others.’

‘My behavior should be different.’

‘I hope there’s no reason to blame myself when it comes to ethical conduct?’

‘I hope that, after examination, sensible spiritual companions don’t reproach any aspect of my ethics?’

‘I must be parted and separated from all I hold dear and beloved.’

‘I am the owner of my deeds and heir to my deeds. Deeds are my womb, my relative, and my refuge.

I shall be the heir of whatever deeds I do, whether good or bad.’

‘As the days and nights pass by, what sort of person am I becoming?’

‘Do I love to stay in empty huts?’

‘Do I have any superhuman distinctions in knowledge and vision worthy of the noble ones, so that when my spiritual companions question me on my deathbed I will not be embarrassed?’

One who has gone forth should often review these ten things.”

AN 10.49 Existing Because of the Body Sarīraṭṭhadhammasutta

“Mendicants, these ten things exist because of the body. What ten? Cold, heat, hunger, thirst, feces, urine, restraint of body, speech, and livelihood, and the will to live that leads to future lives. These ten things exist because of the body.”

AN 10.50 Fights Bhaṇḍanasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. Now at that time, after the meal, on return from almsround, several mendicants sat together in the assembly hall. They were fighting, quarreling, and disputing, wounding each other with barbed words.

Then in the late afternoon, the Buddha came out of retreat and went to the assembly hall. He sat down on the seat spread out, and addressed the mendicants: “Mendicants, what were you sitting talking about just now? What conversation was left unfinished?”

“Sir, after the meal, on return from almsround, we sat together in the assembly hall, fighting, quarreling, and disputing, wounding each other with barbed words.”

“Mendicants, this is not appropriate for you gentlemen who have gone forth out of faith from the lay life to homelessness.

There are ten warm-hearted qualities that make for fondness and respect, conducing to inclusion, harmony, and unity, without dispute. What ten? Firstly, a mendicant is ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken. When a mendicant is ethical, this warm-hearted quality makes for fondness and respect, conducing to inclusion, harmony, and unity, without dispute.

Furthermore, a mendicant is very learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, rehearsing them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically. …

Furthermore, a mendicant has good friends, companions, and associates. …

Furthermore, a mendicant is easy to admonish, having qualities that make them easy to admonish. They’re patient, and take instruction respectfully. …

Furthermore, a mendicant is deft and tireless in a diverse spectrum of duties for their spiritual companions, understanding how to go about things in order to complete and organize the work. …

Furthermore, a mendicant loves the teachings and is a delight to converse with, being full of joy in the teaching and training. …

Furthermore, a mendicant lives with energy roused up for giving up unskillful qualities and embracing skillful qualities. They are strong, staunchly vigorous, not slacking off when it comes to developing skillful qualities. …

Furthermore, a mendicant is content with any kind of robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. …

Furthermore, a mendicant is mindful. They have utmost mindfulness and alertness, and can remember and recall what was said and done long ago. …

Furthermore, a mendicant is wise. They have the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. When a mendicant is wise, this warm-hearted quality makes for fondness and respect, helping the Saṅgha to live in harmony and unity, without quarreling.

These ten warm-hearted qualities make for fondness and respect, conducing to inclusion, harmony, and unity, without dispute.”

The Chapter on the Noble Path

AN 10.189 The Noble Path Ariyamaggasutta

“I will teach you the noble path and the ignoble path. … And what is the ignoble path? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called the ignoble path.

And what is the noble path? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the noble path.”

AN 10.190 The Dark Path Kaṇhamaggasutta

“I will teach you the dark path and the bright path. … And what is the dark path? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called the dark path.

And what is the bright path? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the bright path.”

AN 10.191 The True Teaching Saddhammasutta

“I will teach you what is the true teaching and what is not the true teaching. … And what is not the true teaching? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called what is not the true teaching.

And what is the true teaching? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the true teaching.”

AN 10.192 The Teaching of the True Persons Sappurisadhammasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the teaching of the true persons and the teaching of the untrue persons. And what is the teaching of the untrue persons? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is the teaching of the untrue persons.

And what is the teaching of the true persons? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is the teaching of the true persons.”

AN 10.193 Principles That Should Be Activated Uppādetabbadhammasutta

“I will teach you the principle to activate and the principle not to activate. … And what is the principle not to activate? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called the principle not to activate.

And what is the principle to activate? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the principle to activate.”

AN 10.194 Principles That Should Be Cultivated Āsevitabbadhammasutta

“I will teach you the principle to cultivate and the principle not to cultivate. … And what is the principle not to cultivate? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called the principle not to cultivate.

And what is the principle to cultivate? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the principle to cultivate.”

AN 10.195 Principles That Should Be Developed Bhāvetabbadhammasutta

“I will teach you the principle to develop and the principle not to develop. … Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak. And what is the principle not to develop? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called the principle not to develop.

And what is the principle to develop? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the principle to develop.”

AN 10.196 Principles That Should Be Made Much Of Bahulīkātabbasutta

“I will teach you the principle to make much of and the principle not to make much of. … And what is the principle not to make much of? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called the principle not to make much of.

And what is the principle to make much of? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the principle to make much of.”

AN 10.197 Should Be Recollected Anussaritabbasutta

“I will teach you the principle to recollect and the principle not to recollect. … And what is the principle not to recollect? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called the principle not to recollect.

And what is the principle to recollect? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the principle to recollect.”

AN 10.198 Should Be Realized Sacchikātabbasutta

“I will teach you the principle to realize and the principle not to realize. … And what is the principle not to realize? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called the principle not to realize.

And what is the principle to realize? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the principle to realize.”

Another Chapter on Individuals

AN 10.199–210 Should Not Associate, Etc. Aparapuggalavagga

“Mendicants, you should not associate with an individual who possesses ten qualities. What ten? They kill living creatures, steal, and commit sexual misconduct. They use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. And they’re covetous, malicious, with wrong view. You should not associate with an individual who possesses these ten qualities.

You should associate with an individual who possesses ten qualities. What ten? They don’t kill living creatures, steal, or commit sexual misconduct. They don’t use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. They’re contented, kind-hearted, with right view. You should associate with an individual who possesses these ten qualities.”

“Mendicants, you should not frequent an individual who possesses ten qualities … You should frequent …” “You should not pay homage … You should pay homage …” “You should not venerate … You should venerate …” “You should not praise … You should praise …” “You should not revere … You should revere …” “You should not defer to … You should defer to …” “Someone is not a success … Someone is a success …” “Someone is not pure … Someone is pure …” “Someone does not win over conceit … Someone wins over conceit …” “Someone does not grow in wisdom … Someone grows in wisdom …”

“An individual who possesses these ten qualities brims with much wickedness. … An individual who possesses these ten qualities brims with much merit. What ten? They don’t kill living creatures, steal, or commit sexual misconduct. They don’t use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. They’re contented, kind-hearted, with right view. An individual who possesses these ten qualities brims with much merit.”

The Chapter on the Noble Path

AN 10.145 The Noble Path Ariyamaggasutta

“I will teach you the noble path and the ignoble path. … And what is the ignoble path? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called the ignoble path. And what is the noble path? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the noble path.”

AN 10.146 The Dark Path Kaṇhamaggasutta

“I will teach you the dark path and the bright path. … And what is the dark path? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called the dark path. And what is the bright path? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the bright path.”

AN 10.147 The True Teaching Saddhammasutta

“I will teach you what is the true teaching and what is not the true teaching. … And what is not the true teaching? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called what is not the true teaching. And what is the true teaching? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the true teaching.”

AN 10.148 The Teaching of the True Persons Sappurisadhammasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the teaching of the true persons and the teaching of the untrue persons. … And what is the teaching of the untrue persons? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is the teaching of the untrue persons. And what is the teaching of the true persons? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is the teaching of the true persons.”

AN 10.149 Should Be Activated Uppādetabbasutta

“I will teach you the principle to activate and the principle not to activate. … And what is the principle not to activate? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called the principle not to activate. And what is the principle to activate? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the principle to activate.”

AN 10.150 Should Be Cultivated Āsevitabbasutta

“I will teach you the principle to cultivate and the principle not to cultivate. … And what is the principle not to cultivate? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called the principle not to cultivate. And what is the principle to cultivate? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the principle to cultivate.”

AN 10.151 Should Be Developed Bhāvetabbasutta

“I will teach you the principle to develop and the principle not to develop. … And what is the principle not to develop? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called the principle not to develop. And what is the principle to develop? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the principle to develop.”

AN 10.152 Should Be Made Much Of Bahulīkātabbasutta

“I will teach you the principle to make much of and the principle not to make much of. … And what is the principle not to make much of? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called the principle not to make much of. And what is the principle to make much of? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the principle to make much of.”

AN 10.153 Should Be Recollected Anussaritabbasutta

“I will teach you the principle to recollect and the principle not to recollect. … And what is the principle not to recollect? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called the principle not to recollect. And what is the principle to recollect? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the principle to recollect.”

AN 10.154 Should Be Realized Sacchikātabbasutta

“I will teach you the principle to realize and the principle not to realize. … And what is the principle not to realize? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called the principle not to realize. And what is the principle to realize? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the principle to realize.”

The Fourth Fifty

The Chapter on Individuals

AN 10.155 You Should Associate Sevitabbasutta

“Mendicants, you should not associate with an individual who has ten qualities. What ten? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. You should not associate with an individual who has these ten qualities.

You should associate with an individual who has ten qualities. What ten? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. You should associate with an individual who has these ten qualities.”

AN 10.156–166 Frequenting, Etc. Bhajitabbādisutta

“Mendicants, you should not frequent an individual who has ten qualities. … you should frequent … you should not pay homage … you should pay homage … you should not venerate … you should venerate … you should not praise … you should praise … you should not respect … you should respect … you should not revere … you should revere … is not a success … is a success … is not pure … is pure … does not win over conceit … wins over conceit … does not grow in wisdom … grows in wisdom …

brims with much wickedness … brims with much merit. What ten? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. An individual who has these ten qualities brims with much merit.”

The Chapter on Good

AN 10.178 Good Sādhusutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you what is good and what is not good. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“And what, mendicants, is not good? Killing living creatures, stealing, and sexual misconduct; speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical; covetousness, ill will, and wrong view. This is called what is not good.

And what is good? Refraining from killing living creatures, stealing, and sexual misconduct; refraining from speech that’s false, divisive, harsh, or nonsensical; contentment, good will, and right view. This is called what is good.”

AN 10.179 The Teaching of the Noble Ones Ariyadhammasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the teaching of the noble ones, and what is not the teaching of the noble ones. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak. … And what is not the teaching of the noble ones? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called what is not the teaching of the noble ones.

And what is the teaching of the noble ones? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the teaching of the noble ones.”

AN 10.180 Skillful Kusalasutta

“I will teach you the skillful and the unskillful … And what is the unskillful? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called the unskillful.

And what is the skillful? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the skillful.”

AN 10.181 Beneficial Atthasutta

“I will teach you the beneficial and the harmful. … And what is the harmful? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called the harmful.

And what is the beneficial? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the beneficial.”

AN 10.182 The Teaching Dhammasutta

“I will teach you what is the teaching and what is not the teaching. … And what is not the teaching? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called what is not the teaching.

And what is the teaching? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the teaching.”

AN 10.183 Defiled Āsavasutta

“I will teach you the defiled principle and the undefiled. … And what is the defiled principle? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called the defiled principle.

And what is the undefiled principle? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the undefiled principle.”

AN 10.184 Blameworthy Vajjasutta

“I will teach you the blameworthy principle and the blameless. … And what is the blameworthy principle? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called the blameworthy principle.

And what is the blameless principle? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the blameless principle.”

AN 10.185 Mortifying Tapanīyasutta

“I will teach you the mortifying principle and the unmortifying. … And what is the mortifying principle? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called the mortifying principle.

And what is the unmortifying principle? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the unmortifying principle.”

AN 10.186 Leading to Accumulation Ācayagāmisutta

“I will teach you the principle that leads to accumulation and that which leads to dispersal. … And what is the principle that leads to accumulation? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called the principle that leads to accumulation.

And what is the principle that leads to dispersal? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the principle that leads to dispersal.”

AN 10.187 With Suffering as Outcome Dukkhudrayasutta

“I will teach you the principle that has suffering as outcome, and that which has happiness as outcome. … And what is the principle whose outcome is suffering? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is the principle whose outcome is suffering.

And what is the principle whose outcome is happiness? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is the principle whose outcome is happiness.”

AN 10.188 Result Vipākasutta

“I will teach you the principle that results in suffering and that which results in happiness. … And what is the principle that results in suffering? Killing living creatures … wrong view. This is called the principle that results in suffering.

And what is the principle that results in happiness? Not killing living creatures … right view. This is called the principle that results in happiness.”

The Second Fifty

The Chapter on Your Own Mind

AN 10.51 Your Own Mind Sacittasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, if a mendicant isn’t skilled in encompassing another’s mind, then they should train themselves: ‘I will be skilled in encompassing my own mind.’

And how is a mendicant skilled in encompassing their own mind? Suppose there was a woman or man who was young, youthful, and fond of adornments, and they check their own reflection in a clean bright mirror or a clear bowl of water. If they see any dirt or blemish there, they’d try to remove it. But if they don’t see any dirt or blemish there, they’re happy with that, as they’ve got all they wished for: ‘How fortunate that I’m clean!’ In the same way, checking is very helpful for a mendicant’s skillful qualities. ‘Am I often covetous or not? Am I often malicious or not? Am I often overcome with dullness and drowsiness or not? Am I often restless or not? Am I often doubtful or not? Am I often irritable or not? Am I often corrupted in mind or not? Am I often disturbed in body or not? Am I often energetic or not? Am I often immersed in samādhi or not?’

Suppose that, upon checking, a mendicant knows this: ‘I am often covetous, malicious, overcome with dullness and drowsiness, restless, doubtful, irritable, corrupted in mind, disturbed in body, lazy, and not immersed in samādhi.’ In order to give up those bad, unskillful qualities, they should apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness. Suppose your clothes or head were on fire. In order to extinguish it, you’d apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness. In the same way, in order to give up those bad, unskillful qualities, that mendicant should apply extraordinary enthusiasm …

But suppose that, upon checking, a mendicant knows this: ‘I am often content, kind-hearted, rid of dullness and drowsiness, calm, confident, loving, pure in mind, undisturbed in body, energetic, and immersed in samādhi.’ Grounded on those skillful qualities, they should practice meditation further to end the defilements.”

AN 10.52 With Sāriputta Sāriputtasutta

There Sāriputta addressed the mendicants: “Reverends, mendicants!”

“Reverend,” they replied. Sāriputta said this:

“Reverends, if a mendicant isn’t skilled in encompassing another’s mind, then they should train themselves: ‘I will be skilled in encompassing my own mind.’

And how is a mendicant skilled in encompassing their own mind? Suppose there was a woman or man who was young, youthful, and fond of adornments, and they check their own reflection in a clean bright mirror or a clear bowl of water. If they see any dirt or blemish there, they’d try to remove it. But if they don’t see any dirt or blemish there, they’re happy with that, as they’ve got all they wished for: ‘How fortunate that I’m clean!’

In the same way, checking is very helpful for a mendicant’s skillful qualities. ‘Am I often covetous or not? Am I often malicious or not? Am I often overcome with dullness and drowsiness or not? Am I often restless or not? Am I often doubtful or not? Am I often irritable or not? Am I often corrupted in mind or not? Am I often disturbed in body or not? Am I often energetic or not? Am I often immersed in samādhi or not?’

Suppose that, upon checking, a mendicant knows this: ‘I am often covetous, malicious, overcome with dullness and drowsiness, restless, doubtful, irritable, defiled in mind, disturbed in body, lazy, and not immersed in samādhi.’ In order to give up those bad, unskillful qualities, they should apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness. Suppose your clothes or head were on fire. In order to extinguish it, you’d apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness. In the same way, in order to give up those bad, unskillful qualities, that mendicant should apply extraordinary enthusiasm …

But suppose that, upon checking, a mendicant knows this: ‘I am often content, kind-hearted, rid of dullness and drowsiness, calm, confident, loving, pure in mind, undisturbed in body, energetic, and immersed in samādhi.’ Grounded on those skillful qualities, they should practice meditation further to end the defilements.”

AN 10.53 Stagnation Ṭhitisutta

“Mendicants, I don’t praise stagnation in skillful qualities, let alone decline. I praise growth in skillful qualities, not stagnation or decline.

And how is there decline in skillful qualities, not stagnation or growth? It’s when a mendicant has a certain degree of faith, ethics, generosity, wisdom, and eloquence. Those qualities neither stagnate nor grow in them. I call this decline in skillful qualities, not stagnation or growth. This is how there’s decline in skillful qualities, not stagnation or growth.

And how is there stagnation in skillful qualities, not decline or growth? It’s when a mendicant has a certain degree of faith, ethics, generosity, wisdom, and eloquence. Those qualities neither decline nor grow in them. I call this stagnation in skillful qualities, not decline or growth. This is how there’s stagnation in skillful qualities, not decline or growth.

And how is there growth in skillful qualities, not stagnation or decline? It’s when a mendicant has a certain degree of faith, ethics, generosity, wisdom, and eloquence. Those qualities neither stagnate nor decline in them. I call this growth in skillful qualities, not stagnation or decline. This is how there’s growth in skillful qualities, not stagnation or decline.

If a mendicant isn’t skilled in encompassing another’s mind, then they should train themselves: ‘I will be skilled in encompassing my own mind.’

And how is a mendicant skilled in encompassing their own mind? Suppose there was a woman or man who was young, youthful, and fond of adornments, and they check their own reflection in a clean bright mirror or a clear bowl of water. If they see any dirt or blemish there, they’d try to remove it. But if they don’t see any dirt or blemish there, they’re happy with that, as they’ve got all they wished for: ‘How fortunate that I’m clean!’ In the same way, checking is very helpful for a mendicant’s skillful qualities. ‘Am I often covetous or not? Am I often malicious or not? Am I often overcome with dullness and drowsiness or not? Am I often restless or not? Am I often doubtful or not? Am I often irritable or not? Am I often corrupted in mind or not? Am I often disturbed in body or not? Am I often energetic or not? Am I often immersed in samādhi or not?’

Suppose that, upon checking, a mendicant knows this: ‘I am often covetous, malicious, overcome with dullness and drowsiness, restless, doubtful, irritable, corrupted in mind, disturbed in body, lazy, and not immersed in samādhi.’ In order to give up those bad, unskillful qualities, they should apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness. Suppose your clothes or head were on fire. In order to extinguish it, you’d apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness. In the same way, in order to give up those bad, unskillful qualities, that mendicant should apply extraordinary enthusiasm …

But suppose that, upon checking, a mendicant knows this: ‘I am often content, kind-hearted, rid of dullness and drowsiness, calm, confident, loving, pure in mind, undisturbed in body, energetic, and immersed in samādhi.’ Grounded on those skillful qualities, they should practice meditation further to end the defilements.”

AN 10.54 Serenity Samathasutta

“Mendicants, if a mendicant isn’t skilled in encompassing another’s mind, then they should train themselves: ‘I will be skilled in encompassing my own mind.’

And how is a mendicant skilled in encompassing their own mind? Suppose there was a woman or man who was young, youthful, and fond of adornments, and they check their own reflection in a clean bright mirror or a clear bowl of water. If they see any dirt or blemish there, they’d try to remove it. But if they don’t see any dirt or blemish there, they’re happy with that, as they’ve got all they wished for: ‘How fortunate that I’m clean!’ In the same way, checking is very helpful for a mendicant’s skillful qualities. ‘Do I have internal serenity of heart or not? Do I have the higher wisdom of discernment of principles or not?’

Suppose that, upon checking, a mendicant knows this: ‘I have serenity but not discernment.’ Grounded on serenity, they should practice meditation to get discernment. After some time they have both serenity and discernment.

But suppose that, upon checking, a mendicant knows this: ‘I have discernment but not serenity.’ Grounded on discernment, they should practice meditation to get serenity. After some time they have both serenity and discernment.

But suppose that, upon checking, a mendicant knows this: ‘I have neither serenity nor discernment.’ In order to get those skillful qualities, they should apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness. Suppose your clothes or head were on fire. In order to extinguish it, you’d apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness. In the same way, in order to get those skillful qualities, that mendicant should apply extraordinary enthusiasm … After some time they have both serenity and discernment.

But suppose that, upon checking, a mendicant knows this: ‘I have both serenity and discernment.’ Grounded on those skillful qualities, they should practice meditation further to end the defilements.

I say that there are two kinds of robes: those you should wear, and those you shouldn’t wear. I say that there are two kinds of almsfood: that which you should eat, and that which you shouldn’t eat. I say that there are two kinds of lodging: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent. I say that there are two kinds of village or town: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent. I say that there are two kinds of country: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent. I say that there are two kinds of individual: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent.

‘I say that there are two kinds of robes: those you should wear, and those you shouldn’t wear.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Well, should you know of a robe: ‘When I wear this robe, unskillful qualities grow, and skillful qualities decline.’ You should not wear that kind of robe. Whereas, should you know of a robe: ‘When I wear this robe, unskillful qualities decline, and skillful qualities grow.’ You should wear that kind of robe. ‘I say that there are two kinds of robes: those you should wear, and those you shouldn’t wear.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘I say that there are two kinds of almsfood: that which you should eat, and that which you shouldn’t eat.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Well, should you know of almsfood: ‘When I eat this almsfood, unskillful qualities grow, and skillful qualities decline.’ You should not eat that kind of almsfood. Whereas, should you know of almsfood: ‘When I eat this almsfood, unskillful qualities decline, and skillful qualities grow.’ You should eat that kind of almsfood. ‘I say that there are two kinds of almsfood: that which you should eat, and that which you shouldn’t eat.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘I say that there are two kinds of lodging: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Well, should you know of a lodging: ‘When I frequent this lodging, unskillful qualities grow, and skillful qualities decline.’ You should not frequent that kind of lodging. Whereas, should you know of a lodging: ‘When I frequent this lodging, unskillful qualities decline, and skillful qualities grow.’ You should frequent that kind of lodging. ‘I say that there are two kinds of lodging: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘I say that there are two kinds of village or town: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Well, should you know of a village or town: ‘When I frequent this village or town, unskillful qualities grow, and skillful qualities decline.’ You should not frequent that kind of village or town. Whereas, should you know of a village or town: ‘When I frequent this village or town, unskillful qualities decline, and skillful qualities grow.’ You should frequent that kind of village or town. ‘I say that there are two kinds of village or town: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘I say that there are two kinds of country: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Well, should you know of a country: ‘When I frequent this country, unskillful qualities grow, and skillful qualities decline.’ You should not frequent that kind of country. Whereas, should you know of a country: ‘When I frequent this country, unskillful qualities decline, and skillful qualities grow.’ You should frequent that kind of country. ‘I say that there are two kinds of country: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘I say that there are two two kinds of individual: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Well, should you know of an individual: ‘When I frequent this individual, unskillful qualities grow, and skillful qualities decline.’ You should not frequent that kind of individual. Whereas, should you know of an individual: ‘When I frequent this individual, unskillful qualities decline, and skillful qualities grow.’ You should frequent that kind of individual. ‘I say that there are two kinds of individual: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.”

AN 10.55 Decline Parihānasutta

There Sāriputta addressed the mendicants: “Reverends, mendicants!”

“Reverend,” they replied. Sāriputta said this:

“Reverends, they speak of an individual liable to decline, and one not liable to decline. But how did the Buddha define an individual liable to decline, and one not liable to decline?”

“Reverend, we would travel a long way to learn the meaning of this statement in the presence of Venerable Sāriputta. May Venerable Sāriputta himself please clarify the meaning of this. The mendicants will listen and remember it.”

“Then listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, reverend,” they replied. Sāriputta said this:

“How did the Buddha define an individual liable to decline? It’s when a mendicant doesn’t get to hear a teaching they haven’t heard before. They forget those teachings they have heard. They don’t keep exercising the teachings with which they are already familiar. And they don’t come to understand what they haven’t understood before. That’s how the Buddha defined an individual liable to decline.

And how did the Buddha define an individual not liable to decline? It’s when a mendicant gets to hear a teaching they haven’t heard before. They remember those teachings they have heard. They keep exercising the teachings with which they are already familiar. And they come to understand what they haven’t understood before. That’s how the Buddha defined an individual not liable to decline.

If a mendicant isn’t skilled in encompassing another’s mind, then they should train themselves: ‘I will be skilled in encompassing my own mind.’

And how is a mendicant skilled in encompassing their own mind? Suppose there was a woman or man who was young, youthful, and fond of adornments, and they check their own reflection in a clean bright mirror or a clear bowl of water. If they see any dirt or blemish there, they’d try to remove it. But if they don’t see any dirt or blemish there, they’re happy with that, as they’ve got all they wished for: ‘How fortunate that I’m clean!’

In the same way, checking is very helpful for a mendicant’s skillful qualities. ‘Is contentment often found in me or not? Is good will often found in me or not? Is freedom from dullness and drowsiness often found in me or not? Is calm often found in me or not? Is confidence often found in me or not? Is love often found in me or not? Is purity of mind often found in me or not? Is internal joy with the teaching found in me or not? Is internal serenity of heart found in me or not? Is the higher wisdom of discernment of principles found in me or not?’

Suppose a mendicant, while checking, doesn’t see any of these skillful qualities in themselves. In order to get them they should apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness. Suppose your clothes or head were on fire. In order to extinguish it, you’d apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness. In the same way, they should apply extraordinary enthusiasm to get those skillful qualities …

Suppose a mendicant, while checking, sees some of these skillful qualities in themselves, but doesn’t see others. Grounded on the skillful qualities they see, they should apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness in order to get the skillful qualities they don’t see. Suppose your clothes or head were on fire. In order to extinguish it, you’d apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness. In the same way, grounded on the skillful qualities they see, they should apply extraordinary enthusiasm to get those skillful qualities they don’t see.

But suppose a mendicant, while checking, sees all of these skillful qualities in themselves. Grounded on all these skillful qualities they should practice meditation further to end the defilements.”

AN 10.56 Perceptions (1st) Paṭhamasaññāsutta

“Mendicants, these ten perceptions, when developed and cultivated, are very fruitful and beneficial. They have freedom from death as their objective and culmination. What ten? The perceptions of ugliness, death, repulsiveness of food, dissatisfaction with the whole world, impermanence, suffering in impermanence, and not-self in suffering, giving up, fading away, and cessation. These ten perceptions, when developed and cultivated, are very fruitful and beneficial. They have freedom from death as their objective and culmination.”

AN 10.57 Perceptions (2nd) Dutiyasaññāsutta

“Mendicants, these ten perceptions, when developed and cultivated, are very fruitful and beneficial. They have freedom from death as their objective and culmination. What ten? The perceptions of impermanence, not-self, death, repulsiveness of food, dissatisfaction with the whole world, a skeleton, a worm-infested corpse, a livid corpse, a split open corpse, and a bloated corpse. These ten perceptions, when developed and cultivated, are very fruitful and beneficial. They have freedom from death as their objective and culmination.”

AN 10.58 Rooted Mūlakasutta

“Mendicants, if wanderers of other religions were to ask: ‘Reverends, all things have what as their root? What produces them? What is their origin? What is their meeting place? What is their chief? What is their ruler? What is their overseer? What is their core? What is their objective? What is their culmination?’ How would you answer them?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. He is our guide and our refuge. Sir, may the Buddha himself please clarify the meaning of this. The mendicants will listen and remember it.”

“Well then, mendicants, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, if wanderers of other religions were to ask: ‘Reverends, all things have what as their root? What produces them? What is their origin? What is their meeting place? What is their chief? What is their ruler? What is their overseer? What is their core? What is their objective? What is their culmination?’ You should answer them: ‘Reverends, all things are rooted in desire. They are produced by application of mind. Contact is their origin. Feeling is their meeting place. Immersion is their chief. Mindfulness is their ruler. Wisdom is their overseer. Freedom is their core. Their objective is freedom from death. And extinguishment is their culmination.’ When questioned by wanderers of other religions, that’s how you should answer them.”

AN 10.59 Going Forth Pabbajjāsutta

“So you should train like this: ‘Our minds will be consolidated as they were when we went forth, and arisen bad unskillful qualities will not occupy our minds. Our minds will be consolidated in the perceptions of impermanence, not-self, ugliness, and drawbacks. Knowing what is fair and unfair in the world, our minds will be consolidated in that perception. Knowing existence and nonexistence in the world, our minds will be consolidated in that perception. Knowing the origin and disappearance of the world, our minds will be consolidated in that perception. Our minds will be consolidated in the perceptions of giving up, fading away, and cessation.’ That’s how you should train.

When your minds are consolidated in these ten perceptions, you can expect one of two results: enlightenment in this very life, or if there’s residue left behind, non-return.”

AN 10.60 With Girimānanda Girimānandasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. Now at that time Venerable Girimānanda was sick, suffering, gravely ill. Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, Venerable Girimānanda is sick, suffering, gravely ill. Sir, please go to Venerable Girimānanda out of sympathy.”

“Ānanda, if you were to recite to the mendicant Girimānanda these ten perceptions, it’s possible that after hearing them his illness will die down on the spot.

What ten? The perceptions of impermanence, not-self, ugliness, drawbacks, giving up, fading away, cessation, dissatisfaction with the whole world, impermanence of all conditions, and mindfulness of breathing.

And what is the perception of impermanence? It’s when a mendicant has gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut, and reflects like this: ‘Form, feeling, perception, choices, and consciousness are impermanent.’ And so they meditate observing impermanence in the five grasping aggregates. This is called the perception of impermanence.

And what is the perception of not-self? It’s when a mendicant has gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut, and reflects like this: ‘The eye and sights, ear and sounds, nose and smells, tongue and tastes, body and touches, and mind and ideas are not-self.’ And so they meditate observing not-self in the six interior and exterior sense fields. This is called the perception of not-self.

And what is the perception of ugliness? It’s when a mendicant examines their own body up from the soles of the feet and down from the tips of the hairs, wrapped in skin and full of many kinds of filth. ‘In this body there is head hair, body hair, nails, teeth, skin, flesh, sinews, bones, bone marrow, kidneys, heart, liver, diaphragm, spleen, lungs, intestines, mesentery, undigested food, feces, bile, phlegm, pus, blood, sweat, fat, tears, grease, saliva, snot, synovial fluid, urine.’ And so they meditate observing ugliness in this body. This is called the perception of ugliness.

And what is the perception of drawbacks? It’s when a mendicant has gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut, and reflects like this: ‘This body has much suffering and many drawbacks. For this body is beset with many kinds of affliction, such as the following. Diseases of the eye, inner ear, nose, tongue, body, head, outer ear, mouth, teeth, and lips. Cough, asthma, catarrh, inflammation, fever, stomach ache, fainting, dysentery, gastric pain, cholera, leprosy, boils, eczema, tuberculosis, epilepsy, herpes, itch, scabs, smallpox, scabies, hemorrhage, diabetes, piles, pimples, and ulcers. Afflictions stemming from disorders of bile, phlegm, wind, or their conjunction. Afflictions caused by change in weather, by not taking care of yourself, by exertion, or as the result of past deeds. Cold, heat, hunger, thirst, defecation, and urination.’ And so they meditate observing drawbacks in this body. This is called the perception of drawbacks.

And what is the perception of giving up? It’s when a mendicant doesn’t tolerate a sensual, malicious, or cruel thought that has arisen, and they don’t tolerate any bad, unskillful qualities that have arisen, but give them up, dispel them, eliminate them, and obliterate them. This is called the perception of giving up.

And what is the perception of fading away? It’s when a mendicant has gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut, and reflects like this: ‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, extinguishment.’ This is called the perception of fading away.

And what is the perception of cessation? It’s when a mendicant has gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut, and reflects like this: ‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, cessation, extinguishment.’ This is called the perception of cessation.

And what is the perception of dissatisfaction with the whole world? It’s when a mendicant lives giving up and not grasping on to the attraction and grasping to the world, the mental fixation, insistence, and underlying tendencies. This is called the perception of dissatisfaction with the whole world.

And what is the perception of the impermanence of all conditions? It’s when a mendicant is horrified, repelled, and disgusted with all conditions. This is called the perception of the impermanence of all conditions.

And what is mindfulness of breathing? It’s when a mendicant has gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut, sits down cross-legged, sets their body straight, and brings mindfulness to the present. Just mindful, they breathe in. Mindful, they breathe out. Breathing in heavily they know: ‘I’m breathing in heavily.’ Breathing out heavily they know: ‘I’m breathing out heavily.’ Breathing in lightly they know: ‘I’m breathing in lightly.’ Breathing out lightly they know: ‘I’m breathing out lightly.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing the whole body.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out experiencing the whole body.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in stilling the physical process.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out stilling the physical process.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing rapture.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out experiencing rapture.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing bliss.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out experiencing bliss.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing the mental process.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out experiencing the mental process.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in stilling the mental process.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out stilling the mental process.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in experiencing the mind.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out experiencing the mind.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in gladdening the mind.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out gladdening the mind.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in immersing the mind in samādhi.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out immersing the mind in samādhi.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in freeing the mind.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out freeing the mind.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing impermanence.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing impermanence.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing fading away.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing fading away.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing cessation.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing cessation.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe in observing letting go.’ They practice like this: ‘I’ll breathe out observing letting go.’ This is called mindfulness of breathing.

If you were to recite to the mendicant Girimānanda these ten perceptions, it’s possible that after hearing them his illness will die down on the spot.”

Then Ānanda, having learned these ten perceptions from the Buddha himself, went to Girimānanda and recited them. Then after Girimānanda heard these ten perceptions his illness died down on the spot. And that’s how he recovered from that illness.

The Chapter with Jānussoṇi

AN 10.167 The Brahmin Ceremony of Descent Brāhmaṇapaccorohaṇīsutta

Now, at that time it was the sabbath. The brahmin Jānussoṇi had bathed his head and dressed in a new pair of linen robes. Holding a handful of fresh grass, he stood to one side not far from the Buddha.

The Buddha saw him, and said, “Brahmin, why have you bathed your head and dressed in a new pair of linen robes? Why are you standing to one side holding a handful of fresh grass? What’s going on today with the brahmin clan?”

“Worthy Gotama, today is the ceremony of descent for the brahmin clan.”

“But how do the brahmins observe the ceremony of descent?”

“Well, worthy Gotama, on the sabbath the brahmins bathe their heads and dress in a new pair of linen robes. They make a heap of fresh cow dung and spread it with green grass. Then they make their beds between the boundary and the fire chamber. That night they rise three times and worship the fire with cupped palms: ‘We descend, lord! We descend, lord!’ And they serve the fire with abundant ghee, oil, and butter. And when the night has passed they serve the brahmins with delicious fresh and cooked foods. That’s how the brahmins observe the ceremony of descent.”

“The ceremony of descent observed by the brahmins is quite different from that observed in the training of the Noble One.”

“But worthy Gotama, how is the ceremony of descent observed in the training of the Noble One? Worthy Gotama, please teach me this.”

“Well then, brahmin, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, worthy sir,” Jānussoṇi replied. The Buddha said this:

“It’s when a noble disciple reflects: ‘Killing living creatures has a bad result in the present life and in lives to come.’ Reflecting like this, they give up killing living creatures, they descend from killing living creatures.

… ‘Stealing has a bad result in the present life and in lives to come.’ Reflecting like this, they give up stealing, they descend from stealing.

… ‘Sexual misconduct has a bad result in the present life and in lives to come.’ Reflecting like this, they give up sexual misconduct, they descend from sexual misconduct.

… ‘Lying has a bad result in the present life and in lives to come.’ Reflecting like this, they give up lying, they descend from lying.

… ‘Backbiting has a bad result in the present life and in lives to come.’ Reflecting like this, they give up backbiting, they descend from backbiting.

… ‘Harsh speech has a bad result in the present life and in lives to come.’ Reflecting like this, they give up harsh speech, they descend from harsh speech.

… ‘Talking nonsense has a bad result in the present life and in lives to come.’ Reflecting like this, they give up talking nonsense, they descend from talking nonsense.

… ‘Covetousness has a bad result in the present life and in lives to come.’ Reflecting like this, they give up covetousness, they descend from covetousness.

… ‘Ill will has a bad result in the present life and in lives to come.’ Reflecting like this, they give up ill will, they descend from ill will.

‘Wrong view has a bad result in the present life and in lives to come.’ Reflecting like this, they give up wrong view, they descend from wrong view. This is the ceremony of descent in the training of the Noble One.”

“The ceremony of descent observed by the brahmins is quite different from that observed in the training of the Noble One. And, worthy Gotama, the ceremony of descent observed by the brahmins is not worth a sixteenth part of the ceremony of descent observed in the training of the Noble One. Excellent, worthy Gotama, excellent! … From this day forth, may the worthy Gotama remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

AN 10.168 The Noble Descent Ariyapaccorohaṇīsutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the noble descent. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“And what, mendicants, is the noble descent? It’s when a noble disciple reflects: ‘Killing living creatures has a bad result in the present life and in lives to come.’ Reflecting like this, they give up killing living creatures, they descend from killing living creatures.

… ‘Stealing has a bad result in the present life and in lives to come.’ Reflecting like this, they give up stealing, they descend from stealing.

… ‘Sexual misconduct has a bad result …’ … they descend from sexual misconduct.

… ‘Lying has a bad result …’ … they descend from lying.

… ‘Backbiting has a bad result …’ … they descend from backbiting.

… ‘Harsh speech has a bad result …’ … they descend from harsh speech.

… ‘Talking nonsense has a bad result …’ … they descend from talking nonsense.

… ‘Covetousness has a bad result …’ … they descend from covetousness.

… ‘Ill will has a bad result …’ … they descend from ill will.

… ‘Wrong view has a bad result both in the present life and in lives to come.’ Reflecting like this, they give up wrong view, they descend from wrong view. This is called the noble descent.”

AN 10.169 With Saṅgārava Saṅgāravasutta

Then Saṅgārava the brahmin went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“Worthy Gotama, what is the near shore? And what is the far shore?”

“Killing living creatures is the near shore, brahmin, and not killing living creatures is the far shore. Stealing is the near shore, and not stealing is the far shore. Sexual misconduct is the near shore, and refraining from sexual misconduct is the far shore. Lying is the near shore, and not lying is the far shore. Divisive speech is the near shore, and refraining from divisive speech is the far shore. Harsh speech is the near shore, and refraining from harsh speech is the far shore. Talking nonsense is the near shore, and refraining from talking nonsense is the far shore. Covetousness is the near shore, and contentment is the far shore. Ill will is the near shore, and good will is the far shore. Wrong view is the near shore, and right view is the far shore. This is the near shore, and this is the far shore.

Few are those among humans
who cross to the far shore.
The rest just run
around on the near shore.

When the teaching is well explained,
the people who practice accordingly
will cross over
Death’s dominion so hard to pass.

Rid of dark qualities,
an astute person would develop the bright.
Having left home for homelessness
in seclusion, where joy is hard,

they’d long for satisfaction there.
Forsaking sensual pleasures, owning nothing,
an astute person would cleanse themselves
of mental corruptions.

And those whose minds are rightly developed
in the awakening factors;
who, letting go of attachments,
delight in not grasping—
with defilements ended, brilliant,
they are quenched in this world.”

AN 10.170 The Near Shore Orimasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the near shore and the far shore. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak. … And what, mendicants, is the near shore? What is the far shore? Killing living creatures is the near shore, mendicants, and not killing living creatures is the far shore. Stealing is the near shore, and not stealing is the far shore. Sexual misconduct is the near shore, and refraining from sexual misconduct is the far shore. Lying is the near shore, and not lying is the far shore. Divisive speech is the near shore, and refraining from divisive speech is the far shore. Harsh speech is the near shore, and refraining from harsh speech is the far shore. Talking nonsense is the near shore, and refraining from talking nonsense is the far shore. Covetousness is the near shore, and contentment is the far shore. Ill will is the near shore, and good will is the far shore. Wrong view is the near shore, and right view is the far shore. This is the near shore, and this is the far shore.

Few are those among humans
who cross to the far shore.
The rest just run
around on the near shore.

When the teaching is well explained,
the people who practice accordingly
will cross over
Death’s dominion so hard to pass.

Rid of dark qualities,
an astute person would develop the bright.
Having left home for homelessness
in seclusion, where joy is hard,

they’d long for satisfaction there.
Having given up sensual pleasures, owning nothing,
an astute person would cleanse themselves
of mental corruptions.

And those whose minds are rightly developed
in the awakening factors;
who, letting go of attachments,
delight in not grasping—
with defilements ended, brilliant,
they are quenched in this world.”

AN 10.171 Bad Principles (1st) Paṭhamaadhammasutta

“Mendicants, you should know bad principles with bad results. And you should know good principles with good results. Knowing these things, your practice should follow the good principles with good results.

And what are bad principles with bad results? Killing living creatures, stealing, and sexual misconduct; speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical; covetousness, ill will, and wrong view. These are called bad principles with bad results.

And what are good principles with good results? Refraining from killing living creatures, stealing, and sexual misconduct; refraining from speech that’s false, divisive, harsh, or nonsensical; contentment, good will, and right view. These are called good principles with good results.

‘You should know bad principles with bad results. And you should know good principles with good results. Knowing these things, your practice should follow the good principles with good results.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.”

AN 10.172 Bad Principles (2nd) Dutiyaadhammasutta

“Mendicants, you should know bad principles and good principles. And you should know bad results and good results. Knowing these things, your practice should follow the good principles with good results.”

That is what the Buddha said. When he had spoken, the Holy One rose from his seat and entered his dwelling.

Soon after the Buddha left, those mendicants considered, “The Buddha gave this brief summary recital, then entered his dwelling without explaining the meaning in detail. ‘You should know bad principles and good principles. And you should know bad results and good results. Knowing these things, your practice should follow the good principles with good results.’ Who can explain in detail the meaning of this brief summary recital given by the Buddha?”

Then those mendicants thought, “This Venerable Mahākaccāna is praised by the Buddha and esteemed by his sensible spiritual companions. He is capable of explaining in detail the meaning of this brief summary recital given by the Buddha. Let’s go to him, and ask him about this matter. As he answers, so we’ll remember it.”

Then those mendicants went to Mahākaccāna, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, they sat down to one side. They told him what had happened, and said, “May Venerable Mahākaccāna please explain this.”

“Reverends, suppose there was a person in need of heartwood. And while wandering in search of heartwood he’d come across a large tree standing with heartwood. But he’d pass over the roots and trunk, imagining that the heartwood should be sought in the branches and leaves. Such is the consequence for the venerables. Though you were face to face with the Buddha, you bypassed him, imagining that you should ask me about this matter. For he is the Buddha, the one who knows and sees. He is vision, he is knowledge, he is the manifestation of principle, he is the manifestation of divinity. He is the preacher, the proclaimer, the elucidator of meaning, the bestower of freedom from death, the lord of truth, the Realized One. That was the time to approach the Buddha and ask about this matter. You should have remembered it in line with the Buddha’s answer.”

“Certainly he is the Buddha, the one who knows and sees. He is vision, he is knowledge, he is the manifestation of principle, he is the manifestation of divinity. He is the preacher, the proclaimer, the elucidator of meaning, the bestower of freedom from death, the lord of truth, the Realized One. That was the time to approach the Buddha and ask about this matter. We should have remembered it in line with the Buddha’s answer. Still, Venerable Mahākaccāna is praised by the Buddha and esteemed by his sensible spiritual companions. He is capable of explaining in detail the meaning of this brief summary recital given by the Buddha. Please explain this, if it’s no trouble.”

“Well then, reverends, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, reverend,” they replied. Mahākaccāna said this:

“Reverends, the Buddha gave this brief summary recital, then entered his dwelling without explaining the meaning in detail: ‘You should know bad principles and good principles … and practice accordingly.’

So what are bad principles? What are good principles? What are bad results? And what are good results? Killing living creatures is a bad principle. Not killing living creatures is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by killing living creatures are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of not killing living creatures are good results.

Stealing is a bad principle. Not stealing is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by stealing are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of not stealing are good results.

Sexual misconduct is a bad principle. Refraining from sexual misconduct is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by sexual misconduct are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of refraining from sexual misconduct are good results.

Lying is a bad principle. Not lying is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by lying are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of not lying are good results.

Backbiting is a bad principle. Refraining from divisive speech is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by backbiting are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of refraining from divisive speech are good results.

Harsh speech is a bad principle. Refraining from harsh speech is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by harsh speech are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of refraining from harsh speech are good results.

Talking nonsense is a bad principle. Refraining from talking nonsense is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by talking nonsense are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of refraining from talking nonsense are good results.

Covetousness is a bad principle. Contentment is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by covetousness are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of contentment are good results.

Ill will is a bad principle. Good will is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by ill will are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of good will are good results.

Wrong view is a bad principle. Right view is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong view are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of right view are good results.

The Buddha gave this brief summary recital, then entered his dwelling without explaining the meaning in detail: ‘You should know bad principles and good principles … and practice accordingly.’ And this is how I understand the detailed meaning of this summary recital. If you wish, you may go to the Buddha and ask him about this. You should remember it in line with the Buddha’s answer.”

“Yes, reverend,” said those mendicants, approving and agreeing with what Mahākaccāna said. Then they rose from their seats and went to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened. Then they said:

“Sir, we went to Mahākaccāna and asked him about this matter. And Mahākaccāna clearly explained the meaning to us in this manner, with these words and phrases.”

“Good, good, mendicants! Mahākaccāna is astute, he has great wisdom. If you came to me and asked this question, I would answer it in exactly the same way as Mahākaccāna. That is what it means, and that’s how you should remember it.”

AN 10.173 Bad Principles (3rd) Tatiyaadhammasutta

“Mendicants, you should know bad principles and good principles. And you should know bad results and good results. Knowing these things, your practice should follow the good principles with good results.

So what are bad principles? What are good principles? What are bad results? And what are good results? Killing living creatures is a bad principle. Refraining from killing living creatures is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by killing living creatures are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of not killing living creatures are good results.

Stealing is a bad principle. Refraining from stealing is a good principle. … Sexual misconduct is a bad principle. Refraining from sexual misconduct is a good principle. … Lying is a bad principle. Refraining from lying is a good principle. … Backbiting is a bad principle. Refraining from divisive speech is a good principle. … Harsh speech is a bad principle. Refraining from harsh speech is a good principle. … Talking nonsense is a bad principle. Refraining from talking nonsense is a good principle. … Covetousness is a bad principle. Contentment is a good principle. … Ill will is a bad principle. Good will is a good principle. …

Wrong view is a bad principle. Right view is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong view are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of right view are good results.

‘You should know bad principles and good principles. And you should know bad results and good results. Knowing these things, your practice should follow the good principles with good results.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.”

AN 10.174 Sources of Deeds Kammanidānasutta

“Mendicants, I say that killing living creatures is threefold: caused by greed, hate, or delusion.

I say that stealing is threefold: caused by greed, hate, or delusion.

I say that sexual misconduct is threefold: caused by greed, hate, or delusion.

I say that lying is threefold: caused by greed, hate, or delusion.

I say that backbiting is threefold: caused by greed, hate, or delusion.

I say that harsh speech is threefold: caused by greed, hate, or delusion.

I say that talking nonsense is threefold: caused by greed, hate, or delusion.

I say that covetousness is threefold: caused by greed, hate, or delusion.

I say that ill will is threefold: caused by greed, hate, or delusion.

I say that wrong view is threefold: caused by greed, hate, or delusion. And so greed, hate, and delusion are sources and origins for deeds. With the ending of greed, hate, and delusion, the sources of deeds are ended.”

AN 10.175 The Bypass Parikkamanasutta

“Mendicants, this teaching provides a bypass, it doesn’t lack a bypass. And how does this teaching provide a bypass, not lacking a bypass? Not killing living creatures bypasses killing living creatures. Not stealing bypasses stealing. Refraining from sexual misconduct bypasses sexual misconduct. Not lying bypasses lying. Refraining from divisive speech bypasses divisive speech. Refraining from harsh speech bypasses harsh speech. Refraining from talking nonsense bypasses talking nonsense. Contentment bypasses covetousness. Good will bypasses ill will. Right view bypasses wrong view. That’s how this teaching provides a bypass, it doesn’t lack a bypass.”

AN 10.176 With Cunda Cundasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Pāvā in Cunda the smith’s mango grove. Then Cunda the smith went to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him, “Cunda, whose purity do you believe in?”

“Sir, I believe in the purity advocated by the western brahmins garlanded with aquatic flowers who carry pitchers, serve the sacred flame, and immerse themselves in water.”

“But Cunda, what kind of purity do these western brahmins advocate?”

“The western brahmins encourage their disciple like this: ‘Please, my man, rising early you should stroke the earth from your bed. If you don’t stroke the earth, stroke fresh cow dung. If you don’t stroke fresh cow dung, stroke green grass. If you don’t stroke green grass, serve the sacred flame. If you don’t serve the sacred flame, revere the sun with cupped palms. If you don’t revere the sun with cupped palms, immerse yourself in water three times, including at dusk.’ The western brahmins advocate this kind of purity.”

“The purity advocated by the western brahmins is quite different from that in the training of the Noble One.”

“But what, sir, is purity in the training of the Noble One? Sir, please teach me this.”

“Well then, brahmin, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” Cunda replied. The Buddha said this:

“Cunda, impurity is threefold by way of body, fourfold by way of speech, and threefold by way of mind.

And how is impurity threefold by way of body? It’s when someone kills living creatures. They’re violent, bloody-handed, a hardened killer, merciless to all living beings.

They steal. With the intention to commit theft, they take the wealth or belongings of others from village or wilderness.

They commit sexual misconduct. They have relations with women who have their mother, father, both mother and father, brother, sister, relatives, or clan as guardian. They have relations with a woman who is protected on principle, or who has a husband, or whose violation is punishable by law, or even one who has been garlanded as a token of betrothal.

This is the threefold impurity by way of body.

And how is impurity fourfold by way of speech? It’s when someone lies. They’re summoned to a council, an assembly, a family meeting, a guild, or to the royal court, and asked to bear witness: ‘Please, my friend, say what you know.’ Not knowing, they say ‘I know.’ Knowing, they say ‘I don’t know.’ Not seeing, they say ‘I see.’ And seeing, they say ‘I don’t see.’ So they deliberately lie for the sake of themselves or another, or for some trivial worldly reason.

They backbite. They repeat in one place what they heard in another so as to divide people against each other. And so they divide those who are harmonious, supporting division, delighting in division, loving division, speaking words that promote division.

They speak harshly. They use the kinds of words that are cruel, nasty, hurtful, offensive, bordering on anger, not leading to immersion.

They talk nonsense. Their speech is untimely, and is neither factual nor beneficial. It has nothing to do with the teaching or the training. Their words have no value, and are untimely, unreasonable, rambling, and pointless. This is the fourfold impurity by way of speech.

And how is impurity threefold by way of mind? It’s when someone is covetous. They covet the wealth and belongings of others: ‘Oh, if only their belongings were mine!’

They have ill will and malicious intentions: ‘May these sentient beings be killed, slaughtered, slain, destroyed, or annihilated!’

They have wrong view. Their perspective is distorted: ‘There’s no meaning in giving, sacrifice, or offerings. There’s no fruit or result of good and bad deeds. There’s no afterlife. There’s no such thing as mother and father, or beings that are reborn spontaneously. And there’s no ascetic or brahmin who is rightly comported and rightly practiced, and who describes the afterlife after realizing it with their own insight.’ This is the threefold impurity by way of mind.

These are the ten ways of doing unskillful deeds. When you have these ten ways of doing unskillful deeds, then if you rise early, whether or not you stroke the earth from your bed, you’re still impure.

Whether or not you stroke fresh cow dung, you’re still impure.

Whether or not you stroke green grass, you’re still impure.

Whether or not you serve the sacred flame, you’re still impure.

Whether or not you revere the sun with cupped palms, you’re still impure.

Whether or not you immerse yourself in water three times, you’re still impure. Why is that? These ten ways of doing unskillful deeds are impure and make things impure.

It’s because of those who do these ten kinds of unskillful deeds that hell, the animal realm, the ghost realm, or any other bad places are found.

Cunda, purity is threefold by way of body, fourfold by way of speech, and threefold by way of mind.

And how is purity threefold by way of body? It’s when someone gives up killing living creatures, renouncing the rod and the sword. They’re scrupulous and kind, living full of sympathy for all living beings.

They give up stealing. They don’t, with the intention to commit theft, take the wealth or belongings of others from village or wilderness.

They give up sexual misconduct. They don’t have relations with women who have their mother, father, both mother and father, brother, sister, relatives, or clan as guardian. They don’t have relations with a woman who is protected on principle, or who has a husband, or whose violation is punishable by law, or even one who has been garlanded as a token of betrothal.

This is the threefold purity by way of body.

And how is purity fourfold by way of speech? It’s when someone gives up lying. They’re summoned to a council, an assembly, a family meeting, a guild, or to the royal court, and asked to bear witness: ‘Please, my friend, say what you know.’ Not knowing, they say ‘I don’t know.’ Knowing, they say ‘I know.’ Not seeing, they say ‘I don’t see.’ And seeing, they say ‘I see.’ So they don’t deliberately lie for the sake of themselves or another, or for some trivial worldly reason.

They give up backbiting. They don’t repeat in one place what they heard in another so as to divide people against each other. Instead, they reconcile those who are divided and support those who are united, delighting in harmony, loving harmony, speaking words that promote harmony.

They give up harsh speech. They speak in a way that’s mellow, pleasing to the ear, endearing, going to the heart, polite, and likable and agreeable to the people.

They give up talking nonsense. Their words are timely, true, and meaningful, in line with the teaching and training. They say things at the right time which are valuable, reasonable, succinct, and beneficial.

This is the fourfold purity by way of speech.

And how is purity threefold by way of mind? It’s when someone is content. They don’t covet the wealth and belongings of others: ‘Oh, if only their belongings were mine!’

They have a kind heart and loving intentions: ‘May these sentient beings live free of enmity and ill will, untroubled and happy!’

They have right view, an undistorted perspective: ‘There is meaning in giving, sacrifice, and offerings. There are fruits and results of good and bad deeds. There is an afterlife. There are such things as mother and father, and beings that are reborn spontaneously. And there are ascetics and brahmins who are rightly comported and rightly practiced, and who describe the afterlife after realizing it with their own insight.’

This is the threefold purity by way of mind.

These are the ten ways of doing skillful deeds. When you have these ten ways of doing skillful deeds, then if you rise early, whether or not you stroke the earth from your bed, you’re still pure.

Whether or not you stroke fresh cow dung, you’re still pure.

Whether or not you stroke green grass, you’re still pure.

Whether or not you serve the sacred flame, you’re still pure.

Whether or not you revere the sun with cupped palms, you’re still pure.

Whether or not you immerse yourself in water three times, you’re still pure. Why is that? These ten ways of doing skillful deeds are pure and make things pure.

It’s because of those who do these ten kinds of skillful deeds that gods, humans, or any other good places are found.”

When he said this, Cunda the smith said to the Buddha, “Excellent, sir! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the Buddha remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

AN 10.177 With Jānussoṇi Jāṇussoṇisutta

Then the brahmin Jānussoṇi went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him.

When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha, “We who are known as brahmins give gifts and perform memorial rites for the dead: ‘May this gift aid my departed relatives and kin. May they partake of this gift.’ But does this gift really aid departed relatives and kin? Do they actually partake of it?”

“It aids them if the conditions are right, brahmin, but not if the conditions are wrong.”

“Then, worthy Gotama, what are the right and wrong conditions?”

“Brahmin, take someone who kills living creatures, steals, and commits sexual misconduct. They use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. And they’re covetous, malicious, with wrong view. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in hell. There they survive feeding on the food of the hell beings. The conditions there are wrong, so the gift does not aid the one who lives there.

Take someone else who kills living creatures … and has wrong view. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the animal realm. There they survive feeding on the food of the beings in the animal realm. The conditions there too are wrong, so the gift does not aid the one who lives there.

Take someone else who doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, or commit sexual misconduct. They don’t use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. And they’re contented, kind-hearted, with right view. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the human realm. There they survive feeding on human food. The conditions there too are wrong, so the gift does not aid the one who lives there.

Take someone else who doesn’t kill living creatures … and has right view. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of the gods. There they survive feeding on the food of the gods. The conditions there too are wrong, so the gift does not aid the one who lives there.

Take someone else who kills living creatures … and has wrong view. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the ghost realm. There they survive feeding on the food of the beings in the ghost realm. Or else they survive feeding on what friends and colleagues, relatives and kin provide them with from here. The conditions there are right, so the gift aids the one who lives there.”

“But worthy Gotama, who partakes of that gift if the departed relative is not reborn in that place?”

“Other departed relatives reborn there will partake of that gift.”

“But who partakes of the gift when neither that relative nor other relatives have been reborn in that place?”

“It’s impossible, brahmin, it cannot happen that that place is vacant of departed relatives in all this long time. It’s never fruitless for the donor.”

“Does the worthy Gotama propose this even when the conditions are wrong?”

“I propose this even when the conditions are wrong. Take someone who kills living creatures, steals, and commits sexual misconduct. They use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. And they’re covetous, malicious, with wrong view. They give to ascetics or brahmins such things as food, drink, clothing, vehicles; garlands, fragrance, and makeup; and bed, house, and lighting. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of elephants. There they get to have food and drink, garlands and various adornments.

Since in this life they killed living creatures … and had wrong view, they were reborn in the company of elephants. Since they gave to ascetics or brahmins … they get to have food and drink, garlands and various adornments.

Take someone else who kills living creatures … and has wrong view. They give to ascetics or brahmins … When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of horses. … cattle … dogs. There they get to have food and drink, garlands and various adornments.

Since in this life they killed living creatures … and had wrong view, they were reborn in the company of dogs. Since they gave to ascetics or brahmins … they get to have food and drink, garlands and various adornments.

Take someone else who doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, or commit sexual misconduct. They don’t use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. And they’re contented, kind-hearted, with right view. They give to ascetics or brahmins … When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the human realm. There they get to have the five kinds of human sensual stimulation.

Since in this life they didn’t kill living creatures … and had right view, they were reborn in the company of humans. Since they gave to ascetics or brahmins … they get to have the five kinds of human sensual stimulation.

Take someone else who doesn’t kill living creatures … and has right view. They give to ascetics or brahmins … When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of the gods. There they get to have the five kinds of heavenly sensual stimulation.

Since in this life they didn’t kill living creatures … and had right view, they were reborn in the company of the gods. Since they gave to ascetics or brahmins … they get to have the five kinds of heavenly sensual stimulation. It’s never fruitless for the donor.”

“It’s incredible, worthy Gotama, it’s amazing, This is quite enough to justify giving gifts and performing memorial rites for the dead, since it’s never fruitless for the donor.”

“That’s so true, brahmin. It’s never fruitless for the donor.”

“Excellent, worthy Gotama! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the worthy Gotama remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

The Great Chapter

AN 10.21 The Lion’s Roar Sīhanādasutta

“Mendicants, toward evening the lion, king of beasts, emerges from his den, yawns, surveys the four quarters, and roars his lion’s roar three times. Then he sets out on the hunt. Why is that? ‘May I not injure any little creatures on unclear ground.’

‘Lion’ is a term for the Realized One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha. When the Realized One teaches Dhamma to an assembly, this is his lion’s roar.

The Realized One possesses ten powers of a Realized One. With these he claims the bull’s place, roars his lion’s roar in the assemblies, and turns the divine wheel. What ten? Firstly, the Realized One truly understands the possible as possible and the impossible as impossible. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. Relying on this he claims the bull’s place, roars his lion’s roar in the assemblies, and turns the divine wheel.

Furthermore, the Realized One truly understands the result of deeds undertaken in the past, future, and present in terms of grounds and causes. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, the Realized One truly understands where all paths of practice lead. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, the Realized One truly understands the world with its many and diverse elements. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, the Realized One truly understands the diverse convictions of sentient beings. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, the Realized One truly understands the faculties of other sentient beings and other individuals after encompassing them with his mind. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, the Realized One truly understands corruption, cleansing, and emergence regarding the absorptions, liberations, immersions, and attainments. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, the Realized One recollects many kinds of past lives. That is: one, two, three, four, five, ten, twenty, thirty, forty, fifty, a hundred, a thousand, a hundred thousand rebirths; many eons of the world contracting, many eons of the world expanding, many eons of the world contracting and expanding. He remembers: ‘There, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn somewhere else. There, too, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn here.’ Thus he recollects his many past lives, with features and details. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, with clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, the Realized One sees sentient beings passing away and being reborn—inferior and superior, beautiful and ugly, in a good place or a bad place. He understands how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds. ‘These dear beings did bad things by way of body, speech, and mind. They denounced the noble ones; they had wrong view; and they chose to act out of that wrong view. When their body broke up, after death, they were reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. These dear beings, however, did good things by way of body, speech, and mind. They never denounced the noble ones; they had right view; and they chose to act out of that right view. When their body broke up, after death, they were reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.’ And so, with clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, he sees sentient beings passing away and being reborn—inferior and superior, beautiful and ugly, in a good place or a bad place. He understands how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, the Realized One has realized the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and lives having realized it with his own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

These are the ten powers of a Realized One that the Realized One possesses. With these he claims the bull’s place, roars his lion’s roar in the assemblies, and turns the divine wheel.”

AN 10.22 Hypotheses Adhivuttipadasutta

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him:

“Ānanda, I claim to be self-assured regarding the teachings that lead to realizing by insight the various different hypotheses. So I am able to teach the Dhamma in appropriate ways to different people. Practicing accordingly, when something exists they’ll know it exists. When it doesn’t exist they’ll know it doesn’t exist. When something is inferior they’ll know it’s inferior. When it’s superior they’ll know it’s superior. When something is not supreme they’ll know it’s not supreme. When it is supreme they’ll know it’s supreme. And they will know or see or realize it in whatever way it should be known or seen or realized. This is possible. But this is the unsurpassable knowledge, that is: truly knowing each and every case. And Ānanda, I say that there is no other knowledge better or finer than this.

The Realized One possesses ten powers of a Realized One. With these he claims the bull’s place, roars his lion’s roar in the assemblies, and turns the divine wheel. What ten? Firstly, the Realized One truly understands the possible as possible, and the impossible as impossible. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. Relying on this he claims the bull’s place, roars his lion’s roar in the assemblies, and turns the divine wheel.

Furthermore, the Realized One truly understands the result of deeds undertaken in the past, future, and present in terms of grounds and causes. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, the Realized One truly understands where all paths of practice lead. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, the Realized One truly understands the world with its many and diverse elements. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, the Realized One truly understands the diverse convictions of sentient beings. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, the Realized One truly understands the faculties of other sentient beings and other individuals after encompassing them with his mind. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, the Realized One truly understands corruption, cleansing, and emergence regarding the absorptions, liberations, immersions, and attainments. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, the Realized One recollects many kinds of past lives, with features and details. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, with clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, the Realized One sees sentient beings passing away and being reborn—inferior and superior, beautiful and ugly, in a good place or a bad place. He understands how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, the Realized One has realized the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and lives having realized it with his own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

These are the ten powers of a Realized One that the Realized One possesses. With these he claims the bull’s place, roars his lion’s roar in the assemblies, and turns the divine wheel.”

AN 10.23 Body Kāyasutta

“Mendicants, there are things that should be given up by the body, not by speech. There are things that should be given up by speech, not by the body. There are things that should be given up neither by the body, nor by speech, but by seeing again and again with wisdom.

And what are the things that should be given up by the body, not by speech? It’s when a mendicant has committed a certain unskillful offense by way of body. After examination, sensible spiritual companions say this to them: ‘Venerable, you’ve committed a certain unskillful offense by way of body. Please give up that bad bodily conduct and develop good bodily conduct.’ When spoken to by their sensible spiritual companions they give up that bad bodily conduct and develop good bodily conduct. These are the things that should be given up by the body, not by speech.

And what are the things that should be given up by speech, not by the body? It’s when a mendicant has committed a certain unskillful offense by way of speech. After examination, sensible spiritual companions say this to them: ‘Venerable, you’ve committed a certain unskillful offense by way of speech. Please give up that bad verbal conduct and develop good verbal conduct.’ When spoken to by their sensible spiritual companions they give up that bad verbal conduct and develop good verbal conduct. These are the things that should be given up by speech, not by the body.

And what are the things that should be given up neither by the body, nor by speech, but by seeing again and again with wisdom? Greed … hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … and stinginess are things that should be given up neither by the body, nor by speech, but by seeing again and again with wisdom.

Nasty jealousy should be given up neither by the body, nor by speech, but by seeing again and again with wisdom. And what is nasty jealousy? It’s when a householder or their child is prospering in money, grain, silver, or gold. And a bondservant or dependent thinks: ‘Oh, may that householder or their child not prosper in money, grain, silver, or gold!’ Or an ascetic or brahmin receives robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. And some other ascetic or brahmin thinks: ‘Oh, may that venerable not receive robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick.’ This is called nasty jealousy.

Corrupt wishes should be given up neither by the body, nor by speech, but by seeing again and again with wisdom. And what are corrupt wishes? It’s when a faithless person wishes to be known as faithful. An unethical person wishes to be known as ethical. An unlearned person wishes to be known as learned. A lover of company wishes to be known as secluded. A lazy person wishes to be known as energetic. An unmindful person wishes to be known as mindful. A person without immersion wishes to be known as having immersion. A witless person wishes to be known as wise. Someone who has not ended the defilements wishes to be known as having ended the defilements. These are called corrupt wishes. Corrupt wishes should be given up neither by the body, nor by speech, but by seeing again and again with wisdom.

Suppose that greed masters that mendicant and keeps going. Or that hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … or corrupt wishes master them and keep going. You should know of them: ‘This venerable does not have the understanding that would eliminate greed, so greed masters them and keeps going. They don’t have the understanding that would eliminate hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … or corrupt wishes, so corrupt wishes master them and keep going.’

Suppose that greed does not master that mendicant and keep going. Or that hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … or corrupt wishes don’t master that mendicant and keep going. You should know of them: ‘This venerable has the understanding that eliminates greed, so greed doesn’t master them and keep going. They have the understanding that eliminates hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … and corrupt wishes, so corrupt wishes don’t master them and keep going.’”

AN 10.24 By Mahācunda Mahācundasutta

At one time Venerable Mahācunda was staying in the land of the Cetīs at Sahajāti. There he addressed the mendicants: “Reverends, mendicants!”

“Reverend,” they replied. Venerable Mahācunda said this:

“Reverends, a mendicant who makes a declaration of knowledge says: ‘I know this teaching, I see this teaching.’ Suppose that greed masters that mendicant and keeps going. Or that hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … or corrupt wishes master that mendicant and keep going. You should know of them: ‘This venerable does not have the understanding that would eliminate greed, so greed masters them and keeps going. They don’t have the understanding that would eliminate hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … or corrupt wishes, so corrupt wishes master them and keep going.’

A mendicant who makes a declaration of development says: ‘I am developed in physical endurance, ethics, mind, and wisdom.’ Suppose that greed masters that mendicant and keeps going. Or that hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … or corrupt wishes master that mendicant and keep going. You should know of them: ‘This venerable does not have the understanding that would eliminate greed, so greed masters them and keeps going. They don’t have the understanding that would eliminate hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … or corrupt wishes, so corrupt wishes master them and keep going.’

A mendicant who makes a declaration of both knowledge and development says: ‘I know this teaching, I see this teaching. And I am developed in physical endurance, ethics, mind, and wisdom.’ Suppose that greed masters that mendicant and keeps going. Or that hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … or corrupt wishes master that mendicant and keep going. You should know of them: ‘This venerable does not have the understanding that would eliminate greed, so greed masters them and keeps going. They don’t have the understanding that would eliminate hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … or corrupt wishes, so corrupt wishes master them and keep going.’

Suppose a poor, needy, and penniless person was to declare themselves to be rich, affluent, and wealthy. But when it came time to make a payment they weren’t able to come up with any money, grain, silver, or gold. They would know of them: ‘This person declares themselves to be rich, affluent, and wealthy, but they are in fact poor, penniless, and needy.’ Why is that? Because when it came time to make a payment they weren’t able to come up with any money, grain, silver, or gold.

In the same way, a mendicant who makes a declaration of knowledge and development says: ‘I know this teaching, I see this teaching. And I am developed in physical endurance, ethics, mind, and wisdom.’ Suppose that greed masters that mendicant and keeps going. Or that hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … or corrupt wishes master that mendicant and keep going. You should know of them: ‘This venerable does not have the understanding that would eliminate greed, so greed masters them and keeps going. They don’t have the understanding that would eliminate hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … or corrupt wishes, so corrupt wishes master them and keep going.’

A mendicant who makes a declaration of knowledge says: ‘I know this teaching, I see this teaching.’ Suppose that greed does not master that mendicant and keep going. Or that hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … or corrupt wishes don’t master that mendicant and keep going. You should know of them: ‘This venerable has the understanding that eliminates greed, so greed doesn’t master them and keep going. They have the understanding that eliminates hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … and corrupt wishes, so corrupt wishes don’t master them and keep going.’

A mendicant who makes a declaration of development says: ‘I am developed in physical endurance, ethics, mind, and wisdom.’ Suppose that greed does not master that mendicant and keep going. Or that hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … or corrupt wishes don’t master that mendicant and keep going. You should know of them: ‘This venerable has the understanding that eliminates greed, so greed doesn’t master them and keep going. They have the understanding that eliminates hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … and corrupt wishes, so corrupt wishes don’t master them and keep going.’

A mendicant who makes a declaration of both knowledge and development says: ‘I know this teaching, I see this teaching. And I am developed in physical endurance, ethics, mind, and wisdom.’ Suppose that greed does not master that mendicant and keep going. Or that hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … or corrupt wishes don’t master that mendicant and keep going. You should know of them: ‘This venerable has the understanding that eliminates greed, so greed doesn’t master them and keep going. They have the understanding that eliminates hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … and corrupt wishes, so corrupt wishes don’t master them and keep going.’

Suppose a rich, affluent, and wealthy person was to declare themselves to be rich, affluent, and wealthy. And whenever it came time to make a payment they were able to come up with the money, grain, silver, or gold. They would know of them: ‘This person declares themselves to be rich, affluent, and wealthy, and they are in fact rich, affluent, and wealthy.’ Why is that? Because when it came time to make a payment they were able to come up with the money, grain, silver, or gold.

In the same way, a mendicant who makes a declaration of knowledge and development says: ‘I know this teaching, I see this teaching. And I am developed in physical endurance, ethics, mind, and wisdom.’ Suppose that greed does not master that mendicant and keep going. Or that hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … or corrupt wishes don’t master that mendicant and keep going. You should know of them: ‘This venerable has the understanding that eliminates greed, so greed doesn’t master them and keep going. They have the understanding that eliminates hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … stinginess … nasty jealousy … and corrupt wishes, so corrupt wishes don’t master them and keep going.’”

AN 10.25 Meditation on Universals Kasiṇasutta

“Mendicants, there are these ten universal dimensions of meditation. What ten? Someone perceives the meditation on universal earth above, below, across, undivided and limitless. They perceive the meditation on universal water … the meditation on universal fire … the meditation on universal air … the meditation on universal blue … the meditation on universal yellow … the meditation on universal red … the meditation on universal white … the meditation on universal space … They perceive the meditation on universal consciousness above, below, across, undivided and limitless. These are the ten universal dimensions of meditation.”

AN 10.26 With Kāḷī Kāḷīsutta

At one time Venerable Mahākaccāna was staying in the land of the Avantis near Kuraraghara on Steep Mountain.

Then the laywoman Kāḷī of Kurughara went up to Venerable Mahākaccāna, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him, “Sir, this was said by the Buddha in ‘The Maidens’ Questions’:

‘I’ve reached the goal, peace of heart.
Having conquered the army of the likable and pleasant,
alone, practicing absorption, I awakened to bliss.
That’s why I don’t get too close to people,
and no one gets too close to me.’

How should we see the detailed meaning of the Buddha’s brief statement?”

“Sister, some ascetics and brahmins regard the attainment of the meditation on universal earth to be the ultimate. Thinking ‘this is the goal’, they are reborn. The Buddha directly knew the extent to which the attainment of the meditation on universal earth was the ultimate. Directly knowing this he saw the beginning, the drawback, and the escape. And he saw the knowledge and vision of what is the path and what is not the path. Because he saw the beginning, the drawback, and the escape, and he saw the knowledge and vision of what is the path and what is not the path, he knew that he had reached the goal, peace of heart.

Some ascetics and brahmins regard the attainment of the meditation on universal water to be the ultimate. Thinking ‘this is the goal’, they are reborn. … Some ascetics and brahmins regard the attainment of the meditation on universal fire … universal air … universal blue … universal yellow … universal red … universal white … universal space … universal consciousness to be the ultimate. Thinking ‘this is the goal’, they are reborn. The Buddha directly knew the extent to which the attainment of the meditation on universal consciousness was the ultimate. Directly knowing this he saw the beginning, the drawback, and the escape. And he saw the knowledge and vision of what is the path and what is not the path. Because he saw the beginning, the drawback, and the escape, and he saw the knowledge and vision of what is the path and what is not the path, he knew that he had reached the goal, peace of heart.

So, sister, that’s how to understand the detailed meaning of what the Buddha said in brief in ‘The Maidens’ Questions’:

‘I’ve reached the goal, peace of heart.
Having conquered the army of the likable and pleasant,
alone, practicing absorption, I awakened to bliss.
That’s why I don’t get too close to people,
and no one gets too close to me.’”

AN 10.27 The Great Questions (1st) Paṭhamamahāpañhāsutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery.

Then several mendicants robed up in the morning and, taking their bowls and robes, entered Sāvatthī for alms. Then it occurred to him, “It’s too early to wander for alms in Sāvatthī. Why don’t we visit the monastery for the wanderers of other religions?”

Then they went to the monastery for the wanderers of other religions and exchanged greetings with the wanderers there. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, they sat down to one side. The wanderers said to them:

“Reverends, the ascetic Gotama teaches his disciples like this: ‘Please, mendicants, directly know all things. Meditate having directly known all things.’ We too teach our disciples: ‘Please, reverends, directly know all things. Live having directly known all things.’ What, then, is the difference between the ascetic Gotama’s teaching and instruction and ours?”

Those mendicants neither approved nor rejected that statement of the wanderers of other religions. They rose from their seats, thinking, “We will learn the meaning of this statement from the Buddha himself.”

Then, after the meal, when they returned from almsround, they went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened.

“Mendicants, when wanderers of other religions say this, you should say to them: ‘One thing: question, summary recital, and answer. Two … Three … Four … Five … Six … Seven … Eight … Nine … Ten things: question, summary recital, and answer.’ Questioned like this, the wanderers of other religions would be stumped, and, in addition, would get frustrated. Why is that? Because they’re out of their element. I don’t see anyone in this world—with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans—who could provide a satisfying answer to these questions except the Realized One or his disciple or someone who has heard it from them.

‘One thing: question, summary recital, and answer.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Becoming completely disillusioned, dispassionate, and freed regarding one thing, seeing its limits and fully comprehending its meaning, a mendicant makes an end of suffering in this very life. What one thing? ‘All sentient beings are sustained by food.’ Becoming completely disillusioned, dispassionate, and freed regarding this one thing, seeing its limits and fully comprehending its meaning, a mendicant makes an end of suffering in this very life. ‘One thing: question, summary recital, and answer.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

What two? Name and form. …

What three? Three feelings. …

What four? The four foods. …

What five? The five grasping aggregates. …

What six? The six interior sense fields. …

What seven? The seven planes of consciousness. …

What eight? The eight worldly conditions. …

What nine? The nine abodes of sentient beings. …

‘Ten things: question, summary recital, and answer.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Becoming completely disillusioned, dispassionate, and freed regarding ten things, seeing their limits and fully comprehending their meaning, a mendicant makes an end of suffering in this very life. What ten? The ten ways of performing unskillful deeds. Becoming completely disillusioned, dispassionate, and freed regarding these ten things, seeing their limits and fully comprehending their meaning, a mendicant makes an end of suffering in this very life. ‘Ten things: question, summary recital, and answer.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.”

AN 10.28 The Great Questions (2nd) Dutiyamahāpañhāsutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Kajaṅgalā in a bamboo grove. Then several lay followers of Kajaṅgalā went to the nun Kajaṅgalikā, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to her:

“Ma’am, this was said by the Buddha in ‘The Great Questions’: ‘One thing: question, summary recital, and answer. Two … Three … Four … Five … Six … Seven … Eight … Nine … Ten things: question, summary recital, and answer.’ How should we see the detailed meaning of the Buddha’s brief statement?”

“Respectable sirs, I haven’t heard and learned this in the presence of the Buddha or from esteemed mendicants. But as to how it seems to me, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, ma’am,” replied the lay followers. The nun Kajaṅgalikā said this:

“‘One thing: question, summary recital, and answer.’ That’s what the Buddha said, but why did he say it? Becoming completely disillusioned, dispassionate, and freed regarding one thing, seeing its limits and fully comprehending its meaning, a mendicant makes an end of suffering in this very life. What one thing? ‘All sentient beings are sustained by food.’ Becoming completely disillusioned, dispassionate, and freed regarding this one thing, seeing its limits and fully comprehending its meaning, a mendicant makes an end of suffering in this very life. ‘One thing: question, summary recital, and answer.’ That’s what the Buddha said, and this is why he said it.

What two? Name and form. … What three? Three feelings. …

With a mind well developed in four things—seeing their limits and fully comprehending their meaning—a mendicant makes an end of suffering in this very life. What four? The four kinds of mindfulness meditation. … With a mind well developed in these four things—seeing their limits and fully fathoming their meaning—a mendicant makes an end of suffering in this very life. …

What five? The five faculties. … What six? The six elements of escape. … What seven? The seven awakening factors. … What eight? The noble eightfold path. …

Becoming completely disillusioned, dispassionate, and freed regarding nine things, seeing their limits and fully comprehending their meaning, a mendicant makes an end of suffering in this very life. What nine? The nine abodes of sentient beings. Becoming completely disillusioned, dispassionate, and freed regarding these nine things, seeing their limits and fully comprehending their meaning, a mendicant makes an end of suffering in this very life.

‘Ten things: question, summary recital, and answer.’ That’s what the Buddha said, but why did he say it? Becoming well developed in ten things—seeing their limits and fully fathoming their meaning—a mendicant makes an end of suffering in this very life. What ten? The ten ways of performing skillful deeds. With a mind well developed in these ten things—seeing their limits and fully fathoming their meaning—a mendicant makes an end of suffering in this very life. ‘Ten things: question, summary recital, and answer.’ That’s what the Buddha said, and this is why he said it.

That’s how I understand the detailed meaning of what the Buddha said in brief in ‘The Great Questions’. If you wish, you may go to the Buddha and ask him about this. You should remember it in line with the Buddha’s answer.”

“Yes, ma’am,” replied those lay followers, approving and agreeing with what the nun Kajaṅgalikā said. Then they rose from their seats, bowed, and respectfully circled her, keeping her on their right. Then they went to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and informed the Buddha of all they had discussed.

“Good, good, householders. The nun Kajaṅgalikā is astute, she has great wisdom. If you came to me and asked this question, I would answer it in exactly the same way as the nun Kajaṅgalikā. That is what it means, and that’s how you should remember it.”

AN 10.29 Kosala (1st) Paṭhamakosalasutta

“As far as Kāsi and Kosala extend, and as far as the dominion of King Pasenadi of Kosala extends, King Pasenadi is said to be the foremost. But even King Pasenadi decays and perishes.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with it. Their desire fades away even for the foremost, let alone the inferior.

A galaxy extends a thousand times as far as the moon and sun revolve and the dazzling ones light up the quarters. In that galaxy there are a thousand moons, a thousand suns, a thousand Sinerus king of mountains, a thousand Black Plum Tree Lands, a thousand lands west of Godāvarī, a thousand lands north of Kuru, a thousand lands east of Videha, four thousand oceans, four thousand great kings, a thousand realms of the gods of the four great kings, a thousand realms of the gods of the thirty-three, of the gods of Yama, of the joyful gods, of the gods who love to create, of the gods who control what is created by others, and a thousand realms of divinity. As far as the galaxy extends, the Great Divinity is said to be the foremost. But even the Great Divinity decays and perishes.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with it. Their desire fades away even for the foremost, let alone the inferior.

There comes a time when this cosmos contracts. As it contracts, most sentient beings migrate to the realm of sublime luminosity. There they are mind-made, feeding on rapture, self-radiant, wandering in midair, steadily glorious, and they remain like that for a very long time. When the cosmos is contracting, the gods of sublime luminosity are said to be the foremost. But even the gods of sublime luminosity decay and perish.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with it. Their desire fades away even for the foremost, let alone the inferior.

There are these ten universal dimensions of meditation. What ten? Someone perceives the meditation on universal earth above, below, across, undivided and limitless. They perceive the meditation on universal water … the meditation on universal fire … the meditation on universal air … the meditation on universal blue … the meditation on universal yellow … the meditation on universal red … the meditation on universal white … the meditation on universal space … They perceive the meditation on universal consciousness above, below, across, undivided and limitless. These are the ten universal dimensions of meditation.

The best of these ten universal dimensions of meditation is when someone perceives the meditation on universal consciousness above, below, across, undivided and limitless. Some sentient beings perceive like this. But even the sentient beings who perceive like this decay and perish.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with it. Their desire fades away even for the foremost, let alone the inferior.

There are these eight dimensions of mastery. What eight? Perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, limited, both pretty and ugly. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ This is the first dimension of mastery.

Perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, limitless, both pretty and ugly. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ This is the second dimension of mastery.

Not perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, limited, both pretty and ugly. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ This is the third dimension of mastery.

Not perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, limitless, both pretty and ugly. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ This is the fourth dimension of mastery.

Not perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, blue, with blue color and blue appearance. They’re like a flax flower that’s blue, with blue color and blue appearance. Or a cloth from Varanasi that’s smoothed on both sides, blue, with blue color and blue appearance. In the same way, not perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, blue, with blue color and blue appearance. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ This is the fifth dimension of mastery.

Not perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, yellow, with yellow color and yellow appearance. They’re like a champak flower that’s yellow, with yellow color and yellow appearance. Or a cloth from Varanasi that’s smoothed on both sides, yellow, with yellow color and yellow appearance. In the same way, not perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, yellow, with yellow color and yellow appearance. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ This is the sixth dimension of mastery.

Not perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, red, with red color and red appearance. They’re like a scarlet mallow flower that’s red, with red color and red appearance. Or a cloth from Varanasi that’s smoothed on both sides, red, with red color and red appearance. In the same way, not perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, red, with red color and red appearance. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ This is the seventh dimension of mastery.

Not perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, white, with white color and white appearance. They’re like the morning star that’s white, with white color and white appearance. Or a cloth from Varanasi that’s smoothed on both sides, white, with white color and white appearance. In the same way, not perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, white, with white color and white appearance. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ This is the eighth dimension of mastery. These are the eight dimensions of mastery.

The best of these dimensions of mastery is when someone, not perceiving form internally, sees forms externally, white, with white color and white appearance. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ Some sentient beings perceive like this. But even the sentient beings who perceive like this decay and perish.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with it. Their desire fades away even for the foremost, let alone the inferior.

There are four ways of practice. What four?

Painful practice with slow insight,
painful practice with swift insight,
pleasant practice with slow insight, and
pleasant practice with swift insight.

These are the four ways of practice.

The best of these four ways of practice is the pleasant practice with swift insight. Some sentient beings practice like this. But even the sentient beings who practice like this decay and perish.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with it. Their desire fades away even for the foremost, let alone the inferior.

There are these four perceptions. What four?

One individual perceives the limited.
One individual perceives the expansive.
One individual perceives the limitless.
One individual, aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, perceives the dimension of nothingness.

These are the four perceptions.

The best of these four perceptions is when someone, aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, perceives the dimension of nothingness. Some sentient beings perceive like this. But even the sentient beings who perceive like this decay and perish.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with it. Their desire fades away even for the foremost, let alone the inferior.

This is the best of the convictions of outsiders, that is: ‘I might not be, and it might not be mine. I will not be, and it will not be mine.’ When someone has such a view, you can expect that they will not be attracted to continued existence, and they will not be repulsed by the cessation of continued existence. Some sentient beings have such a view. But even the sentient beings who have views like this decay and perish.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with it. Their desire fades away even for the foremost, let alone the inferior.

There are some ascetics and brahmins who advocate the ultimate purity of the spirit. This is the best of the advocates of the ultimate purity of the spirit, that is, when someone, going totally beyond the dimension of nothingness, enters and remains in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They teach Dhamma in order to directly know and realize this. Some sentient beings have such a doctrine. But even the sentient beings who have such a doctrine decay and perish.

Seeing this, a learned noble disciple grows disillusioned with it. Their desire fades away even for the foremost, let alone the inferior.

There are some ascetics and brahmins who advocate ultimate extinguishment in this very life. This is the best of those who advocate extinguishment in this very life, that is, liberation by not grasping after truly understanding the origin, disappearance, gratification, drawback, and escape of the six fields of contact. Though I state and assert this, certain ascetics and brahmins misrepresent me with the incorrect, hollow, false, untruthful claim: ‘The ascetic Gotama doesn’t advocate the complete understanding of sensual pleasures, forms, or feelings.’ But I do advocate the complete understanding of sensual pleasures, forms, and feelings. And I advocate complete extinguishment with no fuel for grasping in this very life, wishless, quenched, and cooled.”

AN 10.30 Kosala (2nd) Dutiyakosalasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery.

Now at that time King Pasenadi of Kosala returned from combat after winning a battle and succeeding in his strategy. Then King Pasenadi of Kosala went to the monastery. He went by carriage as far as the terrain allowed, then descended and entered the monastery on foot.

At that time several mendicants were walking mindfully in the open air. Then King Pasenadi of Kosala went up to them and said, “Sirs, where is the Blessed One at present, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha? For I want to see the Buddha.”

“Great king, that’s his dwelling, with the door closed. Approach it quietly, without hurrying; go onto the porch, clear your throat, and knock on the door-panel. The Buddha will open the door.”

So the king approached the Buddha’s dwelling, cleared his throat and knocked on the door-panel, and the Buddha opened the door. Then King Pasenadi entered the Buddha’s dwelling. He bowed with his head to the Buddha’s feet, caressing them and covering them with kisses, and pronounced his name: “Sir, I am Pasenadi, king of Kosala! I am Pasenadi, king of Kosala!”

“But, Great King, for what reason do you act with such utmost deference for this body, conveying your manifest love?”

“Sir, it’s because of my gratitude and thanks for the Buddha that I act with such utmost deference, conveying my manifest love.

The Buddha is practicing for the welfare and happiness of the people. He has established many people in the noble system, that is, the principles of goodness and skillfulness. This is a reason that I act with such utmost deference for the Buddha, conveying my manifest love.

Furthermore, the Buddha is ethical, possessing ethical conduct that is mature, noble, and skillful. This is another reason that I act with such utmost deference for the Buddha, conveying my manifest love.

Furthermore, the Buddha lives in the wilderness, frequenting remote lodgings in the wilderness and the forest. This is another reason that I act with such utmost deference for the Buddha, conveying my manifest love.

Furthermore, the Buddha is content with any kind of robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. This is another reason that I act with such utmost deference for the Buddha, conveying my manifest love.

Furthermore, the Buddha is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world. This is another reason that I act with such utmost deference for the Buddha, conveying my manifest love.

Furthermore, the Buddha gets to take part in talk about self-effacement that helps open the heart, when he wants, without trouble or difficulty. That is, talk about fewness of wishes, contentment, seclusion, aloofness, arousing energy, ethics, immersion, wisdom, freedom, and the knowledge and vision of freedom. This is another reason that I act with such utmost deference for the Buddha, conveying my manifest love.

Furthermore, the Buddha gets the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when he wants, without trouble or difficulty. This is another reason that I act with such utmost deference for the Buddha, conveying my manifest love.

Furthermore, the Buddha recollects many kinds of past lives. That is: one, two, three, four, five, ten, twenty, thirty, forty, fifty, a hundred, a thousand, a hundred thousand rebirths; many eons of the world contracting, many eons of the world expanding, many eons of the world contracting and expanding. He remembers: ‘There, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn somewhere else. There, too, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn here.’ And so he recollects his many kinds of past lives, with features and details. This is another reason that I act with such utmost deference for the Buddha, conveying my manifest love.

Furthermore, with clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, the Buddha sees sentient beings passing away and being reborn—inferior and superior, beautiful and ugly, in a good place or a bad place. He understands how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds. ‘These dear beings did bad things by way of body, speech, and mind. They denounced the noble ones; they had wrong view; and they chose to act out of that wrong view. When their body broke up, after death, they were reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. These dear beings, however, did good things by way of body, speech, and mind. They never denounced the noble ones; they had right view; and they chose to act out of that right view. When their body broke up, after death, they were reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.’ He understands how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds. This is another reason that I act with such utmost deference for the Buddha, conveying my manifest love.

Furthermore, the Buddha has realized the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and lives having realized it with his own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. This is another reason that I act with such utmost deference for the Buddha, conveying my manifest love.

Well, now, sir, I must go. I have many duties, and much to do.”

“Please, Great King, go at your convenience.” Then King Pasenadi rose from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before leaving.

The Chapter on a Protector

AN 10.11 Lodgings Senāsanasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with five factors, using and frequenting lodgings with five factors, will soon realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they will live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.

And how does a mendicant have five factors? It’s when a noble disciple has faith in the Realized One’s awakening: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ They are rarely ill or unwell. Their stomach digests well, being neither too hot nor too cold, but just right, and fit for meditation. They’re not devious or deceitful. They reveal themselves honestly to the Teacher or sensible spiritual companions. They live with energy roused up for giving up unskillful qualities and embracing skillful qualities. They’re strong, staunchly vigorous, not slacking off when it comes to developing skillful qualities. They’re wise. They have the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. That’s how a mendicant has five factors.

And how does a lodging have five factors? It’s when a lodging is neither too far nor too near, but convenient for coming and going. It’s not bothered by people by day, and at night it’s quiet and still. There’s little disturbance from flies, mosquitoes, wind, sun, and reptiles. While staying in that lodging the necessities of life—robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick—are easy to come by. And in that lodging there are several senior mendicants who are very learned, inheritors of the heritage, who have memorized the teachings, the monastic law, and the outlines. From time to time they go up to those mendicants and ask them questions: ‘Why, sir, does it say this? What does that mean?’ Those venerables reveal what is hidden, clarify what is unclear, and dispel doubt regarding the many doubtful matters. That’s how a lodging has five factors. A mendicant with five factors, using and frequenting lodgings with five factors, will soon realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they will live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.”

AN 10.12 Five Factors Pañcaṅgasutta

“Mendicants, in this teaching and training a mendicant who has given up five factors and possesses five factors is called consummate, accomplished, a supreme person.

And how has a mendicant given up five factors? It’s when a mendicant has given up sensual desire, ill will, dullness and drowsiness, restlessness and remorse, and doubt. That’s how a mendicant has given up five factors.

And how does a mendicant have five factors? It’s when a mendicant has the entire spectrum of an adept’s ethics, immersion, wisdom, freedom, and knowledge and vision of freedom. That’s how a mendicant has five factors.

In this teaching and training a mendicant who has given up five factors and possesses five factors is called consummate, accomplished, a supreme person.

Sensual desire, ill will,
dullness and drowsiness,
restlessness, and doubt
are not found in a mendicant at all.

That sort are accomplished
in an adept’s ethics,
an adept’s immersion,
and freedom and knowledge.

Possessing these five factors,
and rid of five factors,
in this teaching and training
they’re called ‘consummate’.”

AN 10.13 Fetters Saṁyojanasutta

“Mendicants, there are ten fetters. What ten? The five lower fetters and the five higher fetters. What are the five lower fetters? Substantialist view, doubt, misapprehension of precepts and observances, sensual desire, and ill will. These are the five lower fetters.

What are the five higher fetters? Desire for rebirth in the realm of luminous form, desire for rebirth in the formless realm, conceit, restlessness, and ignorance. These are the five higher fetters. These are the ten fetters.”

AN 10.14 Hard-heartedness Cetokhilasutta

“Mendicants, a monk or nun who has not given up five kinds of hard-heartedness and has not severed five shackles of the heart can expect decline, not growth, in skillful qualities, whether by day or by night.

What are the five kinds of hard-heartedness they haven’t given up?

Firstly, a mendicant has doubts about the Teacher. They’re uncertain, undecided, and lacking confidence. This being so, their mind doesn’t incline toward keenness, commitment, persistence, and striving. This is the first kind of hard-heartedness they haven’t given up.

Furthermore, a mendicant has doubts about the teaching … the Saṅgha … the training … A mendicant is angry and upset with their spiritual companions, resentful and closed off. This being so, their mind doesn’t incline toward keenness, commitment, persistence, and striving. This is the fifth kind of hard-heartedness they haven’t given up. These are the five kinds of hard-heartedness they haven’t given up.

What are the five shackles of the heart they haven’t severed? Firstly, a mendicant isn’t free of greed, desire, fondness, thirst, passion, and craving for sensual pleasures. This being so, their mind doesn’t incline toward keenness, commitment, persistence, and striving. This is the first shackle of the heart they haven’t severed.

Furthermore, a mendicant isn’t free of greed for the body … They’re not free of greed for form … They eat as much as they like until their belly is full, then indulge in the pleasures of sleeping, lying down, and drowsing … They lead the spiritual life wishing to be reborn in one of the orders of gods: ‘By this precept or observance or fervent austerity or spiritual practice, may I become one of the gods!’ This being so, their mind doesn’t incline toward keenness, commitment, persistence, and striving. This is the fifth shackle of the heart they haven’t severed. These are the five shackles of the heart they haven’t severed.

A monk or nun who has not given up these five kinds of hard-heartedness and has not severed these five shackles of the heart can expect decline, not growth, in skillful qualities, whether by day or by night.

It’s like the moon in the waning fortnight. Whether by day or by night, its beauty, roundness, luminosity, and diameter and circumference only decline. In the same way, a monk or nun who has not given up these five kinds of hard-heartedness and has not severed these five shackles of the heart can expect decline, not growth, in skillful qualities, whether by day or by night.

A monk or nun who has given up five kinds of hard-heartedness and has severed five shackles of the heart can expect growth, not decline, in skillful qualities, whether by day or by night.

What are the five kinds of hard-heartedness they’ve given up? Firstly, a mendicant has no doubts about the Teacher. They’re not uncertain, undecided, or lacking confidence. This being so, their mind inclines toward keenness, commitment, persistence, and striving. This is the first kind of hard-heartedness they’ve given up.

Furthermore, a mendicant has no doubts about the teaching … the Saṅgha … the training … A mendicant is not angry and upset with their spiritual companions, not resentful or closed off. This being so, their mind inclines toward keenness, commitment, persistence, and striving. This is the fifth kind of hard-heartedness they’ve given up. These are the five kinds of hard-heartedness they’ve given up.

What are the five shackles of the heart they’ve severed? Firstly, a mendicant is rid of greed, desire, fondness, thirst, passion, and craving for sensual pleasures. This being so, their mind inclines toward keenness, commitment, persistence, and striving. This is the first shackle of the heart they’ve severed.

Furthermore, a mendicant is rid of greed for the body … They’re rid of greed for form … They don’t eat as much as they like until their belly is full, then indulge in the pleasures of sleeping, lying down, and drowsing … They don’t lead the spiritual life wishing to be reborn in one of the orders of gods: ‘By this precept or observance or fervent austerity or spiritual practice, may I become one of the gods!’ This being so, their mind inclines toward keenness, commitment, persistence, and striving. This is the fifth shackle of the heart they’ve severed. These are the five shackles of the heart they’ve severed.

A monk or nun who has given up these five kinds of hard-heartedness and has severed these five shackles of the heart can expect growth, not decline, in skillful qualities, whether by day or by night.

It’s like the moon in the waxing fortnight. Whether by day or by night, its beauty, roundness, luminosity, and diameter and circumference only grow. In the same way, a monk or nun who has given up these five kinds of hard-heartedness and has severed these five shackles of the heart can expect growth, not decline, in skillful qualities, whether by day or by night.”

AN 10.15 Diligence Appamādasutta

“Mendicants, the Realized One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha, is said to be the best of all sentient beings—be they footless, with two feet, four feet, or many feet; with form or formless; with perception or without perception or with neither perception nor non-perception. In the same way, all skillful qualities are rooted in diligence and meet at diligence, and diligence is said to be the best of them.

The footprints of all creatures that walk can fit inside an elephant’s footprint, so an elephant’s footprint is said to be the biggest of them all. In the same way, all skillful qualities are rooted in diligence and meet at diligence, and diligence is said to be the best of them.

The rafters of a bungalow all lean to the peak, slope to the peak, and meet at the peak, so the peak is said to be the topmost of them all. In the same way, all skillful qualities are rooted in diligence and meet at diligence, and diligence is said to be the best of them.

Of all kinds of fragrant root, spikenard is said to be the best. In the same way …

Of all kinds of fragrant heartwood, red sandalwood is said to be the best. In the same way …

Of all kinds of fragrant flower, jasmine is said to be the best. In the same way …

All lesser kings are vassals of a wheel-turning monarch, so the wheel-turning monarch is said to be the foremost of them all. In the same way …

The radiance of all the stars is not worth a sixteenth part of the moon’s radiance, so the moon’s radiance is said to be the best of them all. In the same way …

In the autumn the heavens are sunny and cloudless. And as the sun is rising to the firmament, having dispelled all the darkness of space, it shines and glows and dazzles. In the same way …

All the great rivers—that is, the Ganges, Yamunā, Aciravatī, Sarabhū, and Mahī—flow, slant, slope, and incline toward the ocean, and the ocean is said to be the greatest of them. In the same way, all skillful qualities are rooted in diligence and meet at diligence, and diligence is said to be the best of them.”

AN 10.16 Worthy of Offerings Dedicated to the Gods Āhuneyyasutta

“Mendicants, these ten individuals are worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and are the supreme field of merit for the world. What ten? A Realized One, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha; an independent Buddha; one freed both ways; one freed by wisdom; a direct witness; one attained to view; one freed by faith; a follower by faith; a follower of teachings; a lamb of the flock. These are the ten individuals who are worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and are the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 10.17 A Protector (1st) Paṭhamanāthasutta

“Mendicants, you should live with a protector, not without one. Living without a protector is suffering. There are ten qualities that serve as protector. What ten? Firstly, a mendicant is ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken. This is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant is very learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, rehearsing them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant has good friends, companions, and associates. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant is easy to admonish, having qualities that make them easy to admonish. They’re patient, and take instruction respectfully. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant is deft and tireless in a diverse spectrum of duties for their spiritual companions, understanding how to go about things in order to complete and organize the work. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant loves the teachings and is a delight to converse with, being full of joy in the teaching and training. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant lives with energy roused up for giving up unskillful qualities and embracing skillful qualities. They are strong, staunchly vigorous, not slacking off when it comes to developing skillful qualities. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant is content with any kind of robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant is mindful. They have utmost mindfulness and alertness, and can remember and recall what was said and done long ago. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant is wise. They have the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

You should live with a protector, not without one. Living without a protector is suffering. These are the ten qualities that serve as protector.”

AN 10.18 A Protector (2nd) Dutiyanāthasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, you should live with a protector, not without one. Living without a protector is suffering. There are ten qualities that serve as protector. What ten? Firstly, a mendicant is ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken. Knowing this, the mendicants—whether senior, middle, or junior—think that mendicant is worth advising and instructing. Being treated with such kindness by the senior, middle, and junior mendicants, that mendicant can expect only growth, not decline. This is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant is very learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, reinforcing them by recitation, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically. Knowing this, the mendicants—whether senior, middle, or junior—think that mendicant is worth advising and instructing. Being treated with such kindness by the senior, middle, and junior mendicants, that mendicant can expect only growth, not decline. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant has good friends, companions, and associates. Knowing this, the mendicants—whether senior, middle, or junior—think that mendicant is worth advising and instructing. Being treated with such kindness by the senior, middle, and junior mendicants, that mendicant can expect only growth, not decline. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant is easy to admonish, having qualities that make them easy to admonish. They’re patient, and take instruction respectfully. Knowing this, the mendicants—whether senior, middle, or junior—think that mendicant is worth advising and instructing. Being treated with such kindness by the senior, middle, and junior mendicants, that mendicant can expect only growth, not decline. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant is deft and tireless in a diverse spectrum of duties for their spiritual companions, understanding how to go about things in order to complete and organize the work. Knowing this, the mendicants—whether senior, middle, or junior—think that mendicant is worth advising and instructing. Being treated with such kindness by the senior, middle, and junior mendicants, that mendicant can expect only growth, not decline. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant loves the teachings and is a delight to converse with, being full of joy in the teaching and training. Knowing this, the mendicants—whether senior, middle, or junior—think that mendicant is worth advising and instructing. Being treated with such kindness by the senior, middle, and junior mendicants, that mendicant can expect only growth, not decline. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant lives with energy roused up for giving up unskillful qualities and embracing skillful qualities. They are strong, staunchly vigorous, not slacking off when it comes to developing skillful qualities. Knowing this, the mendicants—whether senior, middle, or junior—think that mendicant is worth advising and instructing. Being treated with such kindness by the senior, middle, and junior mendicants, that mendicant can expect only growth, not decline. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant is content with any kind of robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. Knowing this, the mendicants—whether senior, middle, or junior—think that mendicant is worth advising and instructing. Being treated with such kindness by the senior, middle, and junior mendicants, that mendicant can expect only growth, not decline. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant is mindful. They have utmost mindfulness and alertness, and can remember and recall what was said and done long ago. Knowing this, the mendicants—whether senior, middle, or junior—think that mendicant is worth advising and instructing. Being treated with such kindness by the senior, middle, and junior mendicants, that mendicant can expect only growth, not decline. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

Furthermore, a mendicant is wise. They have the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. Knowing this, the mendicants—whether senior, middle, or junior—think that mendicant is worth advising and instructing. Being treated with such kindness by the senior, middle, and junior mendicants, that mendicant can expect only growth, not decline. This too is a quality that serves as protector.

You should live with a protector, not without one. Living without a protector is suffering. These are the ten qualities that serve as protector.”

That is what the Buddha said. Satisfied, the mendicants approved what the Buddha said.

AN 10.19 Abodes of the Noble Ones (1st) Paṭhamaariyāvāsasutta

“There are these ten abodes of the noble ones in which the noble ones of the past, present, and future abide. What ten? A mendicant has given up five factors, is endowed with six factors, has a single guard, has four supports, has cast aside idiosyncratic interpretations of the truth, has totally given up searching, has unsullied intentions, has stilled the physical process, and is well freed in mind and well freed by wisdom. These are the ten abodes of the noble ones in which the noble ones of the past, present, and future abide.”

AN 10.20 Abodes of the Noble Ones (2nd) Dutiyaariyāvāsasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Kurus, near the Kuru town named Kammāsadamma. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants:

“There are these ten abodes of the noble ones in which the noble ones of the past, present, and future abide. What ten? A mendicant has given up five factors, possesses six factors, has a single guard, has four supports, has cast aside idiosyncratic interpretations of the truth, has totally given up searching, has unsullied intentions, has stilled the physical process, and is well freed in mind and well freed by wisdom.

And how has a mendicant given up five factors? It’s when a mendicant has given up sensual desire, ill will, dullness and drowsiness, restlessness and remorse, and doubt. That’s how a mendicant has given up five factors.

And how does a mendicant possess six factors? It’s when a mendicant, seeing a sight with their eyes, is neither happy nor sad. They remain equanimous, mindful and aware. Hearing a sound with their ears … Smelling an odor with their nose … Tasting a flavor with their tongue …

Encountering a touch with their body … Knowing an idea with their mind, they’re neither happy nor sad. They remain equanimous, mindful and aware. That’s how a mendicant possesses six factors.

And how does a mendicant have a single guard? It’s when a mendicant’s heart is guarded by mindfulness. That’s how a mendicant has a single guard.

And how does a mendicant have four supports? After appraisal, a mendicant uses some things, endures some things, avoids some things, and dispels some things. That’s how a mendicant has four supports.

And how has a mendicant cast aside idiosyncratic interpretations of the truth? Different ascetics and brahmins have different idiosyncratic interpretations of the truth. For example: the cosmos is eternal, or not eternal, or finite, or infinite; the soul and the body are one and the same, or the soul is one thing, the body another; after death, a realized one still exists, or no longer exists, or both still exists and no longer exists, or neither still exists nor no longer exists. A mendicant has cast out, cast aside, thrown out, discarded, let go of, given up, and relinquished all these. That’s how a mendicant has cast aside idiosyncratic interpretations of the truth.

And how has a mendicant totally given up searching? It’s when they’ve given up searching for sensual pleasures, for continued existence, and for a spiritual life. That’s how a mendicant has totally given up searching.

And how does a mendicant have unsullied intentions? It’s when a mendicant has given up intentions of sensuality, malice, and cruelty. That’s how a mendicant has unsullied intentions.

And how has a mendicant stilled the physical process? It’s when, with the giving up of pleasure and pain and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, they enter and remain in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness. That’s how a mendicant has stilled the physical process.

And how is a mendicant well freed in mind? It’s when a mendicant’s mind is freed from greed, hate, and delusion. That’s how a mendicant is well freed in mind.

And how is a mendicant well freed by wisdom? It’s when a mendicant understands: ‘I’ve given up greed, hate, and delusion, cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, obliterated them, so they’re unable to arise in the future.’ That’s how a mendicant’s mind is well freed by wisdom.

Mendicants, whether in the past, future, or present, all noble ones abide in these same ten abodes of the noble ones. These are the ten abodes of the noble ones in which the noble ones of the past, present, and future abide.”

The Chapter on the Ceremony of Descent

AN 10.113 Bad Principles (1st) Paṭhamaadhammasutta

“Mendicants, you should know bad principles with bad results. And you should know good principles with good results. Knowing these things, your practice should follow the good principles with good results.

And what are bad principles with bad results? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. These are called bad principles with bad results.

And what are good principles with good results? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. These are called good principles with good results.

‘You should know bad principles with bad results. And you should know good principles with good results. Knowing these things, your practice should follow the good principles with good results.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.”

AN 10.114 Bad Principles (2nd) Dutiyaadhammasutta

“Mendicants, you should know bad principles and good principles. And you should know bad results and good results. Knowing these things, your practice should follow the good principles with good results.

So what are bad principles? What are good principles? What are bad results? And what are good results?

Wrong view is a bad principle. Right view is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong view are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of right view are good results.

Wrong purpose is a bad principle. Right purpose is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong purpose are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of right purpose are good results.

Wrong speech is a bad principle. Right speech is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong speech are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of right speech are good results.

Wrong action is a bad principle. Right action is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong action are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of right action are good results.

Wrong livelihood is a bad principle. Right livelihood is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong livelihood are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of right livelihood are good results.

Wrong effort is a bad principle. Right effort is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong effort are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of right effort are good results.

Wrong mindfulness is a bad principle. Right mindfulness is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong mindfulness are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of right mindfulness are good results.

Wrong immersion is a bad principle. Right immersion is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong immersion are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of right immersion are good results.

Wrong knowledge is a bad principle. Right knowledge is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong knowledge are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of right knowledge are good results.

Wrong freedom is a bad principle. Right freedom is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong freedom are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of right freedom are good results.

‘You should know bad principles and good principles. And you should know bad results and good results. Knowing these things, your practice should follow the good principles with good results.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.”

AN 10.115 Bad Principles (3rd) Tatiyaadhammasutta

“Mendicants, you should know bad principles and good principles. And you should know bad results and good results. Knowing these things, your practice should follow the good principles with good results.”

That is what the Buddha said. When he had spoken, the Holy One rose from his seat and entered his dwelling.

Soon after the Buddha left, those mendicants considered, “The Buddha gave this brief summary recital, then entered his dwelling without explaining the meaning in detail. Who can explain in detail the meaning of this brief summary recital given by the Buddha?”

Then they considered, “This Venerable Ānanda is praised by the Buddha and esteemed by his sensible spiritual companions. He is capable of explaining in detail the meaning of this brief summary recital given by the Buddha. Let’s go to him, and ask him about this matter. As he answers, so we’ll remember it.”

Then those mendicants went to Ānanda, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, they sat down to one side. They told him what had happened, and said, “May Venerable Ānanda please explain this.”

“Reverends, suppose there was a person in need of heartwood. And while wandering in search of heartwood he’d come across a large tree standing with heartwood. But he’d pass over the roots and trunk, imagining that the heartwood should be sought in the branches and leaves. Such is the consequence for the venerables. Though you were face to face with the Buddha, you bypassed him, imagining that you should ask me about this matter. For he is the Buddha, the one who knows and sees. He is vision, he is knowledge, he is the manifestation of principle, he is the manifestation of divinity. He is the preacher, the proclaimer, the elucidator of meaning, the bestower of freedom from death, the lord of truth, the Realized One. That was the time to approach the Buddha and ask about this matter. You should have remembered it in line with the Buddha’s answer.”

“Certainly he is the Buddha, the one who knows and sees. He is vision, he is knowledge, he is the manifestation of principle, he is the manifestation of divinity. He is the preacher, the proclaimer, the elucidator of meaning, the bestower of freedom from death, the lord of truth, the Realized One. That was the time to approach the Buddha and ask about this matter. We should have remembered it in line with the Buddha’s answer. Still, Venerable Ānanda is praised by the Buddha and esteemed by his sensible spiritual companions. You are capable of explaining in detail the meaning of this brief summary recital given by the Buddha. Please explain this, if it’s no trouble.”

“Then listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, reverend,” they replied. Ānanda said this:

“Reverends, the Buddha gave this brief summary recital, then entered his dwelling without explaining the meaning in detail: ‘You should know bad principles and good principles. And you should know bad results and good results. Knowing these things, your practice should follow the good principles with good results.’

So what are bad principles? What are good principles? What are bad results? And what are good results?

Wrong view is a bad principle. Right view is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong view are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of right view are good results.

Wrong purpose is a bad principle. Right purpose is a good principle. … Wrong speech is a bad principle. Right speech is a good principle. … Wrong action is a bad principle. Right action is a good principle. … Wrong livelihood is a bad principle. Right livelihood is a good principle. … Wrong effort is a bad principle. Right effort is a good principle. … Wrong mindfulness is a bad principle. Right mindfulness is a good principle. … Wrong immersion is a bad principle. Right immersion is a good principle. … Wrong knowledge is a bad principle. Right knowledge is a good principle. …

Wrong freedom is a bad principle. Right freedom is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong freedom are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of right freedom are good results.

The Buddha gave this brief summary recital, then entered his dwelling without explaining the meaning in detail: ‘You should know bad principles and good principles … and practice accordingly.’ And this is how I understand the detailed meaning of this summary recital. If you wish, you may go to the Buddha and ask him about this. You should remember it in line with the Buddha’s answer.”

“Yes, reverend,” said those mendicants, approving and agreeing with what Ānanda said. Then they rose from their seats and went to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened. Then they said:

“Sir, we went to Ānanda and asked him about this matter. And Ānanda clearly explained the meaning to us in this manner, with these words and phrases.”

“Good, good, mendicants! Ānanda is astute, he has great wisdom. If you came to me and asked this question, I would answer it in exactly the same way as Ānanda. That is what it means, and that’s how you should remember it.”

AN 10.116 With Ajita Ajitasutta

Then the wanderer Ajita went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha, “Worthy Gotama, we have a spiritual companion called ‘Astute’. He has worked out around five hundred arguments by which followers of other religions will know when they’ve been refuted.”

Then the Buddha said to the mendicants, “Mendicants, do you remember this Astute’s points?”

“Now is the time, Blessed One! Now is the time, Holy One! Let the Buddha speak and the mendicants will remember it.”

“Well then, mendicants, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, take a certain someone who rebuts and quashes unprincipled statements with unprincipled statements. This delights an unprincipled assembly, who make a colossal racket: ‘He is truly astute! He is truly astute!’

Someone else rebuts and quashes principled statements with unprincipled statements. This delights an unprincipled assembly, who make a colossal racket: ‘He is truly astute! He is truly astute!’

Someone else rebuts and quashes principled and unprincipled statements with unprincipled statements. This delights an unprincipled assembly, who make a colossal racket: ‘He is truly astute! He is truly astute!’

Mendicants, you should know bad principles and good principles. And you should know bad results and good results. Knowing these things, your practice should follow the good principles with good results.

So what are bad principles? What are good principles? What are bad results? And what are good results? Wrong view is a bad principle. Right view is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong view are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of right view are good results.

Wrong purpose is a bad principle. Right purpose is a good principle. … Wrong speech is a bad principle. Right speech is a good principle. … Wrong action is a bad principle. Right action is a good principle. … Wrong livelihood is a bad principle. Right livelihood is a good principle. … Wrong effort is a bad principle. Right effort is a good principle. … Wrong mindfulness is a bad principle. Right mindfulness is a good principle. … Wrong immersion is a bad principle. Right immersion is a good principle. … Wrong knowledge is a bad principle. Right knowledge is a good principle. …

Wrong freedom is a bad principle. Right freedom is a good principle. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong freedom are bad results. And the many skillful qualities fully developed because of right freedom are good results.

‘You should know bad principles and good principles. And you should know bad results and good results. Knowing these things, your practice should follow the good principles with good results.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.”

AN 10.117 With Saṅgārava Saṅgāravasutta

Then Saṅgārava the brahmin went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“Worthy Gotama, what is the near shore? And what is the far shore?”

“Wrong view is the near shore, brahmin, and right view is the far shore. Wrong purpose is the near shore, and right purpose is the far shore. Wrong speech is the near shore, and right speech is the far shore. Wrong action is the near shore, and right action is the far shore. Wrong livelihood is the near shore, and right livelihood is the far shore. Wrong effort is the near shore, and right effort is the far shore. Wrong mindfulness is the near shore, and right mindfulness is the far shore. Wrong immersion is the near shore, and right immersion is the far shore. Wrong knowledge is the near shore, and right knowledge is the far shore. Wrong freedom is the near shore, and right freedom is the far shore. This is the near shore, and this is the far shore.

Few are those among humans
who cross to the far shore.
The rest just run around
on the near shore.

When the teaching is well explained,
the people who practice accordingly
will cross over
Death’s dominion so hard to pass.

Rid of dark qualities,
an astute person would develop the bright.
Having left home for homelessness
in seclusion, where joy is hard,

they’d long for satisfaction there.
Forsaking sensual pleasures, owning nothing,
an astute person would cleanse themselves
of mental corruptions.

And those whose minds are rightly developed
in the awakening factors;
who, letting go of attachments,
delight in not grasping—
with defilements ended, brilliant,
they are quenched in this world.”

AN 10.118 The Near Shore Orimatīrasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the near shore and the far shore. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“And what, mendicants, is the near shore? What is the far shore? Wrong view is the near shore, and right view is the far shore. … Wrong freedom is the near shore, and right freedom is the far shore. This is the near shore, and this is the far shore.

Few are those among humans
who cross to the far shore.
The rest just run
around on the near shore.

When the teaching is well explained,
the people who practice accordingly
will cross over
Death’s dominion so hard to pass.

Rid of dark qualities,
an astute person would develop the bright.
Having left home for homelessness
in seclusion, where joy is hard,

they’d long for satisfaction there.
Forsaking sensual pleasures, owning nothing,
an astute person would cleanse themselves
of mental corruptions.

And those whose minds are rightly developed
in the awakening factors;
letting go of attachments,
they delight in not grasping.
With defilements ended, brilliant,
they are quenched in this world.”

AN 10.119 The Ceremony of Descent (1st) Paṭhamapaccorohaṇīsutta

Now, at that time it was the sabbath. The brahmin Jānussoṇi had bathed his head and dressed in a new pair of linen robes. Holding a handful of fresh grass, he stood to one side not far from the Buddha.

The Buddha saw him, and said, “Brahmin, why have you bathed your head and dressed in a new pair of linen robes? Why are you standing to one side holding a handful of fresh grass? What’s going on today with the brahmin clan?”

“Worthy Gotama, today is the ceremony of descent for the brahmin clan.”

“But how do the brahmins observe the ceremony of descent?”

“Well, worthy Gotama, on the sabbath the brahmins bathe their heads and dress in a new pair of linen robes. They make a heap of fresh cow dung and spread it with green grass. Then they make their beds between the boundary and the fire chamber. That night they rise three times and worship the fire with cupped palms: ‘We descend, lord! We descend, lord!’ And they serve the fire with abundant ghee, oil, and butter. And when the night has passed they serve the brahmins with delicious fresh and cooked foods. That’s how the brahmins observe the ceremony of descent.”

“The ceremony of descent observed by the brahmins is quite different from that observed in the training of the Noble One.”

“But worthy Gotama, how is the ceremony of descent observed in the training of the Noble One? Worthy Gotama, please teach me this.”

“Well then, brahmin, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, worthy sir,” Jānussoṇi replied. The Buddha said this:

“It’s when a noble disciple reflects: ‘Wrong view has a bad result in both this life and the next.’ Reflecting like this, they give up wrong view, they descend from wrong view.

‘Wrong purpose has a bad result in both this life and the next.’ Reflecting like this, they give up wrong purpose, they descend from wrong purpose.

‘Wrong speech has a bad result in both this life and the next.’ Reflecting like this, they give up wrong speech, they descend from wrong speech.

‘Wrong action has a bad result in both this life and the next.’ Reflecting like this, they give up wrong action, they descend from wrong action.

‘Wrong livelihood has a bad result in both this life and the next.’ Reflecting like this, they give up wrong livelihood, they descend from wrong livelihood.

‘Wrong effort has a bad result in both this life and the next.’ Reflecting like this, they give up wrong effort, they descend from wrong effort.

‘Wrong mindfulness has a bad result in both this life and the next.’ Reflecting like this, they give up wrong mindfulness, they descend from wrong mindfulness.

‘Wrong immersion has a bad result in both this life and the next.’ Reflecting like this, they give up wrong immersion, they descend from wrong immersion.

‘Wrong knowledge has a bad result in both this life and the next.’ Reflecting like this, they give up wrong knowledge, they descend from wrong knowledge.

‘Wrong freedom has a bad result in both this life and the next.’ Reflecting like this, they give up wrong freedom, they descend from wrong freedom. This is the ceremony of descent in the training of the Noble One.”

“The ceremony of descent observed by the brahmins is quite different from that observed in the training of the Noble One. And, worthy Gotama, the ceremony of descent observed by the brahmins is not worth a sixteenth part of a master of the ceremony of descent observed in the training of the Noble One. Excellent, worthy Gotama! … From this day forth, may the worthy Gotama remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

AN 10.120 The Ceremony of Descent (2nd) Dutiyapaccorohaṇīsutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the noble descent. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak. … And what is the noble descent? It’s when a noble disciple reflects: ‘Wrong view has a bad result in both this life and the next.’ Reflecting like this, they give up wrong view, they descend from wrong view. ‘Wrong purpose has a bad result …’ … ‘Wrong speech …’ … ‘Wrong action …’ … ‘Wrong livelihood …’ … ‘Wrong effort …’ … ‘Wrong mindfulness …’ … ‘Wrong immersion …’ … ‘Wrong knowledge …’ … ‘Wrong freedom has a bad result in both this life and the next.’ Reflecting like this, they give up wrong freedom, they descend from wrong freedom. This is called the noble descent.”

AN 10.121 Forerunner Pubbaṅgamasutta

“Mendicants, the dawn is the forerunner and harbinger of the sunrise. In the same way right view is the forerunner and harbinger of skillful qualities. Right view produces right purpose. Right purpose produces right speech. Right speech produces right action. Right action produces right livelihood. Right livelihood produces right effort. Right effort produces right mindfulness. Right mindfulness produces right immersion. Right immersion produces right knowledge. Right knowledge produces right freedom.”

AN 10.122 The Ending of Defilements Āsavakkhayasutta

“Mendicants, these ten things, when developed and cultivated, lead to the ending of defilements. What ten? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. These ten things, when developed and cultivated, lead to the ending of defilements.”

The Fifth Fifty

The Chapter on the Body Born of Deeds

AN 10.211 Heaven and Hell (1st) Paṭhamanirayasaggasutta

“Someone with ten qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there. What ten? It’s when someone kills living creatures. They’re violent, bloody-handed, a hardened killer, merciless to all living beings.

They steal. With the intention to commit theft, they take the wealth or belongings of others from village or wilderness.

They commit sexual misconduct. They have relations with women who have their mother, father, both mother and father, brother, sister, relatives, or clan as guardian. They have relations with a woman who is protected on principle, or who has a husband, or whose violation is punishable by law, or even one who has been garlanded as a token of betrothal.

They lie. They’re summoned to a council, an assembly, a family meeting, a guild, or to the royal court, and asked to bear witness: ‘Please, my man, say what you know.’ Not knowing, they say ‘I know.’ Knowing, they say ‘I don’t know.’ Not seeing, they say ‘I see.’ And seeing, they say ‘I don’t see.’ So they deliberately lie for the sake of themselves or another, or for some trivial worldly reason.

They backbite. They repeat in one place what they heard in another so as to divide people against each other. And so they divide those who are harmonious, supporting division, delighting in division, loving division, speaking words that promote division.

They speak harshly. They use the kinds of words that are cruel, nasty, hurtful, offensive, bordering on anger, not leading to immersion.

They talk nonsense. Their speech is untimely, and is neither factual nor beneficial. It has nothing to do with the teaching or the training. Their words have no value, and are untimely, unreasonable, rambling, and pointless.

They’re covetous. They covet the wealth and belongings of others: ‘Oh, if only their belongings were mine!’

They have ill will and malicious intentions: ‘May these sentient beings be killed, slaughtered, slain, destroyed, or annihilated!’

They have wrong view. Their perspective is distorted: ‘There’s no meaning in giving, sacrifice, or offerings. There’s no fruit or result of good and bad deeds. There’s no afterlife. There’s no such thing as mother and father, or beings that are reborn spontaneously. And there’s no ascetic or brahmin who is rightly comported and rightly practiced, and who describes the afterlife after realizing it with their own insight.’ Someone with these ten qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there.

Someone with ten qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there. What ten? It’s when someone gives up killing living creatures, renouncing the rod and the sword. They’re scrupulous and kind, living full of sympathy for all living beings.

They give up stealing. They don’t, with the intention to commit theft, take the wealth or belongings of others from village or wilderness.

They give up sexual misconduct. They don’t have relations with women who have their mother, father, both mother and father, brother, sister, relatives, or clan as guardian. They don’t have relations with a woman who is protected on principle, or who has a husband, or whose violation is punishable by law, or even one who has been garlanded as a token of betrothal.

They give up lying. They’re summoned to a council, an assembly, a family meeting, a guild, or to the royal court, and asked to bear witness: ‘Please, my man, say what you know.’ Not knowing, they say ‘I don’t know.’ Knowing, they say ‘I know.’ Not seeing, they say ‘I don’t see.’ And seeing, they say ‘I see.’ So they don’t deliberately lie for the sake of themselves or another, or for some trivial worldly reason.

They give up backbiting. They don’t repeat in one place what they heard in another so as to divide people against each other. Instead, they reconcile those who are divided and support those who are united, delighting in harmony, loving harmony, speaking words that promote harmony.

They give up harsh speech. They speak in a way that’s mellow, pleasing to the ear, endearing, going to the heart, polite, and likable and agreeable to the people.

They give up talking nonsense. Their words are timely, true, and meaningful, in line with the teaching and training. They say things at the right time which are valuable, reasonable, succinct, and beneficial.

They’re content. They don’t covet the wealth and belongings of others: ‘Oh, if only their belongings were mine!’

They have a kind heart and loving intentions: ‘May these sentient beings live free of enmity and ill will, untroubled and happy!’

They have right view, an undistorted perspective: ‘There is meaning in giving, sacrifice, and offerings. There are fruits and results of good and bad deeds. There is an afterlife. There are such things as mother and father, and beings that are reborn spontaneously. And there are ascetics and brahmins who are rightly comported and rightly practiced, and who describe the afterlife after realizing it with their own insight.’

Someone with these ten qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there.”

AN 10.212 Heaven and Hell (2nd) Dutiyanirayasaggasutta

“Someone with ten qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there. What ten? It’s when someone kills living creatures. They’re violent, bloody-handed, a hardened killer, merciless to all living beings.

They steal. … They commit sexual misconduct. … They lie. … They backbite. … They speak harshly. … They talk nonsense. … They’re covetous. … They have cruel intentions. … They have wrong view. … Someone with these ten qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there.

Someone with ten qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there. What ten? It’s when someone gives up killing living creatures, renouncing the rod and the sword. They’re scrupulous and kind, living full of sympathy for all living beings.

They give up stealing. … They give up sexual misconduct. … They give up lying. … They give up backbiting. … They give up harsh speech. … They give up talking nonsense. … They’re content. … They’re kind hearted. … They have right view. … Someone with these ten qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there.”

AN 10.213 A Lady Mātugāmasutta

“A lady with ten qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there. What ten? She kills living creatures. … She steals. … She commits sexual misconduct. … She lies. … She backbites. … She speaks harshly. … She indulges in talking nonsense. … She’s covetous. … She has cruel intentions. … She has wrong view. … A lady with these ten qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there.

A lady with ten qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there. What ten? She doesn’t kill living creatures. … She doesn’t steal. … She doesn’t commit sexual misconduct. … She doesn’t lie. … She doesn’t backbite. … She doesn’t speak harshly. … She doesn’t indulge in talking nonsense. … She’s content. … She’s kind hearted. … She has right view. … A lady with these ten qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there.”

AN 10.214 A Laywoman Upāsikāsutta

“A laywoman with ten qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there. What ten? She kills living creatures. … She has wrong view. … A laywoman with these ten qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there.

A laywoman with ten qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there. What ten? She doesn’t kill living creatures. … She has right view. … A laywoman with these ten qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there.”

AN 10.215 Assured Visāradasutta

“A laywoman living at home with these ten qualities is not self-assured. What ten? She kills living creatures. … She has wrong view. … A laywoman living at home with these ten qualities is not self-assured.

A laywoman living at home with these ten qualities is self-assured. What ten? She doesn’t kill living creatures. … She has right view. … A laywoman living at home with these ten qualities is self-assured.”

AN 10.216 Creepy Creatures Saṁsappanīyasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you an exposition of the teaching on creepy creatures. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“What is the exposition of the teaching on creepy creatures? Sentient beings are the owners of their deeds and heir to their deeds. Deeds are their womb, their relative, and their refuge. They shall be the heir of whatever deeds they do, whether good or bad.

Take a certain someone who kills living creatures. They’re violent, bloody-handed, a hardened killer, merciless to all living beings. They’re creepy in body, speech, and mind. Doing crooked deeds by way of body, speech, and mind, their destiny and rebirth are crooked.

Someone whose destiny and rebirth is crooked is reborn in one of two places, I say: in an absolutely painful hell, or among the species of creepy animals. And what are the species of creepy animals? Snakes, scorpions, centipedes, mongooses, cats, mice, owls, or whatever other species of animal that creep away when they see humans. This is how a being is born from a being. For your deeds determine your rebirth, and when you’re reborn contacts strike you. This is why I say that sentient beings are heirs to their deeds.

Take someone else who steals … commits sexual misconduct … lies … backbites … speaks harshly … indulges in talking nonsense … is covetous … has cruel intentions … has wrong view … They’re creepy in body, speech, and mind. Doing crooked deeds by way of body, speech, and mind, their destiny and rebirth are crooked.

Someone whose destiny and rebirth is crooked is reborn in one of two places, I say: in an absolutely painful hell, or among the species of creepy animals. And what are the species of creepy animals? Snakes, scorpions, centipedes, mongooses, cats, mice, owls, or whatever other species of animal that creep away when they see humans. This is how a being is born from a being. For your deeds determine your rebirth, and when you’re reborn contacts strike you. This is why I say that sentient beings are heirs to their deeds. Sentient beings are the owners of their deeds and heir to their deeds. Deeds are their womb, their relative, and their refuge. They shall be the heir of whatever deeds they do, whether good or bad.

Take a certain someone who gives up killing living creatures, renouncing the rod and the sword. They’re scrupulous and kind, living full of sympathy for all living beings. They’re not creepy in body, speech, and mind. Doing virtuous deeds by way of body, speech, and mind, their destiny and rebirth is virtuous.

Someone whose destiny and rebirth is virtuous is reborn in one of two places, I say: in a heaven of absolute happiness, or in an eminent well-to-do family of aristocrats, brahmins, or householders—rich, affluent, and wealthy, with lots of gold and silver, lots of property and assets, and lots of money and grain. This is how a being is born from a being. For your deeds determine your rebirth, and when you’re reborn contacts strike you. This is why I say that sentient beings are heirs to their deeds.

Take someone else who gives up stealing … sexual misconduct … lying … backbiting … harsh speech … talking nonsense … They’re content … kind hearted … they have right view … They’re not creepy in body, speech, and mind. Doing virtuous deeds by way of body, speech, and mind, their destiny and rebirth is virtuous.

Someone whose destiny and rebirth is virtuous is reborn in one of two places, I say: in a heaven of absolute happiness, or in an eminent well-to-do family of aristocrats, brahmins, or householders—rich, affluent, and wealthy, with lots of gold and silver, lots of property and assets, and lots of money and grain. This is how a being is born from a being. For your deeds determine your rebirth, and when you’re reborn contacts strike you. This is why I say that sentient beings are heirs to their deeds.

Sentient beings are the owners of their deeds and heir to their deeds. Deeds are their womb, their relative, and their refuge. They shall be the heir of whatever deeds they do, whether good or bad. This is the exposition of the teaching on creepy creatures.”

AN 10.217 Intentional (1st) Paṭhamasañcetanikasutta

“Mendicants, I don’t say that intentional deeds that have been performed and accumulated are eliminated without being experienced. And that may be in this very life, or in the next life, or in some subsequent period. But in any case, there is no making an end of suffering without experiencing intentional deeds that have been performed and accumulated, I say.

Now, there are three kinds of corruption and failure of bodily action that have unskillful intention, with suffering as their outcome and result. There are four kinds of corruption and failure of verbal action that have unskillful intention, with suffering as their outcome and result. There are three kinds of corruption and failure of mental action that have unskillful intention, with suffering as their outcome and result.

And what are the three kinds of corruption and failure of bodily action? It’s when someone kills living creatures. They’re violent, bloody-handed, a hardened killer, merciless to all living beings.

They steal. With the intention to commit theft, they take the wealth or belongings of others from village or wilderness.

They commit sexual misconduct. They have relations with women who have their mother, father, both mother and father, brother, sister, relatives, or clan as guardian. They have relations with a woman who is protected on principle, or who has a husband, or whose violation is punishable by law, or even one who has been garlanded as a token of betrothal.

These are the three kinds of corruption and failure of bodily action.

And what are the four kinds of corruption and failure of verbal action? It’s when someone lies. They’re summoned to a council, an assembly, a family meeting, a guild, or to the royal court, and asked to bear witness: ‘Please, my man, say what you know.’ Not knowing, they say ‘I know.’ Knowing, they say ‘I don’t know.’ Not seeing, they say ‘I see.’ And seeing, they say ‘I don’t see.’ So they deliberately lie for the sake of themselves or another, or for some trivial worldly reason.

They backbite. They repeat in one place what they heard in another so as to divide people against each other. And so they divide those who are harmonious, supporting division, delighting in division, loving division, speaking words that promote division.

They speak harshly. They use the kinds of words that are cruel, nasty, hurtful, offensive, bordering on anger, not leading to immersion.

They talk nonsense. Their speech is untimely, and is neither factual nor beneficial. It has nothing to do with the teaching or the training. Their words have no value, and are untimely, unreasonable, rambling, and pointless.

These are the four kinds of corruption and failure of verbal action.

And what are the three kinds of corruption and failure of mental action? It’s when someone is covetous. They covet the wealth and belongings of others: ‘Oh, if only their belongings were mine!’

They have ill will and malicious intentions: ‘May these sentient beings be killed, slaughtered, slain, destroyed, or annihilated!’

They have wrong view. Their perspective is distorted: ‘There’s no meaning in giving, sacrifice, or offerings. There’s no fruit or result of good and bad deeds. There’s no afterlife. There’s no such thing as mother and father, or beings that are reborn spontaneously. And there’s no ascetic or brahmin who is rightly comported and rightly practiced, and who describes the afterlife after realizing it with their own insight.’

These are the three kinds of corruption and failure of mental action.

When their body breaks up, after death, sentient beings are reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell because of these three kinds of corruption and failure of bodily action, these four kinds of corruption and failure of verbal action, or these three kinds of corruption and failure of mental action that have unskillful intention, with suffering as their outcome and result.

It’s like throwing sure-bet dice: they always fall the right side up. In the same way, when their body breaks up, after death, sentient beings are reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell because of these three kinds of corruption and failure of bodily action, these four kinds of corruption and failure of verbal action, or these three kinds of corruption and failure of mental action that have unskillful intention, with suffering as their outcome and result.

I don’t say that intentional deeds that have been performed and accumulated are eliminated without being experienced. And that may be in this very life, or in the next life, or in some subsequent period. But in any case, there is no making an end of suffering without experiencing intentional deeds that have been performed and accumulated, I say.

Now, there are three kinds of successful bodily action that have skillful intention, with happiness as their outcome and result. There are four kinds of successful verbal action that have skillful intention, with happiness as their outcome and result. There are three kinds of successful mental action that have skillful intention, with happiness as their outcome and result.

And what are the three kinds of successful bodily action? It’s when someone gives up killing living creatures. They renounce the rod and the sword. They’re scrupulous and kind, living full of sympathy for all living beings.

They don’t steal. They don’t, with the intention to commit theft, take the wealth or belongings of others from village or wilderness.

They give up sexual misconduct. They don’t have relations with women who have their mother, father, both mother and father, brother, sister, relatives, or clan as guardian. They don’t have relations with a woman who is protected on principle, or who has a husband, or whose violation is punishable by law, or even one who has been garlanded as a token of betrothal.

These are the three kinds of successful bodily action.

And what are the four kinds of successful verbal action? It’s when someone gives up lying. They’re summoned to a council, an assembly, a family meeting, a guild, or to the royal court, and asked to bear witness: ‘Please, my friend, say what you know.’ Not knowing, they say ‘I don’t know.’ Knowing, they say ‘I know.’ Not seeing, they say ‘I don’t see.’ And seeing, they say ‘I see.’ So they don’t deliberately lie for the sake of themselves or another, or for some trivial worldly reason.

They give up backbiting. They don’t repeat in one place what they heard in another so as to divide people against each other. Instead, they reconcile those who are divided and support those who are united, delighting in harmony, loving harmony, speaking words that promote harmony.

They give up harsh speech. They speak in a way that’s mellow, pleasing to the ear, endearing, going to the heart, polite, and likable and agreeable to the people.

They give up talking nonsense. Their words are timely, true, and meaningful, in line with the teaching and training. They say things at the right time which are valuable, reasonable, succinct, and beneficial.

These are the four kinds of successful verbal action.

And what are the three kinds of successful mental action? It’s when someone is content. They don’t covet the wealth and belongings of others: ‘Oh, if only their belongings were mine!’

They have a kind heart and loving intentions: ‘May these sentient beings live free of enmity and ill will, untroubled and happy!’

They have right view, an undistorted perspective: ‘There is meaning in giving, sacrifice, and offerings. There are fruits and results of good and bad deeds. There is an afterlife. There are such things as mother and father, and beings that are reborn spontaneously. And there are ascetics and brahmins who are rightly comported and rightly practiced, and who describe the afterlife after realizing it with their own insight.’

These are the three kinds of successful mental action.

When their body breaks up, after death, sentient beings are reborn in a good place, in heaven because of these three kinds of successful bodily action, these four kinds of successful verbal action, or these three kinds of successful mental action that have skillful intention, with happiness as their outcome and result.

It’s like throwing unfaling dice: they always fall the right side up. In the same way, when their body breaks up, after death, sentient beings are reborn in a good place, in heaven because of these three kinds of successful bodily action, these four kinds of successful verbal action, or these three kinds of successful mental action that have skillful intention, with happiness as their outcome and result. I don’t say that intentional deeds that have been performed and accumulated are eliminated without being experienced. And that may be in this very life, or in the next life, or in some subsequent period. But in any case, there is no making an end of suffering without experiencing intentional deeds that have been performed and accumulated, I say.”

AN 10.218 Intentional (2nd) Dutiyasañcetanikasutta

“Mendicants, I don’t say that intentional deeds that have been performed and accumulated are eliminated without being experienced. And that may be in this very life, or in the next life, or in some subsequent period. But in any case, there is no making an end of suffering without experiencing intentional deeds that have been performed and accumulated, I say.

Now, there are three kinds of corruption and failure of bodily action that have unskillful intention, with suffering as their outcome and result. There are four kinds of corruption and failure of verbal action that have unskillful intention, with suffering as their outcome and result. There are three kinds of corruption and failure of mental action that have unskillful intention, with suffering as their outcome and result.

And what are the three kinds of corruption and failure of bodily action? … These are the three kinds of corruption and failure of bodily action.

And what are the four kinds of corruption and failure of verbal action? … These are the four kinds of corruption and failure of verbal action.

And what are the three kinds of corruption and failure of mental action? … These are the three kinds of corruption and failure of mental action.

When their body breaks up, after death, sentient beings are reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell because of these three kinds of corruption and failure of bodily action, these four kinds of corruption and failure of verbal action, or these three kinds of corruption and failure of mental action that have unskillful intention, with suffering as their outcome and result.

I don’t say that intentional deeds that have been performed and accumulated are eliminated without being experienced. And that may be in this very life, or in the next life, or in some subsequent period. But in any case, there is no making an end of suffering without experiencing intentional deeds that have been performed and accumulated, I say.

Now, there are three kinds of successful bodily action that have skillful intention, with happiness as their outcome and result. There are four kinds of successful verbal action that have skillful intention, with happiness as their outcome and result. There are three kinds of successful mental action that have skillful intention, with happiness as their outcome and result.

And what are the three kinds of successful bodily action? … These are the three kinds of successful bodily action.

And what are the four kinds of successful verbal action? … These are the four kinds of successful verbal action.

And what are the three kinds of successful mental action? … These are the three kinds of successful mental action.

When their body breaks up, after death, sentient beings are reborn in a good place, in heaven because of these three kinds of successful bodily action, these four kinds of successful verbal action, or these three kinds of successful mental action that have skillful intention, with happiness as their outcome and result. …”

AN 10.219 The Body Born of Deeds Karajakāyasutta

“Mendicants, I don’t say that intentional deeds that have been performed and accumulated are eliminated without being experienced. And that may be in this very life, or in the next life, or in some subsequent period. But in any case, there is no making an end of suffering without experiencing intentional deeds that have been performed and accumulated, I say.

That noble disciple is rid of desire, rid of ill will, unconfused, aware, and mindful. They meditate spreading a heart full of love to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, they spread a heart full of love to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will.

They understand: ‘Formerly my mind was limited and undeveloped. Now it’s limitless and well developed. Whatever limited deeds I’ve done don’t remain or persist there.’

What do you think, mendicants? Suppose a child had developed the heart’s release by love from their childhood on. Would they still do any bad deed?”

“No, sir.”

“Not doing any bad deed, would they still experience any suffering?”

“No, sir. For if they don’t do any bad deed, from where would suffering afflict them?”

“This heart’s release by love should be developed by women or men. For neither women nor men take this body with them when they go. The mind is what’s inside mortal beings. They understand: ‘Whatever bad deeds I have done in the past with this deed-born body I will experience here. It will not follow me to my next life.’ The heart’s release by love developed in this way leads to non-return for a wise mendicant here who has not penetrated to a higher freedom.

They meditate spreading a heart full of compassion … They meditate spreading a heart full of rejoicing … They meditate spreading a heart full of equanimity to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, they spread a heart full of equanimity to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will.

They understand: ‘Formerly my mind was limited and undeveloped. Now it’s limitless and well developed. Whatever limited deeds I’ve done don’t remain or persist there.’

What do you think, mendicants? Suppose a child had developed the heart’s release by equanimity from their childhood on. Would they still do any bad deed?”

“No, sir.”

“Not doing any bad deed, would they still experience any suffering?”

“No, sir. For if they don’t do any bad deed, from where would suffering afflict them?”

“This heart’s release by equanimity should be developed by women or men. For neither women nor men take this body with them when they go. The mind is what’s inside mortal beings. They understand: ‘Whatever bad deeds I have done in the past with this deed-born body I will experience here. It will not follow me to my next life.’ The heart’s release by equanimity developed in this way leads to non-return for a wise mendicant here who has not penetrated to a higher freedom.”

AN 10.220 Unprincipled Conduct Adhammacariyāsutta

Then a certain brahmin went up to the Buddha and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“What is the cause, worthy Gotama, what is the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell?”

“Unprincipled and immoral conduct is the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.”

“But what is the cause, worthy Gotama, what is the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm?”

“Principled and moral conduct is the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.”

“I don’t understand the detailed meaning of what the worthy Gotama has said in brief. Please, worthy Gotama, teach me this matter so I can understand the detailed meaning.”

“Well then, brahmin, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, worthy sir,” the brahmin replied. The Buddha said this:

“Brahmin, unprincipled and immoral conduct is threefold by way of body, fourfold by way of speech, and threefold by way of mind.

And how is unprincipled and immoral conduct threefold by way of body? … That’s how unprincipled and immoral conduct is threefold by way of body.

And how is unprincipled and immoral conduct fourfold by way of speech? … That’s how unprincipled and immoral conduct is fourfold by way of speech.

And how is unprincipled and immoral conduct threefold by way of mind? … That’s how unprincipled and immoral conduct is threefold by way of mind. That’s how unprincipled and immoral conduct is the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.

Principled and moral conduct is threefold by way of body, fourfold by way of speech, and threefold by way of mind.

And how is principled and moral conduct threefold by way of body? … That’s how principled and moral conduct is threefold by way of body.

And how is principled and moral conduct fourfold by way of speech? … That’s how principled and moral conduct is fourfold by way of speech.

And how is principled and moral conduct threefold by way of mind? … That’s how principled and moral conduct is threefold by way of mind. That’s how principled and moral conduct is the reason why some sentient beings, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.”

“Excellent, worthy Gotama! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the worthy Gotama remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

The Chapter on Purified

AN 10.123 First Paṭhamasutta

“Mendicants, these ten things are not purified and cleansed apart from the Holy One’s training. What ten? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. These ten things are not purified and cleansed apart from the Holy One’s training.”

AN 10.124 Second Dutiyasutta

“Mendicants, these ten things don’t arise apart from the Holy One’s training. What ten? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. These are the ten things that don’t arise apart from the Holy One’s training.”

AN 10.125 Third Tatiyasutta

“Mendicants, these ten things are not very fruitful and beneficial apart from the Holy One’s training. What ten? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. These are the ten things that are not very fruitful and beneficial apart from the Holy One’s training.”

AN 10.126 Fourth Catutthasutta

“Mendicants, these ten things don’t culminate in the removal of greed, hate, and delusion apart from the Holy One’s training. What ten? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. These are the ten things that don’t culminate in the removal of greed, hate, and delusion apart from the Holy One’s training.”

AN 10.127 Fifth Pañcamasutta

“Mendicants, these ten things don’t lead solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment apart from the Holy One’s training. What ten? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. These are the ten things that don’t lead solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment apart from the Holy One’s training.”

AN 10.128 Sixth Chaṭṭhasutta

“Mendicants, these ten things don’t arise to be developed and cultivated apart from the Holy One’s training. What ten? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. These are the ten things that don’t arise to be developed and cultivated apart from the Holy One’s training.”

AN 10.129 Seventh Sattamasutta

“Mendicants, these ten things when developed and cultivated are not very fruitful and beneficial apart from the Holy One’s training. What ten? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. These are the ten things that when developed and cultivated are not very fruitful and beneficial apart from the Holy One’s training.”

AN 10.130 Eighth Aṭṭhamasutta

“Mendicants, these ten things when developed and cultivated don’t culminate in the removal of greed, hate, and delusion apart from the Holy One’s training. What ten? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. These are the ten things that when developed and cultivated don’t culminate in the removal of greed, hate, and delusion apart from the Holy One’s training.”

AN 10.131 Ninth Navamasutta

“Mendicants, these ten things when developed and cultivated don’t lead solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment apart from the Holy One’s training. What ten? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. These are the ten things that when developed and cultivated don’t lead solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment apart from the Holy One’s training.”

AN 10.132 Tenth Dasamasutta

“Mendicants, there are ten wrong ways. What ten? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. These are the ten wrong ways.”

AN 10.133 Eleventh Ekādasamasutta

“Mendicants, there are ten right ways. What ten? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. These are the ten right ways.”

The First Fifty

The Chapter on Benefits

AN 10.1 What’s the Goal? Kimatthiyasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, what is the goal and benefit of skillful ethics?”

“Ānanda, having no regrets is the goal and benefit of skillful ethics.”

“But what is the goal and benefit of having no regrets?”

“Joy is the goal and benefit of having no regrets.”

“But what is the goal and benefit of joy?”

“Rapture …”

“But what is the goal and benefit of rapture?”

“Tranquility …”

“But what is the goal and benefit of tranquility?”

“Bliss …”

“But what is the goal and benefit of bliss?”

“Immersion …”

“But what is the goal and benefit of immersion?”

“Truly knowing and seeing …”

“But what is the goal and benefit of truly knowing and seeing?”

“Disillusionment and dispassion …”

“But what is the goal and benefit of disillusionment and dispassion?”

“Knowledge and vision of freedom is the goal and benefit of disillusionment and dispassion.

So, Ānanda, the goal and benefit of skillful ethics is not having regrets. Joy is the goal and benefit of not having regrets. Rapture is the goal and benefit of joy. Tranquility is the goal and benefit of rapture. Bliss is the goal and benefit of tranquility. Immersion is the goal and benefit of bliss. Truly knowing and seeing is the goal and benefit of immersion. Disillusionment and dispassion is the goal and benefit of truly knowing and seeing. Knowledge and vision of freedom is the goal and benefit of disillusionment and dispassion. So, Ānanda, skillful ethics progressively lead up to the highest.”

AN 10.2 Making a Wish Cetanākaraṇīyasutta

“Mendicants, an ethical person, who has fulfilled ethical conduct, need not make a wish: ‘May I have no regrets!’ It’s only natural that an ethical person has no regrets. When you have no regrets you need not make a wish: ‘May I feel joy!’ It’s only natural that joy springs up when you have no regrets. When you feel joy you need not make a wish: ‘May I experience rapture!’ It’s only natural that rapture arises when you’re joyful. When your mind is full of rapture you need not make a wish: ‘May my body become tranquil!’ It’s only natural that your body becomes tranquil when your mind is full of rapture. When your body is tranquil you need not make a wish: ‘May I feel bliss!’ It’s only natural to feel bliss when your body is tranquil. When you feel bliss you need not make a wish: ‘May my mind be immersed in samādhi!’ It’s only natural for the mind to be immersed in samādhi when you feel bliss. When your mind is immersed in samādhi you need not make a wish: ‘May I truly know and see!’ It’s only natural to truly know and see when your mind is immersed in samādhi. When you truly know and see you need not make a wish: ‘May I become disillusioned and dispassionate!’ It’s only natural to become disillusioned and dispassionate when you truly know and see. When you’re disillusioned and dispassionate you need not make a wish: ‘May I realize the knowledge and vision of freedom!’ It’s only natural to realize the knowledge and vision of freedom when you’re disillusioned and dispassionate.

And so, mendicants, the knowledge and vision of freedom is the goal and benefit of disillusionment and dispassion. Disillusionment and dispassion is the goal and benefit of truly knowing and seeing. Truly knowing and seeing is the goal and benefit of immersion. Immersion is the goal and benefit of bliss. Bliss is the goal and benefit of tranquility. Tranquility is the goal and benefit of rapture. Rapture is the goal and benefit of joy. Joy is the goal and benefit of not having regrets. Not having regrets is the goal and benefit of skillful ethics. And so, mendicants, good qualities flow on and fill up from one to the other, for going from the near shore to the far shore.”

AN 10.3 Vital Conditions (1st) Paṭhamaupanisasutta

“Mendicants, an unethical person, who lacks ethics, has destroyed a vital condition for having no regrets. When there are regrets, one who has regrets has destroyed a vital condition for joy. When there is no joy, one who lacks joy has destroyed a vital condition for rapture. When there is no rapture, one who lacks rapture has destroyed a vital condition for tranquility. When there is no tranquility, one who lacks tranquility has destroyed a vital condition for bliss. When there is no bliss, one who lacks bliss has destroyed a vital condition for right immersion. When there is no right immersion, one who lacks right immersion has destroyed a vital condition for true knowledge and vision. When there is no true knowledge and vision, one who lacks true knowledge and vision has destroyed a vital condition for disillusionment and dispassion. When there is no disillusionment and dispassion, one who lacks disillusionment and dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

Suppose there was a tree that lacked branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would not grow to fullness.

In the same way, an unethical person, who lacks ethics, has destroyed a vital condition for having no regrets. When there are regrets, one who has regrets has destroyed a vital condition for joy. … One who lacks disillusionment and dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

An ethical person, who has fulfilled ethics, has fulfilled a vital condition for not having regrets. When there are no regrets, one who has no regrets has fulfilled a vital condition for joy. When there is joy, one who has fulfilled joy has fulfilled a vital condition for rapture. When there is rapture, one who has fulfilled rapture has fulfilled a vital condition for tranquility. When there is tranquility, one who has fulfilled tranquility has fulfilled a vital condition for bliss. When there is bliss, one who has fulfilled bliss has fulfilled a vital condition for right immersion. When there is right immersion, one who has fulfilled right immersion has fulfilled a vital condition for true knowledge and vision. When there is true knowledge and vision, one who has fulfilled true knowledge and vision has fulfilled a vital condition for disillusionment and dispassion. When there is disillusionment and dispassion, one who has fulfilled disillusionment and dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

Suppose there was a tree that was complete with branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would grow to fullness.

In the same way, an ethical person, who has fulfilled ethics, has fulfilled a vital condition for not having regrets. When there are no regrets, one who has no regrets has fulfilled a vital condition for joy. … One who has fulfilled disillusionment and dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.”

AN 10.4 Vital Conditions (2nd) Dutiyaupanisasutta

There Venerable Sāriputta addressed the mendicants … “Reverends, an unethical person, who lacks ethics, has destroyed a vital condition for having no regrets. When there are regrets, one who has regrets has destroyed a vital condition for joy. … One who lacks disillusionment and dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom. Suppose there was a tree that lacked branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would not grow to fullness. In the same way, an unethical person, who lacks ethics, has destroyed a vital condition for having no regrets. When there are regrets, one who has regrets has destroyed a vital condition for joy. … One who lacks disillusionment and dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

An ethical person, who has fulfilled ethics, has fulfilled a vital condition for not having regrets. When there are no regrets, one who has no regrets has fulfilled a vital condition for joy. … One who has fulfilled disillusionment and dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom. Suppose there was a tree that was complete with branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would grow to fullness. In the same way, an ethical person, who has fulfilled ethics, has fulfilled a vital condition for not having regrets. When there are no regrets, one who has no regrets has fulfilled a vital condition for joy. … One who has fulfilled disillusionment and dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.”

AN 10.5 Vital Conditions (3rd) Tatiyaupanisasutta

There Venerable Ānanda addressed the mendicants … “Reverends, an unethical person, who lacks ethics, has destroyed a vital condition for having no regrets. When there are regrets, one who has regrets has destroyed a vital condition for joy. When there is no joy, one who lacks joy has destroyed a vital condition for rapture. When there is no rapture, one who lacks rapture has destroyed a vital condition for tranquility. When there is no tranquility, one who lacks tranquility has destroyed a vital condition for bliss. When there is no bliss, one who lacks bliss has destroyed a vital condition for right immersion. When there is no right immersion, one who lacks right immersion has destroyed a vital condition for true knowledge and vision. When there is no true knowledge and vision, one who lacks true knowledge and vision has destroyed a vital condition for disillusionment and dispassion. When there is no disillusionment and dispassion, one who lacks disillusionment and dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

Suppose there was a tree that lacked branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would not grow to fullness.

In the same way, an unethical person, who lacks ethics, has destroyed a vital condition for having no regrets. When there are regrets, one who has regrets has destroyed a vital condition for joy. … One who lacks disillusionment and dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

An ethical person, who has fulfilled ethics, has fulfilled a vital condition for not having regrets. When there are no regrets, one who has no regrets has fulfilled a vital condition for joy. When there is joy, one who has fulfilled joy has fulfilled a vital condition for rapture. When there is rapture, one who has fulfilled rapture has fulfilled a vital condition for tranquility. When there is tranquility, one who has fulfilled tranquility has fulfilled a vital condition for bliss. When there is bliss, one who has fulfilled bliss has fulfilled a vital condition for right immersion. When there is right immersion, one who has fulfilled right immersion has fulfilled a vital condition for true knowledge and vision. When there is true knowledge and vision, one who has fulfilled true knowledge and vision has fulfilled a vital condition for disillusionment and dispassion. When there is disillusionment and dispassion, one who has fulfilled disillusionment and dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

Suppose there was a tree that was complete with branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would grow to fullness.

In the same way, an ethical person, who has fulfilled ethics, has fulfilled a vital condition for not having regrets. When there are no regrets, one who has no regrets has fulfilled a vital condition for joy. … One who has fulfilled disillusionment and dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.”

AN 10.6 Immersion Samādhisutta

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Could it be, sir, that a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this? They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. And they wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And yet they would still perceive.”

“It could be, Ānanda, that a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this. They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. And they wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And yet they would still perceive.”

“But how could this be, sir?”

“Ānanda, it’s when a mendicant perceives: ‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment.’

That’s how a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this. They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. And they wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And yet they would still perceive.”

AN 10.7 Sāriputta Sāriputtasutta

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to Venerable Sāriputta, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to Sāriputta:

“Could it be, reverend Sāriputta, that a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this? They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. And they wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And yet they would still perceive.”

“It could be, Reverend Ānanda.”

“But how could this be?”

“Reverend Ānanda, this one time I was staying right here at Sāvatthī in the Dark Forest. There I gained a state of immersion like this. I didn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And I didn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. And I didn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And yet I still perceived.”

“But at that time what did Reverend Sāriputta perceive?”

“One perception arose in me and another perception ceased: ‘The cessation of continued existence is extinguishment. The cessation of continued existence is extinguishment.’ Suppose there was a burning pile of twigs. One flame would arise and another would cease. In the same way, one perception arose in me and another perception ceased: ‘The cessation of continued existence is extinguishment. The cessation of continued existence is extinguishment.’ At that time I perceived that the cessation of continued existence is extinguishment.”

AN 10.8 Inspiring All Around: the Absorptions Jhānasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant is faithful but not ethical. So they’re incomplete in that respect, and should fulfill it, thinking: ‘How can I become faithful and ethical?’ When the mendicant is faithful and ethical, they’re complete in that respect.

A mendicant is faithful and ethical, but not learned. … they’re not a Dhamma speaker … they don’t frequent assemblies … they don’t teach Dhamma to the assembly with assurance … they’re not an expert in the monastic law … they don’t stay in the wilderness, in remote lodgings … they don’t get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty … they don’t realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. So they’re incomplete in that respect, and should fulfill it, thinking: ‘How can I become faithful, ethical, and learned, a Dhamma speaker, one who frequents assemblies, one who teaches Dhamma to the assembly with assurance, an expert in the training, one who lives in the wilderness, in remote lodgings, one who gets the four absorptions when they want, and one who lives having realized the ending of defilements?’

When they’re faithful, ethical, and learned, a Dhamma speaker, one who frequents assemblies, one who teaches Dhamma to the assembly with assurance, an expert in the training, one who lives in the wilderness, in remote lodgings, one who gets the four absorptions when they want, and one who lives having realized the ending of defilements, they’re complete in that respect. A mendicant who possesses these ten qualities is impressive all around, and is complete in every respect.”

AN 10.9 Inspiring All Around: the Peaceful Liberations Santavimokkhasutta

“A mendicant is faithful, but not ethical. … they’re not learned. … they’re not a Dhamma speaker … they don’t frequent assemblies … they don’t teach Dhamma to the assembly with assurance … they’re not an expert in the training … they don’t stay in the wilderness, in remote lodgings … they don’t have direct meditative experience of the peaceful liberations that are formless, transcending form … they don’t realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. So they’re incomplete in that respect, and should fulfill it, thinking: ‘How can I become faithful, ethical, and learned, a Dhamma speaker, one who frequents assemblies, one who teaches Dhamma to the assembly with assurance, an expert in the training, one who lives in the wilderness, in remote lodgings, one who gets the formless liberations, and one who lives having realized the ending of defilements?’

When they’re faithful, ethical, and learned, a Dhamma speaker, one who frequents assemblies, one who teaches Dhamma to the assembly with assurance, an expert in the monastic law, one who lives in the wilderness, in remote lodgings, one who gets the formless liberations, and one who lives having realized the ending of defilements, they’re complete in that respect. A mendicant who possesses these ten qualities is impressive all around, and is complete in every respect.”

AN 10.10 Inspiring All Around: the Three Knowledges Vijjāsutta

“A mendicant is faithful, but not ethical. So they’re incomplete in that respect, and should fulfill it, thinking: ‘How can I become faithful and ethical?’ When the mendicant is faithful and ethical, they’re complete in that respect.

A mendicant is faithful and ethical, but not learned … they’re not a Dhamma speaker … they don’t frequent assemblies … they don’t teach Dhamma to the assembly with assurance … they’re not an expert in the monastic law … they don’t recollect their many kinds of past lives … they don’t, with clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, see sentient beings passing away and being reborn … they don’t realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. So they’re incomplete in that respect, and should fulfill it, thinking: ‘How can I become faithful, ethical, and learned, a Dhamma speaker, one who frequents assemblies, one who teaches Dhamma to the assembly with assurance, an expert in the training, one who recollects their many kinds of past lives, one who with clairvoyance that surpasses the human sees sentient beings passing away and being reborn, and one who lives having realized the ending of defilements?’

When they are faithful, ethical, and learned, a Dhamma speaker, one who frequents assemblies, one who teaches Dhamma to the assembly with assurance, an expert in the training, one who recollects their many kinds of past lives, one who with clairvoyance that surpasses the human sees sentient beings passing away and being reborn, and one who lives having realized the ending of defilements, they’re complete in that respect. A mendicant who possesses these ten qualities is impressive all around, and is complete in every respect.”

The Chapter with Upāli

AN 10.31 With Upāli Upālisutta

Then Venerable Upāli went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, for how many reasons did the Realized One lay down training rules for his disciples and recite the monastic code?”

“Upāli, the Realized One laid down training rules for his disciples and recited the monastic code for ten reasons. What ten? For the well-being of the Saṅgha and for the comfort of the Saṅgha. For keeping difficult individuals in check and for the comfort of good-hearted mendicants. For restraining defilements that affect this life and protecting against defilements that affect lives to come. For inspiring confidence in those without it, and increasing confidence in those who have it. For the continuation of the true teaching and the support of the training. The Realized One laid down training rules for his disciples and recited the monastic code for these ten reasons.”

AN 10.32 Suspending the Recitation of the Monastic Code Pātimokkhaṭṭhapanāsutta

“Sir, how many grounds are there to suspend the recitation of the monastic code?”

“Upāli, there are ten grounds to suspend the recitation of the monastic code. What ten? A mendicant who has committed an expulsion offense is sitting in the assembly. A discussion about whether someone has committed an expulsion offense is unfinished. Someone who is not fully ordained is sitting in the assembly. A discussion about whether someone is fully ordained or not is unfinished. Someone who has resigned the training is sitting in the assembly. A discussion about whether someone has resigned the training or not is unfinished. A eunuch is sitting in the assembly. A discussion about whether someone is a eunuch is unfinished. A raper of nuns is sitting in the assembly. A discussion about whether or not someone is a raper of nuns is unfinished. These are the ten grounds to suspend the recitation of the monastic code.”

AN 10.33 A Judge Ubbāhikāsutta

“Sir, how many qualities should a mendicant have to be deemed a judge?”

“Upāli, a mendicant should have ten qualities to be deemed a judge. What ten? It’s when a mendicant is ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken. They’re very learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, rehearsing them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically. Both monastic codes have been passed down to them in detail, well analyzed, well mastered, well evaluated in both the rules and accompanying material. They’re firm and unfaltering in the training. When there are opposing parties, they’re able to persuade, advocate, and convince them, make them see the other side and trust each other. They’re skilled in the instigation and settlement of disciplinary issues. They know what a disciplinary issue is. They know how a disciplinary issue originates. They know how a disciplinary issue ceases. They know the practical way leading to the cessation of a disciplinary issue. A mendicant should possess these ten qualities to be deemed a judge.”

AN 10.34 Ordination Upasampadāsutta

“Sir, how many qualities should a mendicant have to give ordination?”

“Upāli, a mendicant should have ten qualities to give ordination. What ten? It’s when a mendicant is ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken. They’re very learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, rehearsing them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically. Both monastic codes have been passed down to them in detail, well analyzed, well mastered, well evaluated in both the rules and accompanying material. They’re able to care for the sick or get someone else to do so. They’re able to settle dissatisfaction or get someone else to do so. They’re able to dispel remorse when it has come up. They’re able to rationally dissuade someone from misconceptions that come up. They’re able to encourage someone in the higher ethics, the higher mind, and the higher wisdom. A mendicant should possess these ten qualities to give ordination.”

AN 10.35 Dependence Nissayasutta

“Sir, how many qualities should a mendicant have to give dependence?”

“Upāli, a mendicant should have ten qualities to give dependence. What ten? It’s when a mendicant is ethical … They’re learned … Both monastic codes have been passed down to them in detail, well analyzed, well mastered, well evaluated in both the rules and accompanying material. They’re able to care for the sick or get someone else to do so. They’re able to settle dissatisfaction or get someone else to do so. They’re able to dispel remorse when it has come up. They’re able to rationally dissuade someone from misconceptions that come up. They’re able to encourage someone in the higher ethics, the higher mind, and the higher wisdom. A mendicant should possess these ten qualities to give dependence.”

AN 10.36 A Novice Sāmaṇerasutta

“Sir, how many qualities should a mendicant have to be attended on by a novice?”

“Upāli, a mendicant should have ten qualities to be attended on by a novice. What ten? It’s when a mendicant is ethical … They’re learned … Both monastic codes have been passed down to them in detail, well analyzed, well mastered, well evaluated in both the rules and accompanying material. They’re able to care for the sick or get someone else to do so. They’re able to settle dissatisfaction or get someone else to do so. They’re able to dispel remorse when it has come up. They’re able to rationally dissuade someone from misconceptions that come up. They’re able to encourage someone in the higher ethics, the higher mind, and the higher wisdom. A mendicant should possess these ten qualities to be attended on by a novice.”

AN 10.37 Schism in the Saṅgha Saṁghabhedasutta

“Sir, they speak of ‘schism in the Saṅgha’. How is schism in the Saṅgha defined?”

“Upāli, it’s when a mendicant explains what is not the teaching as the teaching, and what is the teaching as not the teaching. They explain what is not the training as the training, and what is the training as not the training. They explain what was not spoken and stated by the Realized One as spoken and stated by the Realized One, and what was spoken and stated by the Realized One as not spoken and stated by the Realized One. They explain what was not practiced by the Realized One as practiced by the Realized One, and what was practiced by the Realized One as not practiced by the Realized One. They explain what was not prescribed by the Realized One as prescribed by the Realized One, and what was prescribed by the Realized One as not prescribed by the Realized One. On these ten grounds they split off and go their own way. They perform legal acts autonomously and recite the monastic code autonomously. That is how schism in the Saṅgha is defined.”

AN 10.38 Harmony in the Saṅgha Saṁghasāmaggīsutta

“Sir, they speak of ‘harmony in the Saṅgha’. How is harmony in the Saṅgha defined?”

“Upāli, it’s when a mendicant explains what is not the teaching as not the teaching, and what is the teaching as the teaching. They explain what is not the training as not the training, and what is the training as the training. They explain what was not spoken and stated by the Realized One as not spoken and stated by the Realized One, and what was spoken and stated by the Realized One as spoken and stated by the Realized One. They explain what was not practiced by the Realized One as not practiced by the Realized One, and what was practiced by the Realized One as practiced by the Realized One. They explain what was not prescribed by the Realized One as not prescribed by the Realized One, and what was prescribed by the Realized One as prescribed by the Realized One. On these ten grounds they don’t split off and go their own way. They don’t perform legal acts autonomously or recite the monastic code autonomously. That is how harmony in the Saṅgha is defined.”

AN 10.39 With Ānanda (1st) Paṭhamaānandasutta

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, they speak of ‘schism in the Saṅgha’. How is schism in the Saṅgha defined?”

“Ānanda, it’s when a mendicant explains what is not the teaching as the teaching … and what was prescribed by the Realized One as not prescribed by the Realized One. On these ten grounds they split off and go their own way. They perform legal acts autonomously and recite the monastic code autonomously. That is how schism in the Saṅgha is defined.”

“But sir, what does someone who has split a harmonious Saṅgha brim with?”

“They brim with sin that lasts for an eon.”

“But sir, what is the sin that lasts for an eon?”

“They burn in hell for an eon, Ānanda.

A schismatic remains for the eon
in a place of loss, in hell.
Taking a stand against the teaching,
favoring factions, they ruin their sanctuary.
After causing schism in a harmonious Saṅgha,
they burn in hell for an eon.”

AN 10.40 With Ānanda (2nd) Dutiyaānandasutta

“Sir, they speak of ‘harmony in the Saṅgha’. How is harmony in the Saṅgha defined?”

“Ānanda, it’s when a mendicant explains what is not the teaching as not the teaching, and what is the teaching as the teaching. They explain what is not the training as not the training, and what is the training as the training. They explain what was not spoken and stated by the Realized One as not spoken and stated by the Realized One, and what was spoken and stated by the Realized One as spoken and stated by the Realized One. They explain what was not practiced by the Realized One as not practiced by the Realized One, and what was practiced by the Realized One as practiced by the Realized One. They explain what was not prescribed by the Realized One as not prescribed by the Realized One, and what was prescribed by the Realized One as prescribed by the Realized One. On these ten grounds they don’t split off and go their own way. They don’t perform legal acts autonomously or recite the monastic code autonomously. That is how harmony in the Saṅgha is defined.”

“But sir, what does someone who has forged harmony in a schismatic Saṅgha brim with?”

“They brim with divine merit.”

“But what is divine merit?”

“They rejoice in heaven for an eon, Ānanda.

A Saṅgha in harmony is happy,
as is support for those in harmony.
Taking a stand on the teaching,
favoring harmony, they ruin no sanctuary.
After forging harmony in the Saṅgha,
they rejoice in heaven for an eon.”

Abbreviated Texts Beginning With Greed

AN 10.237 Untitled Discourse on Greed (1st) ~

“For insight into greed, ten things should be developed. What ten? The perceptions of ugliness, death, repulsiveness of food, dissatisfaction with the whole world, impermanence, suffering in impermanence, and not-self in suffering, giving up, fading away, and cessation. For insight into greed, these ten things should be developed.”

AN 10.238 Untitled Discourse on Greed (2nd) ~

“For insight into greed, ten things should be developed. What ten? The perceptions of impermanence, not-self, repulsiveness of food, dissatisfaction with the whole world, a skeleton, a worm-infested corpse, a livid corpse, a festering corpse, a split open corpse, and a bloated corpse. For insight into greed, these ten things should be developed.”

AN 10.239 Untitled Discourse on Greed (3rd) ~

“For insight into greed, ten things should be developed. What ten? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. For insight into greed, these ten things should be developed.”

AN 10.240–266 Untitled Discourses on Greed ~

“For the complete understanding of greed … complete ending … giving up … ending … vanishing … fading away … cessation … giving away … letting go … these ten things should be developed.”

AN 10.267–746 Untitled Discourses on Hate, Etc. ~

“Of hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … jealousy … stinginess … deceitfulness … deviousness … obstinacy … aggression … conceit … arrogance … vanity … for the complete understanding of negligence … complete ending … giving up … ending … vanishing … fading away … cessation … giving away … letting go of negligence … these ten things should be developed.”

The Book of the Tens is finished.

The Chapter on Similarity

AN 10.221 Untitled Discourse on Ten Qualities ~

“Someone with ten qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there. What ten? They kill living creatures, steal, and commit sexual misconduct. They use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. And they’re covetous, malicious, with wrong view. Someone with these ten qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there.

Someone with ten qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there. What ten? They don’t kill living creatures, steal, or commit sexual misconduct. They don’t use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. They’re contented, kind-hearted, with right view. Someone with these ten qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there.”

AN 10.222 Untitled Discourse on Twenty Qualities ~

“Someone with twenty qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there. What twenty? They kill living creatures, steal, and commit sexual misconduct. They use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. They’re covetous, malicious, with wrong view. And they encourage others to do these things. Someone with these twenty qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there.

Someone with twenty qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there. What twenty? They don’t kill living creatures, steal, or commit sexual misconduct. They don’t use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. They’re contented, kind-hearted, with right view. And they encourage others to do these things. Someone with these twenty qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there.”

AN 10.223 Untitled Discourse on Thirty Qualities ~

“Someone with thirty qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there. What thirty? They kill living creatures, steal, and commit sexual misconduct. They use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. They’re covetous, malicious, with wrong view. They encourage others to do these things. And they approve of these things. Someone with these thirty qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there.

Someone with thirty qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there. What thirty? They don’t kill living creatures, steal, or commit sexual misconduct. They don’t use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. They’re contented, kind-hearted, with right view. They encourage others to do these things. And they approve of these things. Someone with these thirty qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there.”

AN 10.224 Untitled Discourse on Forty Qualities ~

“Someone with forty qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there. What forty? They kill living creatures, steal, and commit sexual misconduct. They use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. They’re covetous, malicious, with wrong view. They encourage others to do these things. They approve of these things. And they praise these things. Someone with these forty qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there.

Someone with forty qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there. What forty? They don’t kill living creatures, steal, or commit sexual misconduct. They don’t use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical. They’re contented, kind-hearted, with right view. They encourage others to do these things. They approve of these things. And they praise these things. Someone with these forty qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there.”

AN 10.225–228 Untitled Discourses on Ten to Forty Qualities (1st) ~

“Someone with ten qualities keeps themselves broken and damaged … keeps themselves intact and unscathed … twenty … thirty … forty …”

AN 10.229–232 Untitled Discourses on Ten to Forty Qualities (2nd) ~

“When they have ten qualities, some people, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. … some people, when their body breaks up, after death, are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm … twenty … thirty … forty …”

AN 10.233–236 Untitled Discourses on Ten to Forty Qualities (3rd) ~

“A fool is known by ten qualities … astute person … twenty … thirty … forty …”

The Third Fifty

The Chapter on Perceptions for Ascetics

AN 10.101 Perceptions for Ascetics Samaṇasaññāsutta

“Mendicants, when these three perceptions for ascetics are developed and cultivated they fulfill seven things. What three? ‘I have secured freedom from class.’ ‘My livelihood is tied up with others.’ ‘My behavior should be different.’ When these three perceptions for ascetics are developed and cultivated they fulfill seven things.

What seven? Their deeds and behavior are always consistent with the precepts. They’re content, kind-hearted, and humble. They want to train. They use the necessities of life after reflecting on their purpose. They’re energetic. When those three perceptions for ascetics are developed and cultivated they fulfill these seven things.”

AN 10.102 Awakening Factors Bojjhaṅgasutta

“Mendicants, when the seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated they fulfill three knowledges. What seven? The awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity. When these seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated they fulfill three knowledges. What three? It’s when a mendicant recollects their many kinds of past lives. That is: one, two, three, four, five, ten, twenty, thirty, forty, fifty, a hundred, a thousand, a hundred thousand rebirths; many eons of the world contracting, many eons of the world expanding, many eons of the world contracting and expanding. They recollect their many kinds of past lives, with features and details. With clairvoyance that is purified and surpasses the human, they understand how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds. They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. When those seven awakening factors are developed and cultivated they fulfill these three knowledges.”

AN 10.103 The Wrong Way Micchattasutta

“Mendicants, relying on the wrong way leads to failure, not success. And how does relying on the wrong way lead to failure, not success? Wrong view produces wrong purpose. Wrong purpose produces wrong speech. Wrong speech produces wrong action. Wrong action produces wrong livelihood. Wrong livelihood produces wrong effort. Wrong effort produces wrong mindfulness. Wrong mindfulness produces wrong immersion. Wrong immersion produces wrong knowledge. Wrong knowledge produces wrong freedom. That’s how relying on the wrong way leads to failure, not success.

Relying on the right way leads to success, not failure. And how does relying on the right way lead to success, not failure? Right view produces right purpose. Right purpose produces right speech. Right speech produces right action. Right action produces right livelihood. Right livelihood produces right effort. Right effort produces right mindfulness. Right mindfulness produces right immersion. Right immersion produces right knowledge. Right knowledge produces right freedom. That’s how relying on the right way leads to success, not failure.”

AN 10.104 A Seed Bījasutta

“Mendicants, consider an individual who has wrong view, purpose, speech, action, livelihood, effort, mindfulness, immersion, knowledge, and freedom. Whatever bodily, verbal, or mental deeds they undertake in line with that view, their intentions, aims, wishes, and choices all lead to what is unlikable, undesirable, disagreeable, harmful, and suffering. Why is that? Because their view is bad.

Suppose a seed of neem, angled gourd, or bitter gourd was planted in moist earth. Whatever nutrients it takes up from the earth and water would lead to its bitter, acerbic, and unpleasant taste. Why is that? Because the seed is bad. In the same way, consider an individual who has wrong view, purpose, speech, action, livelihood, effort, mindfulness, immersion, knowledge, and freedom. Whatever bodily, verbal, or mental deeds they undertake in line with that view, their intentions, aims, wishes, and choices all lead to what is unlikable, undesirable, disagreeable, harmful, and suffering. Why is that? Because their view is bad.

Consider an individual who has right view, purpose, speech, action, livelihood, effort, mindfulness, immersion, knowledge, and freedom. Whatever bodily, verbal, or mental deeds they undertake in line with that view, their intentions, aims, wishes, and choices all lead to what is likable, desirable, agreeable, beneficial, and pleasant. Why is that? Because their view is good.

Suppose a seed of sugarcane, fine rice, or grape was planted in moist earth. Whatever nutrients it takes up from the earth and water would lead to its sweet, pleasant, delectable flavor. Why is that? Because the seed is good. In the same way, consider an individual who has right view, purpose, speech, action, livelihood, effort, mindfulness, immersion, knowledge, and freedom. Whatever bodily, verbal, or mental deeds they undertake in line with that view, their intentions, aims, wishes, and choices all lead to what is likable, desirable, agreeable, beneficial, and pleasant. Why is that? Because their view is good.”

AN 10.105 Knowledge Vijjāsutta

“Mendicants, ignorance leads the attainment of unskillful qualities, with lack of conscience and prudence following along. An ignoramus, sunk in ignorance, produces wrong view. Wrong view produces wrong purpose. Wrong purpose produces wrong speech. Wrong speech produces wrong action. Wrong action produces wrong livelihood. Wrong livelihood produces wrong effort. Wrong effort produces wrong mindfulness. Wrong mindfulness produces wrong immersion. Wrong immersion produces wrong knowledge. Wrong knowledge produces wrong freedom.

Knowledge leads the attainment of skillful qualities, with conscience and prudence following along. A knowing one, firm in knowledge, produces right view. Right view produces right purpose. Right purpose produces right speech. Right speech produces right action. Right action produces right livelihood. Right livelihood produces right effort. Right effort produces right mindfulness. Right mindfulness produces right immersion. Right immersion produces right knowledge. Right knowledge produces right freedom.”

AN 10.106 Wearing Away Nijjarasutta

“Mendicants, there are these ten grounds for wearing away. What ten?

For one of right view, wrong view is worn away. And the many bad, unskillful qualities that arise because of wrong view are worn away. And because of right view, many skillful qualities are fully developed.

For one of right purpose, wrong purpose is worn away. And the many bad, unskillful qualities that arise because of wrong purpose are worn away. And because of right purpose, many skillful qualities are fully developed.

For one of right speech, wrong speech is worn away. And the many bad, unskillful qualities that arise because of wrong speech are worn away. And because of right speech, many skillful qualities are fully developed.

For one of right action, wrong action is worn away. And the many bad, unskillful qualities that arise because of wrong action are worn away. And because of right action, many skillful qualities are fully developed.

For one of right livelihood, wrong livelihood is worn away. And the many bad, unskillful qualities that arise because of wrong livelihood are worn away. And because of right livelihood, many skillful qualities are fully developed.

For one of right effort, wrong effort is worn away. And the many bad, unskillful qualities that arise because of wrong effort are worn away. And because of right effort, many skillful qualities are fully developed.

For one of right mindfulness, wrong mindfulness is worn away. And the many bad, unskillful qualities that arise because of wrong mindfulness are worn away. And because of right mindfulness, many skillful qualities are fully developed.

For one of right immersion, wrong immersion is worn away. And the many bad, unskillful qualities that arise because of wrong immersion are worn away. And because of right immersion, many skillful qualities are fully developed.

For one of right knowledge, wrong knowledge is worn away. And the many bad, unskillful qualities that arise because of wrong knowledge are worn away. And because of right knowledge, many skillful qualities are fully developed.

For one of right freedom, wrong freedom is worn away. And the many bad, unskillful qualities that arise because of wrong freedom are worn away. And because of right freedom, many skillful qualities are fully developed.

These are the ten grounds for wearing away.”

AN 10.107 The Bone-Washing Ceremony Dhovanasutta

“Mendicants, in the southern lands there is a ceremony named ‘bone-washing’. There they have food, drink, snacks, meals, refreshments, and beverages, as well as dancing, singing, and music. There is such a washing, I don’t deny it. But that washing is low, crude, ordinary, ignoble, and pointless. It doesn’t lead to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment.

I will teach a noble washing that leads solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment. Relying on that washing, sentient beings who are liable to rebirth, old age, and death, to sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress are freed from all these things. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“And what is that noble washing?

For one of right view, wrong view is washed away. And the many bad, unskillful qualities that arise because of wrong view are washed away. And because of right view, many skillful qualities are fully developed.

For one of right purpose, wrong purpose is washed away. … For one of right speech, wrong speech is washed away. … For one of right action, wrong action is washed away. … For one of right livelihood, wrong livelihood is washed away. … For one of right effort, wrong effort is washed away. … For one of right mindfulness, wrong mindfulness is washed away. … For one of right immersion, wrong immersion is washed away. … For one of right knowledge, wrong knowledge is washed away. …

For one of right freedom, wrong freedom is washed away. And the many bad, unskillful qualities that arise because of wrong freedom are washed away. And because of right freedom, many skillful qualities are fully developed. This is the noble washing that leads solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment. Relying on this washing, sentient beings who are liable to rebirth, old age, and death, to sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress are freed from all these things.”

AN 10.108 Doctors Tikicchakasutta

“Mendicants, doctors prescribe a purgative for eliminating illnesses stemming from disorders of bile, phlegm, and wind. There is such a purgative, I don’t deny it. But this kind of purgative sometimes works and sometimes fails.

I will teach a noble purgative that works without fail. Relying on that purgative, sentient beings who are liable to rebirth, old age, and death, to sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress are freed from all these things. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“And what is the noble purgative that works without fail?

For one of right view, wrong view is purged. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong view are purged. And because of right view, many skillful qualities are fully developed.

For one of right purpose, wrong purpose is purged. … For one of right speech, wrong speech is purged. … For one of right action, wrong action is purged. … For one of right livelihood, wrong livelihood is purged. … For one of right effort, wrong effort is purged. … For one of right mindfulness, wrong mindfulness is purged. … For one of right immersion, wrong immersion is purged. … For one of right knowledge, wrong knowledge is purged. …

For one of right freedom, wrong freedom is purged. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong freedom are purged. And because of right freedom, many skillful qualities are fully developed. This is the noble purgative that works without fail. Relying on this purgative, sentient beings who are liable to rebirth, old age, and death, to sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress are freed from all these things.”

AN 10.109 Emetic Vamanasutta

“Mendicants, doctors prescribe an emetic for eliminating illnesses stemming from disorders of bile, phlegm, and wind. There is such an emetic, I don’t deny it. But this kind of emetic sometimes works and sometimes fails.

I will teach a noble emetic that works without fail. Relying on that emetic, sentient beings who are liable to rebirth, old age, and death, to sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress are freed from all these things. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak. …

And what is that noble emetic that works without fail?

For one of right view, wrong view is vomited up. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong view are vomited up. And because of right view, many skillful qualities are fully developed.

For one of right purpose, wrong purpose is vomited up. … For one of right speech, wrong speech is vomited up. … For one of right action, wrong action is vomited up. … For one of right livelihood, wrong livelihood is vomited up. … For one of right effort, wrong effort is vomited up. … For one of right mindfulness, wrong mindfulness is vomited up. … For one of right immersion, wrong immersion is vomited up. … For one of right knowledge, wrong knowledge is vomited up. …

For one of right freedom, wrong freedom is vomited up. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong freedom are vomited up. And because of right freedom, many skillful qualities are fully developed. This is the noble emetic that works without fail. Relying on this emetic, sentient beings who are liable to rebirth, old age, and death, to sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress are freed from all these things.”

AN 10.110 Blown Away Niddhamanīyasutta

“Mendicants, these ten qualities should be blown away. What ten? For one of right view, wrong view is blown away. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong view are blown away. And because of right view, many skillful qualities are fully developed.

For one of right purpose, wrong purpose is blown away. … For one of right speech, wrong speech is blown away. … For one of right action, wrong action is blown away. … For one of right livelihood, wrong livelihood is blown away. … For one of right effort, wrong effort is blown away. … For one of right mindfulness, wrong mindfulness is blown away. … For one of right immersion, wrong immersion is blown away. … For one of right knowledge, wrong knowledge is blown away. …

For one of right freedom, wrong freedom is blown away. And the many bad, unskillful qualities produced by wrong freedom are blown away. And because of right freedom, many skillful qualities are fully developed. These are the ten qualities that should be blown away.”

AN 10.111 An Adept (1st) Paṭhamaasekhasutta

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, they speak of the one called ‘an adept’. How is an adept mendicant defined?”

“Mendicant, it’s when a mendicant has an adept’s right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. That’s how a mendicant is an adept.”

AN 10.112 An Adept (2nd) Dutiyaasekhasutta

“Mendicants, there are ten qualities of an adept. What ten? An adept’s right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. These are the ten qualities of an adept.”

The Chapter on Good

AN 10.134 Good Sādhusutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you what is good and what is not good. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“And what, mendicants, is not good? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called what is not good. And what is good? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called what is good.”

AN 10.135 The Teaching of the Noble Ones Ariyadhammasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the teaching of the noble ones, and what is not the teaching of the noble ones. … And what is not the teaching of the noble ones? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called what is not the teaching of the noble ones. And what is the teaching of the noble ones? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the teaching of the noble ones.”

AN 10.136 Unskillful Akusalasutta

“I will teach you the skillful and the unskillful … And what is the unskillful? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called the unskillful. And what is the skillful? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the skillful.”

AN 10.137 Beneficial Atthasutta

“I will teach you the beneficial and the harmful. … And what is the harmful? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called the harmful. And what is the beneficial? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the beneficial.”

AN 10.138 The Teaching Dhammasutta

“I will teach you what is the teaching and what is not the teaching. … And what is not the teaching? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called what is not the teaching. And what is the teaching? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the teaching.”

AN 10.139 Defiled Sāsavasutta

“I will teach you the defiled principle and the undefiled. … And what is the defiled principle? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called the defiled principle. And what is the undefiled principle? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the undefiled principle.”

AN 10.140 Blameworthy Sāvajjasutta

“I will teach you the blameworthy principle and the blameless principle. … And what is the blameworthy principle? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called the blameworthy principle. And what is the blameless principle? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the blameless principle.”

AN 10.141 Mortifying Tapanīyasutta

“I will teach you the mortifying principle and the unmortifying. … And what is the mortifying principle? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called the mortifying principle. And what is the unmortifying principle? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the unmortifying principle.”

AN 10.142 Accumulation Ācayagāmisutta

“I will teach you the principle that leads to accumulation and that which leads to dispersal. … And what is the principle that leads to accumulation? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called the principle that leads to accumulation. And what is the principle that leads to dispersal? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the principle that leads to dispersal.”

AN 10.143 With Suffering as Outcome Dukkhudrayasutta

“I will teach you the principle that has suffering as outcome, and that which has happiness as outcome. … And what is the principle whose outcome is suffering? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is the principle whose outcome is suffering. And what is the principle whose outcome is happiness? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is the principle whose outcome is happiness.”

AN 10.144 Result in Suffering Dukkhavipākasutta

“I will teach you the principle that results in suffering and that which results in happiness. … And what principle results in suffering? Wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, wrong immersion, wrong knowledge, and wrong freedom. This is called the principle that results in suffering. And what principle results in happiness? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right immersion, right knowledge, and right freedom. This is called the principle that results in happiness.”

The Chapter on Senior Mendicants

AN 10.81 With Bāhuna Vāhanasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Campā on the banks of the Gaggarā Lotus Pond. Then Venerable Bāhuna went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, how many things has the Realized One escaped from, so that he lives detached, liberated, with mind free of boundaries?”

“Bāhuna, the Realized One has escaped from ten things, so that he lives detached, liberated, with mind free of boundaries. What ten? Form … feeling … perception … choices … consciousness … rebirth … old age … death … suffering … defilements … Suppose there was a blue water lily, or a pink or white lotus. Though it sprouted and grew in the water, it would rise up above the water and stand with no water clinging to it. In the same way, the Realized One has escaped from ten things, so that he lives detached, liberated, with mind free of boundaries.”

AN 10.82 With Ānanda Ānandasutta

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him:

“Ānanda, it is quite impossible for a faithless mendicant to achieve growth, improvement, or maturity in this teaching and training.

It is quite impossible for a mendicant who is unethical …

unlearned …

hard to admonish …

with bad friends …

lazy …

unmindful …

lacking contentment …

of corrupt wishes …

of wrong view to achieve growth, improvement, or maturity in this teaching and training.

It is quite impossible for a mendicant with these ten qualities to achieve growth, improvement, or maturity in this teaching and training.

It is quite possible for a faithful mendicant to achieve growth, improvement, or maturity in this teaching and training.

It is quite possible for a mendicant who is ethical …

a learned memorizer …

easy to admonish …

with good friends …

energetic …

mindful …

contented …

of few desires …

of right view to achieve growth, improvement, or maturity in this teaching and training.

It is quite possible for a mendicant with these ten qualities to achieve growth, improvement, or maturity in this teaching and training.”

AN 10.83 With Puṇṇiya Puṇṇiyasutta

Then Venerable Puṇṇiya went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, what is the cause, what is the reason why sometimes the Realized One feels inspired to teach, and other times not?”

“Puṇṇiya, when a mendicant has faith but doesn’t approach, the Realized One doesn’t feel inspired to teach. But when a mendicant has faith and approaches, the Realized One feels inspired to teach.

When a mendicant has faith and approaches, but doesn’t pay homage … they pay homage, but don’t ask questions … they ask questions, but don’t actively listen to the teaching … they actively listen to the teaching, but don’t remember the teaching they’ve heard … they remember the teaching they’ve heard, but don’t examine the meaning of the teachings they’ve remembered … they examine the meaning of the teachings they’ve remembered, but, not having understood the meaning and the teaching, they don’t practice in line with the principle of the teaching … they practice in line with the teaching, but they’re not a good speaker and do not enunciate well. Their voice is not polished, clear, articulate, and doesn’t express the meaning … They’re a good speaker who enunciates well, but they don’t educate, encourage, fire up, and inspire their spiritual companions. The Realized One doesn’t feel inspired to teach.

But when a mendicant has faith, approaches, pays homage, asks questions, actively listens to the teachings, remembers the teachings, examines the meaning, practices in line with the principle of the teaching, has a good voice, and encourages their spiritual companions, the Realized One feels inspired to teach. When someone possesses these ten qualities, the Realized One feels totally inspired to teach.”

AN 10.84 Declaration Byākaraṇasutta

There Venerable Mahāmoggallāna addressed the mendicants: “Reverends, mendicants!”

“Reverend,” they replied. Venerable Mahāmoggallāna said this:

“Take a mendicant who declares enlightenment: ‘I understand: “Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.”’ They’re pursued, pressed, and grilled by the Realized One, or by one of his disciples who is a meditator skilled in attainments, in the minds of others, and in encompassing another’s mind. Grilled in this way they get stuck or lose their way. They fall to ruin and disaster.

The Realized One or one of his disciples encompasses their mind and investigates: ‘Why does this venerable declare enlightenment, saying:

“I understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place’”?’

They understand:

‘This venerable gets irritable, and often lives with a heart full of anger. But being full of anger means decline in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.

This venerable is acrimonious …

prone to disdain …

contemptuous …

jealous …

stingy …

devious …

deceitful …

This venerable has corrupt wishes, and often lives with a heart full of desire. But being full of desire means decline in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.

When there is still more to be done, this venerable stopped half-way after achieving some trifling distinction. But stopping half-way means decline in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.’

It is quite impossible for a mendicant to achieve growth, improvement, or maturity in this teaching and training without giving up these ten qualities. It is quite possible for a mendicant to achieve growth, improvement, or maturity in this teaching and training after giving up these ten qualities.”

AN 10.85 A Boaster Katthīsutta

At one time Venerable Mahācunda was staying in the land of the Cetīs at Sahajāti. There he addressed the mendicants: “Reverends, mendicants!”

“Reverend,” they replied. Venerable Mahācunda said this:

“Take a mendicant who boasts and brags about their achievements: ‘I enter and emerge from the first absorption, the second absorption, the third absorption, and the fourth absorption. And I enter and emerge from the dimensions of infinite space, infinite consciousness, nothingness, and neither perception nor non-perception. And I enter and emerge from the cessation of perception and feeling.’

They’re pursued, pressed, and grilled by the Realized One, or by one of his disciples who has the absorptions, and is skilled in attainments, in the minds of others, and in encompassing another’s mind. Grilled in this way they get stuck or lose their way. They fall to ruin and disaster.

The Realized One or one of his disciples encompasses their mind and investigates: ‘Why does this venerable boast and brag about their achievements, saying, “I enter and emerge from the first absorption … and the cessation of perception and feeling.”’

They understand, ‘For a long time this venerable’s deeds have been broken, tainted, spotty, and marred. Their deeds and behavior are inconsistent. This venerable is unethical, and unethical conduct means decline in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.

This venerable is unfaithful, and lack of faith means decline …

This venerable is unlearned and unpracticed, and lack of learning means decline …

This venerable is hard to admonish, and being hard to admonish means decline …

This venerable has bad friends, and bad friends mean decline …

This venerable is lazy, and laziness means decline …

This venerable is unmindful, and unmindfulness means decline …

This venerable is deceptive, and deceitfulness means decline …

This venerable is burdensome, and being burdensome means decline …

This venerable is witless, and lack of wisdom means decline in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.’

Suppose one friend was to say to another: ‘My dear, when you need money for some payment, just ask me and I’ll give it.’ Then when some payment falls due, that friend says to their friend: ‘I need some money, my dear. Give me some.’ They’d say: ‘Well then, my dear, dig here.’ So they dig there, but don’t find anything. They’d say: ‘You lied to me, my dear, you spoke hollow words when you told me to dig here.’ They’d say: ‘My dear, I didn’t lie or speak hollow words. Well then, dig here.’ So they dig there as well, but don’t find anything. They’d say: ‘You lied to me, my dear, you spoke hollow words when you said dig here.’ They’d say: ‘My dear, I didn’t lie or speak hollow words. Well then, dig here.’ So they dig there as well, but don’t find anything. They’d say: ‘You lied to me, my dear, you spoke hollow words when you said dig here.’ They’d say: ‘My dear, I didn’t lie or speak hollow words. But I had gone mad, I was out of my mind.’

In the same way, take a mendicant who boasts and brags about their achievements: ‘I enter and emerge from the first absorption … and the cessation of perception and feeling.’

They’re pursued, pressed, and grilled by the Realized One, or by one of his disciples … Grilled in this way they get stuck or lose their way. They fall to ruin and disaster.

The Realized One or one of his disciples encompasses their mind and investigates: ‘Why does this venerable boast and brag about their achievements, saying, “I enter and emerge from the first absorption … and the cessation of perception and feeling.”’

They understand, ‘For a long time this venerable’s deeds have been broken, tainted, spotty, and marred. Their deeds and behavior are inconsistent. This venerable is unethical, and unethical conduct means decline in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.

This venerable is unfaithful …

unlearned and unpracticed …

hard to admonish …

with bad friends …

lazy …

unmindful …

deceptive …

burdensome …

This venerable is witless, and lack of wisdom means decline in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.’

It is quite impossible for a mendicant to achieve growth, improvement, or maturity in this teaching and training without giving up these ten qualities. It is quite possible for a mendicant to achieve growth, improvement, or maturity in this teaching and training after giving up these ten qualities.”

AN 10.86 Overestimation Adhimānasutta

At one time Venerable Mahākassapa was staying near Rājagaha in the Bamboo Grove, the squirrels’ feeding ground. There he addressed the mendicants: “Reverends, mendicants!”

“Reverend,” they replied. Venerable Mahākassapa said this:

“Take a mendicant who declares enlightenment: ‘I understand: “Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.”’ They’re pursued, pressed, and grilled by the Realized One, or by one of his disciples who has the absorptions, and is skilled in attainments, in the minds of others, and in encompassing another’s mind. Grilled in this way they get stuck or lose their way. They fall to ruin and disaster.

The Realized One or one of his disciples encompasses their mind and investigates: ‘Why does this venerable declare enlightenment, saying, “I understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place’”?’

They understand, ‘This venerable overestimates themselves and takes that to be the truth. They perceive that they’ve attained what they haven’t attained, done what they haven’t done, and achieved what they haven’t achieved. And they declare enlightenment out of overestimation:

“I understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”’

The Realized One or one of his disciples encompasses their mind and investigates: ‘Why does this venerable overestimate themselves and take that to be the truth? Why do they perceive that they’ve attained what they haven’t attained, done what they haven’t done, and achieved what they haven’t achieved? And why do they declare enlightenment out of overestimation:

“I understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”’

They understand, ‘This venerable is very learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, rehearsing them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically. Therefore this venerable overestimates themselves and takes that to be the truth. …’

They understand, ‘This venerable is covetous, and often lives with a heart full of covetousness. But being full of covetousness means decline in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.

This venerable has ill will …

dullness and drowsiness …

restlessness …

doubt …

This venerable relishes work. They love it and like to relish it …

This venerable relishes talk …

sleep …

company …

When there is still more to be done, this venerable stopped half-way after achieving some trifling distinction. But stopping half-way means decline in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.’

It is quite impossible for a mendicant to achieve growth, improvement, or maturity in this teaching and training without giving up these ten qualities. It is quite possible for a mendicant to achieve growth, improvement, or maturity in this teaching and training after giving up these ten qualities.”

AN 10.87 Disciplinary Issues Nappiyasutta

There the Buddha addressed the mendicants concerning the mendicant Kalandaka:

“Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Firstly, a mendicant raises disciplinary issues and doesn’t praise the settling of disciplinary issues. This quality doesn’t conduce to fondness, respect, esteem, harmony, and unity.

Furthermore, a mendicant doesn’t want to train, and doesn’t praise taking up the training. …

Furthermore, a mendicant has corrupt wishes, and doesn’t praise getting rid of wishes. …

Furthermore, a mendicant is irritable, and doesn’t praise getting rid of anger. …

Furthermore, a mendicant denigrates others, and doesn’t praise getting rid of denigration. …

Furthermore, a mendicant is devious, and doesn’t praise getting rid of deviousness. …

Furthermore, a mendicant is deceitful, and doesn’t praise getting rid of deceitfulness. …

Furthermore, a mendicant doesn’t pay attention to the teachings, and doesn’t praise attending to the teachings. …

Furthermore, a mendicant is not in retreat, and doesn’t praise retreat. …

Furthermore, a mendicant is inhospitable to their spiritual companions, and doesn’t praise hospitality. This quality doesn’t conduce to fondness, respect, esteem, harmony, and unity.

Even though a mendicant such as this might wish: ‘If only my spiritual companions would honor, respect, esteem, and venerate me!’ Still they don’t honor, respect, esteem, and venerate them. Why is that? Because their sensible spiritual companions see that they haven’t given up those bad unskillful qualities.

Suppose a wild colt was to wish: ‘If only the humans would put me in a thoroughbred’s place, feed me a thoroughbred’s food, and give me a thoroughbred’s grooming.’ Still the humans wouldn’t put them in a thoroughbred’s place, feed them a thoroughbred’s food, or give them a thoroughbred’s grooming. Why is that? Because sensible humans see that they haven’t given up their tricks, bluffs, ruses, and feints. In the same way, even though a mendicant such as this might wish: ‘If only my spiritual companions would honor, respect, esteem, and venerate me!’ Still they don’t honor, respect, esteem, and venerate them. Why is that? Because their sensible spiritual companions see that they haven’t given up those bad unskillful qualities.

Next, a mendicant doesn’t raise disciplinary issues and praises the settling of disciplinary issues. This quality conduces to fondness, respect, esteem, harmony, and unity.

Furthermore, a mendicant wants to train, and praises taking up the training. …

Furthermore, a mendicant has few desires, and praises getting rid of desires. …

Furthermore, a mendicant is not irritable, and praises getting rid of anger. …

Furthermore, a mendicant doesn’t denigrate others, and praises getting rid of denigration. …

Furthermore, a mendicant isn’t devious, and praises getting rid of deviousness. …

Furthermore, a mendicant isn’t deceitful, and praises getting rid of deceitfulness. …

Furthermore, a mendicant pays attention to the teachings, and praises attending to the teachings. …

Furthermore, a mendicant is in retreat, and praises retreat. …

Furthermore, a mendicant is hospitable to their spiritual companions, and praises hospitality. This quality conduces to fondness, respect, esteem, harmony, and unity.

Even though a mendicant such as this might never wish: ‘If only my spiritual companions would honor, respect, esteem, and venerate me!’ Still they honor, respect, esteem, and venerate them. Why is that? Because their sensible spiritual companions see that they’ve given up those bad unskillful qualities.

Suppose a fine thoroughbred never wished: ‘If only the humans would put me in a thoroughbred’s place, feed me a thoroughbred’s food, and give me a thoroughbred’s grooming.’ Still the humans would put them in a thoroughbred’s place, feed them a thoroughbred’s food, and give them a thoroughbred’s grooming. Why is that? Because sensible humans see that they’ve given up their tricks, bluffs, ruses, and feints.

In the same way, even though a mendicant such as this might never wish: ‘If only my spiritual companions would honor, respect, esteem, and venerate me!’ Still they honor, respect, esteem, and venerate them. Why is that? Because their sensible spiritual companions see that they’ve given up those bad unskillful qualities.”

AN 10.88 An Abuser Akkosakasutta

“Mendicants, any mendicant who abuses and insults their spiritual companions, denouncing the noble ones, will, without a doubt, fall into one or other of these ten disasters. What ten? They don’t achieve the unachieved. What they have achieved falls away. They don’t refine their good qualities. They overestimate their good qualities. Or they lead the spiritual life dissatisfied. Or they commit a corrupt offense. Or they contract a severe illness. Or they go mad and lose their mind. They feel lost when they die. And when their body breaks up, after death, they are reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. Any mendicant who abuses and insults their spiritual companions, denouncing the noble ones, will, without a doubt, fall into one or other of these ten disasters.”

AN 10.89 With Kokālika Kokālikasutta

Then the mendicant Kokālika went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him, “Sir, Sāriputta and Moggallāna have corrupt wishes. They’ve fallen under the sway of corrupt wishes.”

“Don’t say that, Kokālika! Don’t say that, Kokālika! Have confidence in Sāriputta and Moggallāna, they’re good monks.”

For a second time Kokālika said to the Buddha, “Despite my faith and trust in the Buddha, Sāriputta and Moggallāna have corrupt wishes. They’ve fallen under the sway of corrupt wishes.”

“Don’t say that, Kokālika! Don’t say that, Kokālika! Have confidence in Sāriputta and Moggallāna, they’re good monks.”

For a third time Kokālika said to the Buddha, “Despite my faith and trust in the Buddha, Sāriputta and Moggallāna have corrupt wishes. They’ve fallen under the sway of corrupt wishes.”

“Don’t say that, Kokālika! Don’t say that, Kokālika! Have confidence in Sāriputta and Moggallāna, they’re good monks.”

Then Kokālika rose from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before leaving. Not long after he left his body erupted with boils the size of mustard seeds. The boils grew to the size of mung beans, then chickpeas, then jujube seeds, then jujubes, then myrobalans, then unripe wood-apples, then ripe wood-apples. Finally they burst open, and pus and blood oozed out. He just laid down on banana leaves like a poisoned fish.

Then Tudu the independent divinity went to Kokālika, and standing in the air he said to him, “Kokālika, have confidence in Sāriputta and Moggallāna, they’re good monks.”

“Who are you, reverend?”

“I am Tudu the independent divinity.”

“Didn’t the Buddha declare you a non-returner? So what then are you doing back here? See how far you have strayed!”

Then Tudu addressed Kokālika in verse:

“A person is born
with an axe in their mouth.
A fool cuts themselves with it
when they say bad words.

When you praise someone worthy of criticism,
or criticize someone worthy of praise,
you choose a losing hand with your own mouth:
you’ll never find happiness that way.

A losing hand at dice is a trivial thing,
if all you lose is your money
and all you own, even yourself.
What’s a really terrible hand
is to hate the holy ones.

For a hundred thousand times a hundred million
times five hundred and thirty-six times a thousand times ten million years
a slanderer of noble ones goes to hell,
having aimed bad words and thoughts at them.”

Then the mendicant Kokālika died of that illness. He was reborn in the Pink Lotus hell because of his resentment for Sāriputta and Moggallāna.

Then, late at night, the glorious divinity Sahampati, lighting up the entire Jeta’s Grove, went up to the Buddha, bowed, stood to one side, and said to him, “Sir, the mendicant Kokālika has passed away. He was reborn in the Pink Lotus hell because of his resentment for Sāriputta and Moggallāna.”

That is what the divinity Sahampati said. Then he bowed and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before vanishing right there.

Then, when the night had passed, the Buddha told the mendicants all that had happened.

When he said this, one of the mendicants said to the Buddha, “Sir, how long is the lifespan in the Pink Lotus hell?”

“It’s long, mendicant. It’s not easy to calculate how many years, how many hundreds or thousands or hundreds of thousands of years it lasts.”

“But sir, is it possible to give a simile?”

“It’s possible,” said the Buddha.

“Suppose there was a Kosalan load of twenty packs of sesame seed. And at the end of every hundred years someone would remove a single seed from it. By this means the Kosalan load of twenty packs of sesame seed would run out faster than a single lifetime in the Abbuda hell. Now, twenty lifetimes in the Abbuda hell equal one lifetime in the Nirabbuda hell. Twenty lifetimes in the Nirabbuda hell equal one lifetime in the Ababa hell. Twenty lifetimes in the Ababa hell equal one lifetime in the Aṭaṭa hell. Twenty lifetimes in the Aṭaṭa hell equal one lifetime in the Ahaha hell. Twenty lifetimes in the Ahaha hell equal one lifetime in the Yellow Lotus hell. Twenty lifetimes in the Yellow Lotus hell equal one lifetime in the Fragrant Water Lily hell. Twenty lifetimes in the Fragrant Water Lily hell equal one lifetime in the Blue Water Lily hell. Twenty lifetimes in the Blue Water Lily hell equal one lifetime in the White Lotus hell. Twenty lifetimes in the White Lotus hell equal one lifetime in the Pink Lotus hell. The mendicant Kokālika has been reborn in the Pink Lotus hell because of his resentment for Sāriputta and Moggallāna.”

That is what the Buddha said. Then the Holy One, the Teacher, went on to say:

“A person is born
with an axe in their mouth.
A fool cuts themselves with it
when they say bad words.

When you praise someone worthy of criticism,
or criticize someone worthy of praise,
you choose a losing hand with your own mouth:
you’ll never find happiness that way.

A losing hand at dice is a trivial thing,
if all you lose is your money
and all you own, even yourself.
What’s a really terrible hand
is to hate the holy ones.

For a hundred thousand times a hundred million,
times five hundred and thirty-six times a thousand times ten million years
a slanderer of noble ones goes to hell,
having aimed bad words and thoughts at them.”

AN 10.90 The Powers of One Who has Ended Defilements Khīṇāsavabalasutta

Then Venerable Sāriputta went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him:

“Sāriputta, how many powers does a mendicant who has ended the defilements have that qualify them to claim: ‘My defilements have ended.’”

“Sir, a mendicant who has ended the defilements has ten powers that qualify them to claim: ‘My defilements have ended.’ What ten? Firstly, a mendicant with defilements ended has clearly seen with right wisdom all conditions as truly impermanent. This is a power that a mendicant who has ended the defilements relies on to claim: ‘My defilements have ended.’

Furthermore, a mendicant with defilements ended has clearly seen with right wisdom that sensual pleasures are truly like a pit of glowing coals. This is a power that a mendicant who has ended the defilements relies on to claim: ‘My defilements have ended.’

Furthermore, the mind of a mendicant with defilements ended slants, slopes, and inclines to seclusion. They’re withdrawn, loving renunciation, and have totally eliminated defiling influences. This is a power that a mendicant who has ended the defilements relies on to claim: ‘My defilements have ended.’

Furthermore, a mendicant with defilements ended has well developed the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. This is a power that a mendicant who has ended the defilements relies on to claim: ‘My defilements have ended.’

Furthermore, a mendicant with defilements ended has well developed the four right efforts. … the four bases of psychic power … the five faculties … the five powers … the seven awakening factors … the noble eightfold path. This is a power that a mendicant who has ended the defilements relies on to claim: ‘My defilements have ended.’

A mendicant who has ended the defilements possesses these ten powers that qualify them to claim: ‘My defilements have ended.’”

The Chapter on Recollection

AN 11.11 With Mahānāma (1st) Paṭhamamahānāmasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sakyans, near Kapilavatthu in the Banyan Tree Monastery.

At that time several mendicants were making a robe for the Buddha, thinking that when his robe was finished and the three months of the rains residence had passed the Buddha would set out wandering.

Mahānāma the Sakyan heard about this. He went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, I have heard that several mendicants are making a robe for the Buddha, thinking that when his robe was finished and the three months of the rains residence had passed the Buddha would set out wandering. Now, we spend our life in various ways. Which of these should we practice?”

“Good, good, Mahānāma! It’s appropriate that gentlemen such as you come to me and ask: ‘We spend our life in various ways. Which of these should we practice?’ The faithful succeed, not the faithless. The energetic succeed, not the lazy. The mindful succeed, not the unmindful. Those with immersion succeed, not those without immersion. The wise succeed, not the witless.

When you’re grounded on these five things, go on to develop six further things.

Firstly, you should recollect the Realized One: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ When a noble disciple recollects the Realized One their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. At that time their mind is quite unswerving, based on the Realized One. A noble disciple whose mind is unswerving finds inspiration in the meaning and the teaching, and finds joy connected with the teaching. When they’re joyful, rapture springs up. When the mind is full of rapture, the body becomes tranquil. When the body is tranquil, they feel bliss. And when they’re blissful, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. This is called a noble disciple who lives in balance among people who are unbalanced, and lives untroubled among people who are troubled. They’ve entered the stream of the teaching and developed the recollection of the Buddha.

Furthermore, you should recollect the teaching: ‘The teaching is well explained by the Buddha—apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.’ When a noble disciple recollects the teaching their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. … This is called a noble disciple who lives in balance among people who are unbalanced, and lives untroubled among people who are troubled. They’ve entered the stream of the teaching and developed the recollection of the teaching.

Furthermore, you should recollect the Saṅgha: ‘The Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples is practicing the way that’s good, direct, systematic, and proper. It consists of the four pairs, the eight individual persons. This is the Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples that is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.’ When a noble disciple recollects the Saṅgha their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. … This is called a noble disciple who lives in balance among people who are unbalanced, and lives untroubled among people who are troubled. They’ve entered the stream of the teaching and developed the recollection of the Saṅgha.

Furthermore, you should recollect your own ethical conduct, which is intact, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion. When a noble disciple recollects their ethical precepts their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. … This is called a noble disciple who lives in balance among people who are unbalanced, and lives untroubled among people who are troubled. They’ve entered the stream of the teaching and developed the recollection of their ethical conduct.

Furthermore, you should recollect your own generosity: ‘I’m so fortunate, so very fortunate. Among people full of the stain of stinginess I live at home with heart rid of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share.’ When a noble disciple recollects their generosity their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. … This is called a noble disciple who lives in balance among people who are unbalanced, and lives untroubled among people who are troubled. They’ve entered the stream of the teaching and developed the recollection of generosity.

Furthermore, you should recollect the deities: ‘There are the gods of the four great kings, the gods of the thirty-three, the gods of Yama, the joyful gods, the gods who love to create, the gods who control what is created by others, the gods of the Divinity’s host, and gods even higher than these. When those deities passed away from here, they were reborn there because of their faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom. I, too, have the same kind of faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom.’ When a noble disciple recollects the faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom of both themselves and the deities their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. At that time their mind is quite unswerving, based on the deities. A noble disciple whose mind is unswerving finds inspiration in the meaning and the teaching, and finds joy connected with the teaching. When they’re joyful, rapture springs up. When the mind is full of rapture, the body becomes tranquil. When the body is tranquil, they feel bliss. And when they’re blissful, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. This is called a noble disciple who lives in balance among people who are unbalanced, and lives untroubled among people who are troubled. They’ve entered the stream of the teaching and developed the recollection of the deities.”

AN 11.12 With Mahānāma (2nd) Dutiyamahānāmasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sakyans, near Kapilavatthu in the Banyan Tree Monastery. Now at that time Mahānāma the Sakyan had recently recovered from an illness. At that time several mendicants were making a robe for the Buddha …

Mahānāma the Sakyan heard about this. He went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, I have heard that several mendicants are making a robe for the Buddha, thinking that when his robe was finished and the three months of the rains residence had passed the Buddha would set out wandering. Now, we spend our life in various ways. Which of these should we practice?”

“Good, good, Mahānāma! It’s appropriate that gentlemen such as you come to me and ask: ‘We spend our life in various ways. Which of these should we practice?’ The faithful succeed, not the faithless. The energetic succeed, not the lazy. The mindful succeed, not the unmindful. Those with immersion succeed, not those without immersion. The wise succeed, not the witless. When you’re grounded on these five things, go on to develop six further things.

Firstly, you should recollect the Realized One: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ When a noble disciple recollects the Realized One their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. At that time their mind is quite unswerving, based on the Realized One. A noble disciple whose mind is unswerving finds inspiration in the meaning and the teaching, and finds joy connected with the teaching. When they’re joyful, rapture springs up. When the mind is full of rapture, the body becomes tranquil. When the body is tranquil, they feel bliss. And when they’re blissful, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. You should develop this recollection of the Buddha while walking, standing, sitting, lying down, while working, and while at home with your children.

Furthermore, you should recollect the teaching … the Saṅgha … your own ethical conduct … your own generosity … the deities … When a noble disciple recollects the faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom of both themselves and the deities their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. At that time their mind is quite unswerving, based on the deities. A noble disciple whose mind is unswerving finds inspiration in the meaning and the teaching, and finds joy connected with the teaching. When they’re joyful, rapture springs up. When the mind is full of rapture, the body becomes tranquil. When the body is tranquil, they feel bliss. And when they’re blissful, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. You should develop this recollection of the deities while walking, standing, sitting, lying down, while working, and while at home with your children.”

AN 11.13 With Nandiya Nandiyasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sakyans, near Kapilavatthu in the Banyan Tree Monastery.

Now at that time the Buddha wanted to commence the rains residence at Sāvatthī.

Nandiya the Sakyan heard about this, and thought, “Why don’t I also commence the rains residence at Sāvatthī. There I can focus on my work and from time to time get to see the Buddha.”

So the Buddha commenced the rains residence in Sāvatthī, and so did Nandiya. There he focused on his work and from time to time got to see the Buddha.

At that time several mendicants were making a robe for the Buddha, thinking that when his robe was finished and the three months of the rains residence had passed the Buddha would set out wandering.

Nandiya the Sakyan heard about this. He went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, I have heard that several mendicants are making a robe for the Buddha, thinking that when his robe was finished and the three months of the rains residence had passed the Buddha would set out wandering. Now, we spend our life in various ways. Which of these should we practice?”

“Good, good, Nandiya! It’s appropriate that gentlemen such as you come to me and ask: ‘We spend our life in various ways. Which of these should we practice?’ The faithful succeed, not the faithless. The ethical succeed, not the unethical. The energetic succeed, not the lazy. The mindful succeed, not the unmindful. Those with immersion succeed, not those without immersion. The wise succeed, not the witless. When you’re grounded on these six things, go on to establish mindfulness on five further things internally.

Firstly, you should recollect the Realized One: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ In this way you should establish mindfulness internally based on the Realized One.

Furthermore, you should recollect the teaching: ‘The teaching is well explained by the Buddha—apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.’ In this way you should establish mindfulness internally based on the teaching.

Furthermore, you should recollect your good friends: ‘I’m fortunate, so very fortunate, to have good friends who advise and instruct me out of kindness and sympathy.’ In this way you should establish mindfulness internally based on good friends.

Furthermore, you should recollect your own generosity: ‘I’m so fortunate, so very fortunate. Among people full of the stain of stinginess I live at home with heart rid of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share.’ In this way you should establish mindfulness internally based on generosity.

Furthermore, you should recollect the deities: ‘There are deities who, surpassing the company of deities that consume edible food, are reborn in a certain host of mind-made deities. They don’t see in themselves anything more to do, or anything that needs improvement.’ An irreversibly freed mendicant doesn’t see in themselves anything more to do, or anything that needs improvement. In the same way, Nandiya, there are deities who, surpassing the company of deities that consume edible food, are reborn in a certain host of mind-made deities. They don’t see in themselves anything more to do, or anything that needs improvement. In this way you should establish mindfulness internally based on the deities.

A noble disciple who possesses these eleven qualities gives up bad, unskillful qualities and doesn’t cling to them. It’s like when a pot full of water is tipped over, so the water drains out and doesn’t go back in. Suppose there was an uncontrolled fire. It advances burning up dry woodlands and doesn’t turn back over what it has burned. In the same way, a noble disciple who possesses these eleven qualities gives up bad, unskillful qualities and doesn’t cling to them.”

AN 11.14 With Subhūti Subhūtisutta

And then Venerable Subhūti together with the mendicant Saddha went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him, “Subhūti, what is the name of this mendicant?”

“Sir, the name of this mendicant is Saddha. He is the son of the layman Sudatta, and has gone forth out of faith from the lay life to homelessness.”

“Well, I hope this mendicant Saddha exhibits the various evidences of faith.”

“Now is the time, Blessed One! Now is the time, Holy One! Let the Buddha speak on the evidence of faith. Now I will find out whether or not this mendicant Saddha exhibits the various evidences of faith.”

“Well then, Subhūti, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” Subhūti replied. The Buddha said this:

“Firstly, a mendicant is ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken. When a mendicant is ethical, this is evidence of faith.

Furthermore, a mendicant is very learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, rehearsing them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically. When a mendicant is learned, this is evidence of faith.

Furthermore, a mendicant has good friends, companions, and associates. When a mendicant has good friends, this is evidence of faith.

Furthermore, a mendicant is easy to admonish, having qualities that make them easy to admonish. They’re patient, and take instruction respectfully. When a mendicant is easy to admonish, this is evidence of faith.

Furthermore, a mendicant is deft and tireless in a diverse spectrum of duties for their spiritual companions, understanding how to go about things in order to complete and organize the work. When a mendicant is deft and tireless in a diverse spectrum of duties, this is evidence of faith.

Furthermore, a mendicant loves the teachings and is a delight to converse with, being full of joy in the teaching and training. When a mendicant loves the teachings, this is evidence of faith.

Furthermore, a mendicant lives with energy roused up for giving up unskillful qualities and embracing skillful qualities. They are strong, staunchly vigorous, not slacking off when it comes to developing skillful qualities. When a mendicant is energetic, this is evidence of faith.

Furthermore, a mendicant gets the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty. When a mendicant gets the four absorptions, this is evidence of faith.

Furthermore, a mendicant recollects many kinds of past lives. That is: one, two, three, four, five, ten, twenty, thirty, forty, fifty, a hundred, a thousand, a hundred thousand rebirths; many eons of the world contracting, many eons of the world expanding, many eons of the world contracting and expanding. They remember: ‘There, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn somewhere else. There, too, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn here.’ And so they recollect their many kinds of past lives, with features and details. When a mendicant recollects many kinds of past lives, this is evidence of faith.

Furthermore, with clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, a mendicant sees sentient beings passing away and being reborn—inferior and superior, beautiful and ugly, in a good place or a bad place. They understand how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds. ‘These dear beings did bad things by way of body, speech, and mind. They denounced the noble ones; they had wrong view; and they chose to act out of that wrong view. When their body broke up, after death, they were reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. These dear beings, however, did good things by way of body, speech, and mind. They never denounced the noble ones; they had right view; and they chose to act out of that right view. When their body broke up, after death, they were reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.’ And so, with clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, they see sentient beings passing away and being reborn—inferior and superior, beautiful and ugly, in a good place or a bad place. They understand how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds. When a mendicant has clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, this is evidence of faith.

Furthermore, a mendicant has realized the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and lives having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. When a mendicant has ended the defilements, this is evidence of faith.”

When he said this, Venerable Subhūti said to the Buddha:

“Sir, the various evidences of faith for a faithful person that the Buddha speaks of are found in this mendicant; he does exhibit them.

This mendicant is ethical …

This mendicant is learned …

This mendicant has good friends …

This mendicant is easy to admonish …

This mendicant is deft and tireless in a diverse spectrum of duties …

This mendicant loves the teachings …

This mendicant is energetic …

This mendicant gets the four absorptions …

This mendicant recollects their many kinds of past lives …

This mendicant has clairvoyance that is purified and surpasses the human …

This mendicant has ended the defilements …

The various evidences of faith for a faithful person that the Buddha speaks of are found in this mendicant; he does exhibit them.”

“Good, good, Subhūti! So, Subhūti, you should live together with this mendicant Saddha. And when you want to see the Realized One, you should come together with him.”

AN 11.15 The Benefits of Love Mettāsutta

“Mendicants, you can expect eleven benefits when the heart’s release by love has been cultivated, developed, and practiced, made a vehicle and a basis, kept up, consolidated, and properly implemented.

What eleven? You sleep at ease. You wake happily. You don’t have bad dreams. Humans love you. Non-humans love you. Deities protect you. You can’t be harmed by fire, poison, or blade. Your mind quickly enters immersion. Your face is clear and bright. You don’t feel lost when you die. If you don’t penetrate any higher, you’ll be reborn in a realm of divinity. You can expect eleven benefits when the heart’s release by love has been cultivated, developed, and practiced, made a vehicle and a basis, kept up, consolidated, and properly implemented.”

AN 11.16 The Wealthy Citizen Aṭṭhakanāgarasutta

At one time Venerable Ānanda was staying near Vesālī in the little village of Beluva.

Now at that time the householder Dasama, a wealthy citizen, had arrived at Pāṭaliputta on some business. He went to the Chicken Monastery, approached a certain mendicant, and said to him, “Sir, where is Venerable Ānanda now staying? For I want to see him.”

“Householder, Venerable Ānanda is staying near Vesālī in the little village of Beluva.”

Then the householder Dasama, having concluded his business there, went to the little village of Beluva in Vesālī to see Ānanda. He bowed, sat down to one side, and said to Ānanda:

“Honorable Ānanda, is there one thing that has been rightly explained by the Blessed One—who knows and sees, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha—practicing which a diligent, keen, and resolute mendicant’s mind is freed, their defilements are ended, and they arrive at the supreme sanctuary from the yoke?”

“There is, householder.”

“And what is that one thing?”

“Householder, it’s when a mendicant, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. Then they reflect: ‘Even this first absorption is produced by choices and intentions.’ They understand: ‘But whatever is produced by choices and intentions is impermanent and liable to cessation.’ Abiding in that they attain the ending of defilements. If they don’t attain the ending of defilements, with the ending of the five lower fetters they’re reborn spontaneously, because of their passion and love for that meditation. They are extinguished there, and are not liable to return from that world. This is one thing that has been rightly explained by the Blessed One—who knows and sees, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha—practicing which a diligent, keen, and resolute mendicant’s mind is freed, their defilements are ended, and they arrive at the supreme sanctuary from the yoke.

Furthermore, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, they enter and remain in the second absorption … third absorption … fourth absorption. Then they reflect: ‘Even this fourth absorption is produced by choices and intentions.’ They understand: ‘But whatever is produced by choices and intentions is impermanent and liable to cessation.’ Abiding in that they attain the ending of defilements. If they don’t attain the ending of defilements, with the ending of the five lower fetters they’re reborn spontaneously, because of their passion and love for that meditation. They are extinguished there, and are not liable to return from that world. This too is one thing that has been rightly explained by the Blessed One—who knows and sees, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha—practicing which a diligent, keen, and resolute mendicant’s mind is freed, their defilements are ended, and they arrive at the supreme sanctuary from the yoke.

Furthermore, a mendicant meditates spreading a heart full of love to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, they spread a heart full of love to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will. Then they reflect: ‘Even this heart’s release by love is produced by choices and intentions.’ They understand: ‘But whatever is produced by choices and intentions is impermanent and liable to cessation.’ Abiding in that they attain the ending of defilements. If they don’t attain the ending of defilements, with the ending of the five lower fetters they’re reborn spontaneously, because of their passion and love for that meditation. They are extinguished there, and are not liable to return from that world. This too is one thing that has been rightly explained by the Blessed One …

Furthermore, a mendicant meditates spreading a heart full of compassion … They meditate spreading a heart full of rejoicing … They meditate spreading a heart full of equanimity to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, they spread a heart full of equanimity to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will. Then they reflect: ‘Even this heart’s release by equanimity is produced by choices and intentions.’ They understand: ‘But whatever is produced by choices and intentions is impermanent and liable to cessation.’ Abiding in that they attain the ending of defilements. If they don’t attain the ending of defilements, with the ending of the five lower fetters they’re reborn spontaneously, because of their passion and love for that meditation. They are extinguished there, and are not liable to return from that world. This too is one thing that has been rightly explained by the Blessed One …

Furthermore, a mendicant, going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that ‘space is infinite’, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite space. Then they reflect: ‘Even this attainment of the dimension of infinite space is produced by choices and intentions.’ They understand: ‘But whatever is produced by choices and intentions is impermanent and liable to cessation.’ Abiding in that they attain the ending of defilements. If they don’t attain the ending of defilements, with the ending of the five lower fetters they’re reborn spontaneously, because of their passion and love for that meditation. They are extinguished there, and are not liable to return from that world. This too is one thing that has been rightly explained by the Blessed One …

Furthermore, a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite space, aware that ‘consciousness is infinite’, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite consciousness. … Going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, they enter and remain in the dimension of nothingness. … Then they reflect: ‘Even this attainment of the dimension of nothingness is produced by choices and intentions.’ They understand: ‘But whatever is produced by choices and intentions is impermanent and liable to cessation.’ Abiding in that they attain the ending of defilements. If they don’t attain the ending of defilements, with the ending of the five lower fetters they’re reborn spontaneously, because of their passion and love for that meditation. They are extinguished there, and are not liable to return from that world. This too is one thing that has been rightly explained by the Blessed One—who knows and sees, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha—practicing which a diligent, keen, and resolute mendicant’s mind is freed, their defilements are ended, and they reach the supreme sanctuary from the yoke.”

When he said this, the householder Dasama said to Venerable Ānanda:

“Honorable Ānanda, suppose a person was looking for the entrance to a treasure trove. And all at once they’d come across eleven entrances! In the same way, I was searching for the door to freedom from death. And all at once I found eleven doors to freedom from death for cultivation. Suppose a person had a house with eleven doors. If the house caught fire they’d be able to flee to safety through any one of those doors. In the same way, I’m able to flee to safety through any one of these eleven doors to freedom from death. Sir, those of other religions will seek a fee for the tutor. Why shouldn’t I make an offering to Venerable Ānanda?”

Then the householder Dasama, having assembled the Saṅgha from Vesālī and Pāṭaliputta, served and satisfied them with his own hands with delicious fresh and cooked foods. He clothed each and every mendicant in a pair of garments, with a set of three robes for Ānanda. And he had a dwelling worth five hundred built for Ānanda.

AN 11.17 The Cowherd Gopālasutta

“Mendicants, a cowherd with eleven factors can’t maintain and expand a herd of cattle. What eleven? It’s when a cowherd doesn’t know form, is unskilled in characteristics, doesn’t pick out flies’ eggs, doesn’t dress wounds, doesn’t spread smoke, doesn’t know the ford, doesn’t know satisfaction, doesn’t know the trail, is not skilled in pastures, milks dry, and doesn’t show extra respect to the bulls who are fathers and captains of the herd. A cowherd with these eleven factors can’t maintain and expand a herd of cattle.

In the same way, a mendicant with eleven qualities can’t achieve growth, improvement, or maturity in this teaching and training. What eleven? It’s when a mendicant doesn’t know form, is unskilled in characteristics, doesn’t pick out flies’ eggs, doesn’t dress wounds, doesn’t spread smoke, doesn’t know the ford, doesn’t know satisfaction, doesn’t know the trail, is not skilled in pastures, milks dry, and doesn’t show extra respect to senior mendicants of long standing, long gone forth, fathers and leaders of the Saṅgha.

And how does a mendicant not know form? It’s when a mendicant doesn’t truly understand that all form is the four principal states, or form derived from the four principal states. That’s how a mendicant doesn’t know form.

And how is a mendicant not skilled in characteristics? It’s when a mendicant doesn’t understand that a fool is characterized by their deeds, and an astute person is characterized by their deeds. That’s how a mendicant isn’t skilled in characteristics.

And how does a mendicant not pick out flies’ eggs? It’s when a mendicant tolerates a sensual, malicious, or cruel thought that has arisen. They don’t give it up, dispel it, eliminate it, and obliterate it. They tolerate any bad, unskillful qualities that have arisen. They don’t give them up, dispel them, eliminate them, and obliterate them. That’s how a mendicant doesn’t pick out flies’ eggs.

And how does a mendicant not dress wounds? When a mendicant sees a sight with their eyes, they get caught up in the features and details. Since the faculty of sight is left unrestrained, bad unskillful qualities of covetousness and displeasure become overwhelming. They don’t practice restraint, they don’t protect the faculty of sight, and they don’t achieve its restraint. When they hear a sound with their ears … When they smell an odor with their nose … When they taste a flavor with their tongue … When they feel a touch with their body … When they know an idea with their mind, they get caught up in the features and details. Since the faculty of the mind is left unrestrained, bad unskillful qualities of covetousness and displeasure become overwhelming. They don’t practice restraint, they don’t protect the faculty of the mind, and they don’t achieve its restraint. That’s how a mendicant doesn’t dress wounds.

And how does a mendicant not spread smoke? It’s when a mendicant doesn’t teach others the Dhamma in detail as they learned and memorized it. That’s how a mendicant doesn’t spread smoke.

And how does a mendicant not know the ford? It’s when a mendicant doesn’t from time to time go up to those mendicants who are very learned—inheritors of the heritage, who have memorized the teachings, the monastic law, and the outlines—and ask them questions: ‘Why, sir, does it say this? What does that mean?’ Those venerables don’t reveal what is hidden, clarify what is unclear, and dispel doubt regarding the many doubtful matters. That’s how a mendicant doesn’t know the ford.

And how does a mendicant not know satisfaction? It’s when a mendicant, when the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One are being taught, finds no inspiration in the meaning and the teaching, and finds no joy connected with the teaching. That’s how a mendicant doesn’t know satisfaction.

And how does a mendicant not know the trail? It’s when a mendicant doesn’t truly understand the noble eightfold path. That’s how a mendicant doesn’t know the trail.

And how is a mendicant not skilled in pastures? It’s when a mendicant doesn’t truly understand the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. That’s how a mendicant is not skilled in pastures.

And how does a mendicant milk dry? It’s when a mendicant is invited by a householder to accept robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. But they don’t know moderation in accepting. That’s how a mendicant milks dry.

And how does a mendicant not show extra respect to senior mendicants of long standing, long gone forth, fathers and leaders of the Saṅgha? It’s when a mendicant doesn’t consistently treat senior mendicants of long standing, long gone forth, fathers and leaders of the Saṅgha with kindness by way of body, speech, and mind, both in public and in private. That’s how a mendicant doesn’t show extra respect to senior mendicants of long standing, long gone forth, fathers and leaders of the Saṅgha.

A mendicant with these eleven qualities can’t achieve growth, improvement, or maturity in this teaching and training.

A cowherd with eleven factors can maintain and expand a herd of cattle. What eleven? It’s when a cowherd knows form, is skilled in characteristics, picks out flies’ eggs, dresses wounds, spreads smoke, knows the ford, knows satisfaction, knows the trail, is skilled in pastures, doesn’t milk dry, and shows extra respect to the bulls who are fathers and captains of the herd. A cowherd with these eleven factors can maintain and expand a herd of cattle.

In the same way, a mendicant with eleven qualities can achieve growth, improvement, and maturity in this teaching and training. What eleven? It’s when a mendicant knows form, is skilled in characteristics, picks out flies’ eggs, dresses wounds, spreads smoke, knows the ford, knows satisfaction, knows the trail, is skilled in pastures, doesn’t milk dry, and shows extra respect to senior mendicants of long standing, long gone forth, fathers and leaders of the Saṅgha.

And how does a mendicant know form? It’s when a mendicant truly understands that all form is the four principal states, or form derived from the four principal states. That’s how a mendicant knows form.

And how is a mendicant skilled in characteristics? It’s when a mendicant understands that a fool is characterized by their deeds, and an astute person is characterized by their deeds. That’s how a mendicant is skilled in characteristics.

And how does a mendicant pick out flies’ eggs? It’s when a mendicant doesn’t tolerate a sensual, malicious, or cruel thought that has arisen, but gives it up, dispels it, eliminates it, and exterminates it. They don’t tolerate any bad, unskillful qualities that have arisen, but give them up, dispel them, eliminate them, and obliterate them. That’s how a mendicant picks out flies’ eggs.

And how does a mendicant dress wounds? When a mendicant sees a sight with their eyes, they don’t get caught up in the features and details. If the faculty of sight were left unrestrained, bad unskillful qualities of covetousness and displeasure would become overwhelming. For this reason, they practice restraint, protecting the faculty of sight, and achieving its restraint. When they hear a sound with their ears … When they smell an odor with their nose … When they taste a flavor with their tongue … When they feel a touch with their body … When they know an idea with their mind, they don’t get caught up in the features and details. If the faculty of mind were left unrestrained, bad unskillful qualities of covetousness and displeasure would become overwhelming. For this reason, they practice restraint, protecting the faculty of mind, and achieving its restraint. That’s how a mendicant dresses wounds.

And how does a mendicant spread smoke? It’s when a mendicant teaches others the Dhamma in detail as they learned and memorized it. That’s how a mendicant spreads smoke.

And how does a mendicant know the ford? It’s when from time to time a mendicant goes up to those mendicants who are very learned—inheritors of the heritage, who have memorized the teachings, the monastic law, and the outlines—and asks them questions: ‘Why, sir, does it say this? What does that mean?’ Those venerables reveal what is hidden, clarify what is unclear, and dispel doubt regarding the many doubtful matters. That’s how a mendicant knows the ford.

And how does a mendicant know satisfaction? It’s when a mendicant, when the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One are being taught, finds inspiration in the meaning and the teaching, and finds joy connected with the teaching. That’s how a mendicant knows satisfaction.

And how does a mendicant know the trail? It’s when a mendicant truly understands the noble eightfold path. That’s how a mendicant knows the trail.

And how is a mendicant skilled in pastures? It’s when a mendicant truly understands the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. That’s how a mendicant is skilled in pastures.

And how does a mendicant not milk dry? It’s when a mendicant is invited by a householder to accept robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. And that mendicant knows moderation in accepting. That’s how a mendicant doesn’t milk dry.

And how does a mendicant show extra respect to senior mendicants of long standing, long gone forth, fathers and leaders of the Saṅgha? It’s when a mendicant consistently treats senior mendicants of long standing, long gone forth, fathers and leaders of the Saṅgha with kindness by way of body, speech, and mind, both in public and in private. That’s how a mendicant shows extra respect to senior mendicants of long standing, long gone forth, fathers and leaders of the Saṅgha.

A mendicant with these eleven qualities can achieve growth, improvement, or maturity in this teaching and training.”

AN 11.18 Immersion (1st) Paṭhamasamādhisutta

And then several mendicants went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Could it be, sir, that a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this? They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

“It could be, mendicants.”

“But how could this be?”

“It’s when a mendicant perceives: ‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment.’ That’s how a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this. They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

AN 11.19 Immersion (2nd) Dutiyasamādhisutta

There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Could it be, mendicants, that a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this? They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. He is our guide and our refuge. Sir, may the Buddha himself please clarify the meaning of this. The mendicants will listen and remember it.”

“Well then, mendicants, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“A mendicant could gain such a state of immersion.”

“But how could this be?”

“It’s when a mendicant perceives: ‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment.’ That’s how a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this. They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

AN 11.20 Immersion (3rd) Tatiyasamādhisutta

And then several mendicants went up to Venerable Sāriputta, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, they sat down to one side and said to him:

“Could it be, reverend, that a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this? They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

“It could be, reverends.”

“But how could this be?”

“It’s when a mendicant perceives: ‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment.’ That’s how a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this. They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

AN 11.21 Immersion (4th) Catutthasamādhisutta

There Sāriputta addressed the mendicants:

“Could it be, reverends, that a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this? They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

“Reverend, we would travel a long way to learn the meaning of this statement in the presence of Venerable Sāriputta. May Venerable Sāriputta himself please clarify the meaning of this. The mendicants will listen and remember it.”

“Then listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, reverend,” they replied. Sāriputta said this:

“A mendicant could gain such a state of immersion.”

“But how could this be?”

“It’s when a mendicant perceives: ‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment.’ That’s how a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this. They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

The First Fifty

The Chapter on Dependence

AN 11.1 What’s the Goal? Kimatthiyasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery.

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, what is the goal and benefit of skillful ethics?”

“Ānanda, having no regrets is the goal and benefit of skillful ethics.”

“But what is the goal and benefit of having no regrets?”

“Joy is the goal and benefit of having no regrets.”

“But what is the goal and benefit of joy?”

“Rapture …”

“But what is the goal and benefit of rapture?”

“Tranquility …”

“But what is the goal and benefit of tranquility?”

“Bliss …”

“But what is the goal and benefit of bliss?”

“Immersion …”

“But what is the goal and benefit of immersion?”

“Truly knowing and seeing …”

“But what is the goal and benefit of truly knowing and seeing?”

“Disillusionment …”

“But what is the goal and benefit of disillusionment?”

“Dispassion …”

“But what is the goal and benefit of dispassion?”

“Knowledge and vision of freedom is the goal and benefit of dispassion.

So, Ānanda, the goal and benefit of skillful ethics is not having regrets. Joy is the goal and benefit of not having regrets. Rapture is the goal and benefit of joy. Tranquility is the goal and benefit of rapture. Bliss is the goal and benefit of tranquility. Immersion is the goal and benefit of bliss. Truly knowing and seeing is the goal and benefit of immersion. Disillusionment is the goal and benefit of truly knowing and seeing. Dispassion is the goal and benefit of disillusionment. And knowledge and vision of freedom is the goal and benefit of dispassion. So, Ānanda, skillful ethics progressively lead up to the highest.”

AN 11.2 Making a Wish Cetanākaraṇīyasutta

“Mendicants, an ethical person, who has fulfilled ethical conduct, need not make a wish: ‘May I have no regrets!’ It’s only natural that an ethical person has no regrets.

When you have no regrets you need not make a wish: ‘May I feel joy!’ It’s only natural that joy springs up when you have no regrets.

When you feel joy you need not make a wish: ‘May I experience rapture!’ It’s only natural that rapture arises when you’re joyful.

When your mind is full of rapture you need not make a wish: ‘May my body become tranquil!’ It’s only natural that your body becomes tranquil when your mind is full of rapture.

When your body is tranquil you need not make a wish: ‘May I feel bliss!’ It’s only natural to feel bliss when your body is tranquil.

When you feel bliss you need not make a wish: ‘May my mind be immersed in samādhi!’ It’s only natural for the mind to become immersed in samādhi when you feel bliss.

When your mind is immersed in samādhi you need not make a wish: ‘May I truly know and see!’ It’s only natural to truly know and see when your mind is immersed in samādhi.

When you truly know and see you need not make a wish: ‘May I grow disillusioned!’ It’s only natural to grow disillusioned when you truly know and see.

When you’re disillusioned you need not make a wish: ‘May I become dispassionate!’ It’s only natural to grow dispassionate when you’re disillusioned.

When you’re dispassionate you need not make a wish: ‘May I realize the knowledge and vision of freedom!’ It’s only natural to realize the knowledge and vision of freedom when you’re dispassionate.

And so, mendicants, the knowledge and vision of freedom is the goal and benefit of dispassion. Dispassion is the goal and benefit of disillusionment. Disillusionment is the goal and benefit of truly knowing and seeing. Truly knowing and seeing is the goal and benefit of immersion. Immersion is the goal and benefit of bliss. Bliss is the goal and benefit of tranquility. Tranquility is the goal and benefit of rapture. Rapture is the goal and benefit of joy. Joy is the goal and benefit of not having regrets. Not having regrets is the goal and benefit of skillful ethics. And so, mendicants, good qualities flow on and fill up from one to the other, for going from the near shore to the far shore.”

AN 11.3 Vital Conditions (1st) Paṭhamaupanisāsutta

“Mendicants, an unethical person, who lacks ethics, has destroyed a vital condition for having no regrets. When there are regrets, one who has regrets has destroyed a vital condition for joy. When there is no joy, one who lacks joy has destroyed a vital condition for rapture. When there is no rapture, one who lacks rapture has destroyed a vital condition for tranquility. When there is no tranquility, one who lacks tranquility has destroyed a vital condition for bliss. When there is no bliss, one who lacks bliss has destroyed a vital condition for right immersion. When there is no right immersion, one who lacks right immersion has destroyed a vital condition for true knowledge and vision. When there is no true knowledge and vision, one who lacks true knowledge and vision has destroyed a vital condition for disillusionment. When there is no disillusionment, one who lacks disillusionment has destroyed a vital condition for dispassion. When there is no dispassion, one who lacks dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

Suppose there was a tree that lacked branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would not grow to fullness.

In the same way, an unethical person, who lacks ethics, has destroyed a vital condition for having no regrets. When there are regrets, one who has regrets has destroyed a vital condition for joy. … When there is no dispassion, one who lacks dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

An ethical person, who has fulfilled ethics, has fulfilled a vital condition for not having regrets. When there are no regrets, one who has no regrets has fulfilled a vital condition for joy. When there is joy, one who has fulfilled joy has fulfilled a vital condition for rapture. When there is rapture, one who has fulfilled rapture has fulfilled a vital condition for tranquility. When there is tranquility, one who has fulfilled tranquility has fulfilled a vital condition for bliss. When there is bliss, one who has fulfilled bliss has fulfilled a vital condition for right immersion. When there is right immersion, one who has fulfilled right immersion has fulfilled a vital condition for true knowledge and vision. When there is true knowledge and vision, one who has fulfilled true knowledge and vision has fulfilled a vital condition for disillusionment. When there is disillusionment, one who has fulfilled disillusionment has fulfilled a vital condition for dispassion. When there is dispassion, one who has fulfilled dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

Suppose there was a tree that was complete with branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would grow to fullness.

In the same way, an ethical person, who has fulfilled ethics, has fulfilled a vital condition for not having regrets. When there are no regrets, one who has no regrets has fulfilled a vital condition for joy. … When there is dispassion, one who has fulfilled dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.”

AN 11.4 Vital Conditions (2nd) Dutiyaupanisāsutta

There Venerable Sāriputta addressed the mendicants: “Reverends, mendicants!”

“Reverend,” they replied. Sāriputta said this:

“An unethical person, who lacks ethics, has destroyed a vital condition for not having regrets. When there are regrets, one who has regrets has destroyed a vital condition for joy. When there is no joy, one who lacks joy has destroyed a vital condition for rapture. When there is no rapture, one who lacks rapture has destroyed a vital condition for tranquility. When there is no tranquility, one who lacks tranquility has destroyed a vital condition for bliss. When there is no bliss, one who lacks bliss has destroyed a vital condition for right immersion. When there is no right immersion, one who lacks right immersion has destroyed a vital condition for true knowledge and vision. When there is no true knowledge and vision, one who lacks true knowledge and vision has destroyed a vital condition for disillusionment. When there is no disillusionment, one who lacks disillusionment has destroyed a vital condition for dispassion. When there is no dispassion, one who lacks dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

Suppose there was a tree that lacked branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would not grow to fullness.

In the same way, an unethical person, who lacks ethics, has destroyed a vital condition for having no regrets. When there are regrets, one who has regrets has destroyed a vital condition for joy. … When there is no dispassion, one who lacks dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

An ethical person, who has fulfilled ethics, has fulfilled a vital condition for not having regrets. When there are no regrets, one who has no regrets has fulfilled a vital condition for joy. When there is joy, one who has fulfilled joy has fulfilled a vital condition for rapture. When there is rapture, one who has fulfilled rapture has fulfilled a vital condition for tranquility. When there is tranquility, one who has fulfilled tranquility has fulfilled a vital condition for bliss. When there is bliss, one who has fulfilled bliss has fulfilled a vital condition for right immersion. When there is right immersion, one who has fulfilled right immersion has fulfilled a vital condition for true knowledge and vision. When there is true knowledge and vision, one who has fulfilled true knowledge and vision has fulfilled a vital condition for disillusionment. When there is disillusionment, one who has fulfilled disillusionment has fulfilled a vital condition for dispassion. When there is dispassion, one who has fulfilled dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

Suppose there was a tree that was complete with branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would grow to fullness.

In the same way, an ethical person, who has fulfilled ethics, has fulfilled a vital condition for not having regrets. When there are no regrets, one who has no regrets has fulfilled a vital condition for joy. … When there is dispassion, one who has fulfilled dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.”

AN 11.5 Vital Conditions (3rd) Tatiyaupanisāsutta

There Venerable Ānanda addressed the mendicants …

“An unethical person, who lacks ethics, has destroyed a vital condition for not having regrets. When there are regrets, one who has regrets has destroyed a vital condition for joy. When there is no joy, one who lacks joy has destroyed a vital condition for rapture. When there is no rapture, one who lacks rapture has destroyed a vital condition for tranquility. When there is no tranquility, one who lacks tranquility has destroyed a vital condition for bliss. When there is no bliss, one who lacks bliss has destroyed a vital condition for right immersion. When there is no right immersion, one who lacks right immersion has destroyed a vital condition for true knowledge and vision. When there is no true knowledge and vision, one who lacks true knowledge and vision has destroyed a vital condition for disillusionment. When there is no disillusionment, one who lacks disillusionment has destroyed a vital condition for dispassion. When there is no dispassion, one who lacks dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

Suppose there was a tree that lacked branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would not grow to fullness.

In the same way, an unethical person, who lacks ethics, has destroyed a vital condition for having no regrets. When there are regrets, one who has regrets has destroyed a vital condition for joy. … When there is no dispassion, one who lacks dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

An ethical person, who has fulfilled ethics, has fulfilled a vital condition for not having regrets. When there are no regrets, one who has no regrets has fulfilled a vital condition for joy. When there is joy, one who has fulfilled joy has fulfilled a vital condition for rapture. When there is rapture, one who has fulfilled rapture has fulfilled a vital condition for tranquility. When there is tranquility, one who has fulfilled tranquility has fulfilled a vital condition for bliss. When there is bliss, one who has fulfilled bliss has fulfilled a vital condition for right immersion. When there is right immersion, one who has fulfilled right immersion has fulfilled a vital condition for true knowledge and vision. When there is true knowledge and vision, one who has fulfilled true knowledge and vision has fulfilled a vital condition for disillusionment. When there is disillusionment, one who has fulfilled disillusionment has fulfilled a vital condition for dispassion. When there is dispassion, one who has fulfilled dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

Suppose there was a tree that was complete with branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would grow to fullness.

In the same way, an ethical person, who has fulfilled ethics, has fulfilled a vital condition for not having regrets. When there are no regrets, one who has no regrets has fulfilled a vital condition for joy. … When there is dispassion, one who has fulfilled dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.”

AN 11.6 Disasters Byasanasutta

“Mendicants, any mendicant who abuses and insults their spiritual companions, denouncing the noble ones, will, without a doubt, fall into one or other of these eleven disasters. What eleven?

They don’t achieve the unachieved. What they have achieved falls away. They don’t refine their good qualities. They overestimate their good qualities. Or they lead the spiritual life dissatisfied. Or they commit a corrupt offense. Or they resign the training and return to a lesser life. Or they contract a severe illness. Or they go mad or lose their mind. They feel lost when they die. And when their body breaks up, after death, they are reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.

Any mendicant who abuses and insults their spiritual companions, denouncing the noble ones, will, without a doubt, fall into one or other of these eleven disasters.

Any mendicant who does not abuse and insult their spiritual companions, denouncing the noble ones, will, without a doubt, not fall into one or other of these eleven disasters. What eleven?

They don’t achieve the unachieved. What they have achieved falls away. They don’t refine their good qualities. They overestimate their good qualities. Or they lead the spiritual life dissatisfied. Or they commit one of the corrupt offenses. Or they resign the training and return to a lesser life. Or they contract a severe illness. Or they go mad or lose their mind. They feel lost when they die. And when their body breaks up, after death, they are reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.

Any mendicant who does not abuse and insult their spiritual companions, denouncing the noble ones, will, without a doubt, not fall into one or other of these eleven disasters.”

AN 11.7 Percipient Saññāsutta

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Could it be, sir, that a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this? They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

“It could be, Ānanda, that a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this. They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

“But how could this be, sir?”

“Ānanda, it’s when a mendicant perceives: ‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment.’

That’s how a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this. They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t perceive the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They wouldn’t perceive this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

And then Ānanda approved and agreed with what the Buddha said. He got up from his seat, bowed and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right. Then he went up to Venerable Sāriputta, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to Sāriputta:

“Could it be, reverend Sāriputta, that a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this? They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth … And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

“It could be, Reverend Ānanda.”

“But how could this be?”

“Ānanda, it’s when a mendicant perceives: ‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment.’ That’s how a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this. They wouldn’t perceive earth in earth … And they wouldn’t perceive what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. And yet they would still perceive.”

“It’s incredible, it’s amazing! How the meaning and the phrasing of the Teacher and the disciple fit together and agree without conflict when it comes to the chief matter! Just now I went to the Buddha and asked him about this matter. And the Buddha explained it to me in this manner, with these words and phrases, just like Venerable Sāriputta. It’s incredible, it’s amazing! How the meaning and the phrasing of the Teacher and the disciple fit together and agree without conflict when it comes to the chief matter!”

AN 11.8 Focus Manasikārasutta

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Could it be, sir, that a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this. They wouldn’t focus on the eye or sights, ear or sounds, nose or smells, tongue or tastes, or body or touches. They wouldn’t focus on earth in earth, water in water, fire in fire, or air in air. And they wouldn’t focus on the dimension of infinite space in the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness in the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness in the dimension of nothingness, or the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They wouldn’t focus on this world in this world, or the other world in the other world. And they wouldn’t focus on what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. Yet they would focus?”

“It could be, Ānanda.”

“But how could this be?”

“Ānanda, it’s when a mendicant focuses thus: ‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment.’

That’s how a mendicant might gain a state of immersion like this. They wouldn’t focus on the eye or sights, ear or sounds, nose or smells, tongue or tastes, or body or touches. … And they wouldn’t focus on what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. Yet they would focus.”

AN 11.9 With Sandha Saddhasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying at Ñātika in the brick house.

Then Venerable Sandha went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him:

“Sandha, meditate like a thoroughbred, not like a wild colt.

And how does a wild colt meditate? A wild colt, tied up by the feeding trough, meditates: ‘Fodder, fodder!’ Why is that? Because it doesn’t occur to the wild colt tied up by the feeding trough: ‘What task will the horse trainer have me do today? How should I respond?’ Tied up by the feeding trough they just meditate: ‘Fodder, fodder!’

In the same way, take a certain wild person who has gone to the forest, the root of a tree, or an empty hut. Their heart is overcome and mired in sensual desire, and they don’t truly understand the escape from sensual desire that has arisen. Harboring sensual desire within they meditate and concentrate and contemplate and ruminate. Their heart is overcome by ill will … dullness and drowsiness … restlessness and remorse … doubt … Harboring doubt within they meditate and concentrate and contemplate and ruminate. They meditate dependent on earth, water, fire, and air. They meditate dependent on the dimension of infinite space, infinite consciousness, nothingness, or neither perception nor non-perception. They meditate dependent on this world or the other world. They meditate dependent on what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. That’s how a wild colt meditates.

And how does a thoroughbred meditate? A fine thoroughbred, tied up by the feeding trough, doesn’t meditate: ‘Fodder, fodder!’ Why is that? Because it occurs to the fine thoroughbred tied up by the feeding trough: ‘What task will the horse trainer have me do today? How should I respond?’ Tied up by the feeding trough they don’t meditate: ‘Fodder, fodder!’ For that fine thoroughbred regards the use of the goad as a debt, a bond, a loss, a misfortune.

In the same way, take a certain fine thoroughbred person who has gone to the forest, the root of a tree, or an empty hut. Their heart is not overcome and mired in sensual desire, and they truly understand the escape from sensual desire that has arisen. Their heart is not overcome by ill will … dullness and drowsiness … restlessness and remorse … doubt … They don’t meditate dependent on earth, water, fire, and air. They don’t meditate dependent on the dimension of infinite space, infinite consciousness, nothingness, or neither perception nor non-perception. They don’t meditate dependent on this world or the other world. They don’t meditate dependent on what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. Yet they do meditate.

When a fine thoroughbred meditates like this, the gods together with Indra, the Divinity, and the Progenitor worship them from afar:

‘Homage to you, O thoroughbred!
Homage to you, supreme among men!
We don’t understand
the basis of your absorption.’”

When he said this, Venerable Sandha asked the Buddha, “But sir, how does that fine thoroughbred meditate?”

“Sandha, for a fine thoroughbred person, the perception of earth has vanished in relation to earth. The perception of water … fire … air has vanished in relation to air. The perception of the dimension of infinite space has vanished in relation to the dimension of infinite space. The perception of the dimension of infinite consciousness … nothingness … neither perception nor non-perception has vanished in relation to the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. The perception of this world has vanished in relation to this world. The perception of the other world has vanished in relation to the other world. And the perception of what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind has vanished. That’s how that fine thoroughbred person doesn’t meditate dependent on earth, water, fire, and air. They don’t meditate dependent on the dimension of infinite space, infinite consciousness, nothingness, or neither perception nor non-perception. They don’t meditate dependent on this world or the other world. They don’t meditate dependent on what is seen, heard, thought, known, attained, sought, or explored by the mind. Yet they do meditate.

When a fine thoroughbred person meditates like this, the gods together with Indra, the Divinity, and the Progenitor worship them from afar:

‘Homage to you, O thoroughbred!
Homage to you, supreme among men!
We don’t understand
the basis of your absorption.’”

AN 11.10 At the Peacocks’ Feeding Ground Moranivāpasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha, at the monastery for the wanderers in the peacocks’ feeding ground. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, a mendicant with three qualities has reached the ultimate end, the ultimate sanctuary from the yoke, the ultimate spiritual life, the ultimate goal. They are best among gods and humans. What three? The entire spectrum of an adept’s ethics, immersion, and wisdom. A mendicant with these three qualities has reached the ultimate end, the ultimate sanctuary from the yoke, the ultimate spiritual life, the ultimate goal. They are best among gods and humans.

A mendicant with another three qualities has reached the ultimate end, the ultimate sanctuary from the yoke, the ultimate spiritual life, the ultimate goal. They are best among gods and humans. What three? A demonstration of psychic power, a demonstration of revealing, and a demonstration of instruction. A mendicant with these three qualities has reached the ultimate end, the ultimate sanctuary from the yoke, the ultimate spiritual life, the ultimate goal. They are best among gods and humans.

A mendicant with another three qualities has reached the ultimate end, the ultimate sanctuary from the yoke, the ultimate spiritual life, the ultimate goal. They are best among gods and humans. What three? Right view, right knowledge, and right freedom. A mendicant with these three qualities has reached the ultimate end, the ultimate sanctuary from the yoke, the ultimate spiritual life, the ultimate goal. They are best among gods and humans.

A mendicant who has two qualities has reached the ultimate end, the ultimate sanctuary from the yoke, the ultimate spiritual life, the ultimate goal. They are best among gods and humans. What two? Knowledge and conduct. A mendicant with these two qualities has reached the ultimate end, the ultimate sanctuary from the yoke, the ultimate spiritual life, the ultimate goal. They are best among gods and humans. The divinity Sanaṅkumāra also spoke this verse:

‘The aristocrat is best among people
who take clan as the standard.
But one accomplished in knowledge and conduct
is first among gods and humans.’

Now, that verse spoken by the divinity Sanaṅkumāra is well spoken, not poorly spoken. It’s beneficial, not pointless, and I agree with it. I also say:

‘The aristocrat is best among people
who take clan as the standard.
But one accomplished in knowledge and conduct
is first among gods and humans.’”

Abbreviated Texts Beginning With Greed

AN 11.982 Untitled Discourse on Greed ~

“For insight into greed, eleven things should be developed. What eleven? The first, second, third, and fourth absorptions; the heart’s releases by love, compassion, rejoicing, and equanimity; the dimensions of infinite space, infinite consciousness, and nothingness. For insight into greed, these eleven things should be developed.”

AN 11.983–991 Untitled Discourses on Greed ~

“For the complete understanding of greed … complete ending … giving up … ending … vanishing … fading away … cessation … giving away … letting go … these eleven things should be developed.”

AN 11.992–1151 Untitled Discourses on Hate, Etc. ~

“Of hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … jealousy … stinginess … deceitfulness … deviousness … obstinacy … aggression … conceit … arrogance … vanity … for insight into negligence … complete understanding … complete ending … giving up … ending … vanishing … fading away … cessation … giving away … For the letting go of negligence, these eleven things should be developed.”

That is what the Buddha said. Satisfied, the mendicants approved what the Buddha said.

The Book of the Elevens is finished.

The Numbered Discourses are complete.

The Chapter on Similarity

AN 11.22–29 Untitled Discourses on the Eye ~

“Mendicants, a cowherd with eleven factors can’t maintain and expand a herd of cattle. What eleven? It’s when a cowherd doesn’t know form, is unskilled in characteristics, doesn’t pick out flies’ eggs, doesn’t dress wounds, doesn’t spread smoke, doesn’t know the ford, doesn’t know satisfaction, doesn’t know the trail, is not skilled in pastures, milks dry, and doesn’t show extra respect to the bulls who are fathers and captains of the herd. A cowherd with these eleven factors can’t maintain and expand a herd of cattle.

In the same way, a mendicant with eleven qualities can’t meditate observing impermanence in the eye …

… meditate observing suffering …

… not-self …

… ending …

… vanishing …

… fading away …

… cessation …

… letting go …”

AN 11.30–69 Untitled Discourses on the Ear, Etc. ~

… “… ear … nose … tongue … body … mind …”

AN 11.70–117 Untitled Discourses on Sights, Etc. ~

… “… sights … sounds … smells … tastes … touches … ideas …”

AN 11.118–165 Untitled Discourses on Eye Consciousness, Etc. ~

… “… eye consciousness … ear consciousness … nose consciousness … tongue consciousness … body consciousness … mind consciousness. …”

AN 11.166–213 Untitled Discourses on Eye Contact, Etc. ~

… “… eye contact … ear contact … nose contact … tongue contact … body contact … mind contact. …”

AN 11.214–261 Untitled Discourses on Feeling Born of Eye Contact, Etc. ~

… “… feeling born of eye contact … feeling born of ear contact … feeling born of nose contact … feeling born of tongue contact … feeling born of body contact … feeling born of mind contact …”

AN 11.262–309 Untitled Discourses on Perception of Sights, Etc. ~

… “… perception of sights … perception of sounds … perception of smells … perception of tastes … perception of touches … perception of ideas. …”

AN 11.310–357 Untitled Discourses on Intention Regarding Sights, Etc. ~

… “… intention regarding sights … intention regarding sounds … intention regarding smells … intention regarding tastes … intention regarding touches … intention regarding ideas. …”

AN 11.358–405 Untitled Discourses on Craving For Sights, Etc. ~

… “… craving for sights … craving for sounds … craving for smells … craving for tastes … craving for touches … craving for ideas. …”

AN 11.406–453 Untitled Discourses on Thoughts About Sights, Etc. ~

… “… thoughts about sights … thoughts about sounds … thoughts about smells … thoughts about tastes … thoughts about touches … thoughts about ideas. …”

AN 11.454–501 Untitled Discourses on Considerations Regarding Sights, Etc. ~

… “… considerations regarding sights … considerations regarding sounds … considerations regarding smells … considerations regarding tastes … considerations regarding touches … meditate observing impermanence in considerations about ideas … meditate observing suffering … meditate observing not-self … meditate observing ending … meditate observing vanishing … meditate observing fading away … meditate observing cessation … meditate observing letting go. …”

AN 11.502–981 Untitled Discourses on the Eye, Etc. ~

“Mendicants, a cowherd with eleven factors can maintain and expand a herd of cattle. What eleven? It’s when a cowherd knows form …

In the same way, a mendicant with eleven qualities can meditate observing impermanence in the eye … meditate observing letting go. …”

Acknowledgements

I remember with gratitude all those from whom I have learned the Dhamma, especially Ajahn Brahm and Bhikkhu Bodhi, the two monks who more than anyone else showed me the depth, meaning, and practical value of the Suttas.

Special thanks to Dustin and Keiko Cheah and family, who sponsored my stay in Qi Mei while I made this translation.

Thanks also for Blake Walshe, who provided essential software support for my translation work.

Throughout the process of translation, I have frequently sought feedback and suggestions from the SuttaCentral community on our forum, “Discuss and Discover”. I want to thank all those who have made suggestions and contributed to my understanding, as well as to the moderators who have made the forum possible. These translations were significantly improved due to the careful work of my proofreaders: Ayyā Pāsādā, John and Lynn Kelly, and Derek Sola. Special thanks are due to Sabbamittā, a true friend of all, who has tirelessly and precisely checked my work.

Finally my everlasting thanks to all those people, far too many to mention, who have supported SuttaCentral, and those who have supported my life as a monastic. None of this would be possible without you.